"lang"
{
"Language""english"
"Tokens"
{
//Neccessities
"CaptionMod_GameSaved"		"Game Saved..."
"HalfLife_Hologram"			"[Hologram] "
"HalfLife_Scientist"		"[Scientist] "
"HalfLife_HEV_Voice"		"[HEV] "
"HalfLife_VOX"		"[Announcer] "
"HalfLife_HECU"		"[HECU] "
"HalfLife_Radio"		"[Radio] "
"HalfLife_Security"	"[Security Officer] "
"HalfLife_Train"		"[Train] "
"HalfLife_Nihilanth"	"[Nihilanth] "

//Messages
"GAMETITLE"	"Half-Life"
"CR27"	"Black Mesa Research Facility\nBlack Mesa, New Mexico"
"CR28"	"SUBJECT:\nGordon Freeman\nMale, age 27"
"CR29"	"EDUCATION:\nPh.D., MIT, Theoretical Physics"
"CR30"	"POSITION:\nResearch Associate"
"CR31"	"ASSIGNMENT:\nAnomalous Materials Laboratory"
"CR32"	"CLEARANCE:\nLevel 3"
"CR33"	"ADMINISTRATIVE SPONSOR:\nClassified"
"CR34"	"DISASTER RESPONSE PRIORITY:\nDiscretionary"
"GAMEOVER"	"SUBJECT:  FREEMAN\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubject failed to effectively utilize\nhuman assets in achievement of goal."
"TRAITOR"	"SUBJECT:  FREEMAN\n\nSTATUS:  HIRED\n\nAWAITING ASSIGNMENT"
"LOSER"	"SUBJECT:  FREEMAN\n\nSTATUS:  OBSERVATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubject declined offer of employment."
"T0A0TITLE"	"HAZARD COURSE"
"C0A0TITLE"	"BLACK MESA INBOUND"
"C0A1TITLE"	"ANOMALOUS MATERIALS"
"C1A1TITLE"	"UNFORESEEN CONSEQUENCES"
"C1A2TITLE"	"OFFICE COMPLEX"
"C1A3TITLE"	"\"WE'VE GOT HOSTILES\""
"C1A4TITLE"	"BLAST PIT"
"C2A1TITLE"	"POWER UP"
"C2A2TITLE"	"ON A RAIL"
"C2A3TITLE"	"APPREHENSION"
"C2A4TITLE1"	"RESIDUE PROCESSING"
"C2A4TITLE2"	"QUESTIONABLE ETHICS"
"C2A5TITLE"	"SURFACE TENSION"
"C3A1TITLE"	"\"FORGET ABOUT FREEMAN!\""
"C3A2TITLE"	"LAMBDA CORE"
"C4A1TITLE"	"XEN"
"C4A1ATITLE"	"INTERLOPER"
"C4A2TITLE"	"GONARCH'S LAIR"
"C4A3TITLE"	"NIHILANTH"
"C5TITLE"	"ENDGAME"
"HZBUTTON1"	"PRESS YOUR USE KEY TO PUSH A BUTTON"
"HZBUTTON2"	"PRESS YOUR USE KEY TO PUSH A BUTTON"
"HZMOVE"	"MOVE FORWARD BY PRESSING FORWARD KEY\nMOVE BACKWARD BY PRESSING BACKWARD KEY\nMOVE LEFT BY PRESSING MOVELEFT\nMOVE RIGHT BY PRESSING MOVERIGHT"
"HZJUMP"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO RUN FORWARD\nPRESS JUMP KEY TO JUMP"
"HZDUCK"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO RUN FORWARD\nPRESS DUCK KEY TO DUCK\nPRESS FORWARD + DUCK KEYS TOGETHER\nTO MOVE IN STEALTH MODE"
"HZCOMBO"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO RUN FORWARD\nPRESS JUMP KEY TO JUMP\nPRESS DUCK KEY TO DUCK\nPRESS JUMP KEY TO JUMP"
"HZDUCKJUMP"	"PRESS FORWARD + JUMP TOGETHER,\nTHEN THE DUCK KEY"
"HZLADDER"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO MOVE UP LADDERS\nPRESS BACKWARD KEY TO MOVE DOWN LADDERS"
"HZLJUMP"	"WHILE MOVING FORWARD,\nHOLD DOWN DUCK KEY--\nTHEN PRESS JUMP"
"HZLMOD"	"BE SURE YOU PICKED UP THE LONG-JUMP MODULE\nAT THE BEGINNING OF THE OBSTACLE"
"HZMEDKIT"	"USE MED-KITS BY HOLDING DOWN THE USE KEY\nHOLD DOWN USE KEY UNTIL HEALTH IS\nAT 100 OR KIT IS DEPLETED"
"HZMOMENT"	"ACTIVATE WHEELS AND DIALS\nBY HOLDING DOWN THE USE KEY\nHOLD USE KEY UNTIL BRIDGE IS IN POSITION"
"HZPUSH"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO MOVE AGAINST BOX\nKEEP PRESSING FORWARD TO PUSH BOX"
"HZPULL"	"PRESS USE + BACKWARD KEYS TOGETHER\nTO PULL BOX BACKWARD"
"HZCROWBAR"	"MOVE UP TO CROWBAR\nPRESS ATTACK1 KEY TO BREAK OBJECTS"
"HZLITEON"	"PRESS FLASHLIGHT KEY\nTO TURN FLASHLIGHT ON"
"HZLITEOFF"	"PRESS FLASHLIGHT KEY AGAIN\nTO TURN FLASHLIGHT OFF"
"HZWEAPON"	"MOVE UP TO WEAPON TO PICK IT UP"
"HZFIREWEAP"	"PRESS ATTACK1 KEY FOR PRIMARY ATTACK\nPRESS ATTACK2 KEY FOR ALTERNATE ATTACK\nPRESS RELOAD KEY TO RELOAD AT WILL"
"HZARMOR"	"PRESS AND HOLD YOUR USE KEY\nHOLD DOWN UNTIL SUIT ARMOR IS CHARGED\nOR CHARGER IS DEPLETED"
"HZSWIM"	"PRESS YOUR FORWARD KEY\nAIM WITH THE MOUSE AS YOU SWIM\nFIND AIR IF YOU BEGIN TO LOSE HEALTH\nWAIT IN THE AIR UNTIL HEALTH \nRETURNS TO FORMER LEVEL"
"HZDAMAGE"	"CERTAIN TYPES OF DAMAGE WILL REGISTER\nON YOUR HEADS-UP DISPLAY.\nDIRECTION OF DAMAGE IS INDICATED BY RED\nFLASHES IN THE CENTER OF YOUR SCREEN"
"HZHAZARD"	"RADIATION HAZARDS\nACTIVATE A GEIGER COUNTER"
"HZSCIENTIST"	"APPROACH SCIENTIST\nPRESS USE KEY TO RECEIVE HEALTH FROM SCIENTIST"
"HZBARNEY"	"APPROACH SECURITY GUARD\nPRESS YOUR USE KEY TO GET HIS HELP\nWALK TOWARD DOOR AND GUARD\nWILL ACTIVATE BUTTONS"
"HZTRAIN"	"PRESS USE KEY TO ENGAGE TRAIN\nPRESS FORWARD KEY TO ACCELERATE\nPRESS BACKWARD KEY TO DECELERATE\nPRESS USE KEY AGAIN TO DISENGAGE"
"HZDONE"	"CONGRATULATIONS!\nYOU HAVE COMPLETED \nTHE BLACK MESA HAZARD COURSE.\nCOME BACK ANY TIME."
"DEMOTITLE"	"UPLINK"
"DEMOTXT1"	"SUBJECT:\nGORDON FREEMAN, Ph.D."
"DEMOTXT2"	"CURRENT LOCATION:\nLAMBDA REACTOR COMPLEX\nBLACK MESA RESEARCH FACILITY"
"DEMOTXT3"	"TIME:\nCONTAINMENT FAILURE + 48.00 HRS"
"DEMOTXT4"	"STATUS:\nEVALUATION IN PROGRESS"
"DEMOTXT6"	"CURRENT EVALUATION:\nUPLINK COMPLETED."
"DEMOTXT7"	"REQUIRE FURTHER DATA."


//Vox
"C1A0_0"	"Agent Coomer, report to Topside Tactical Operations Center."
"C1A0_1"	"Inspection team to Radioactive Materials Handling Bay."
"C1A0_2"	"Agent 16, report to Administration Sub-Level 2."
"C1A0_3"	"Dr. Johnson, please call Observation Tank 1."
"C1A0_4"	"Dr. West, please report to Lambda Reactor Complex."
"C1A0_5"	"Dr. Cross, call 729 please."
"C1A0_6"	"Sergeant Bailey to Topside Checkpoint Bravo."
"C1A0_7"	"Cryogenic Safety Crew, report status at 11:00 please."
"C1A0_8"	"Coded message for Captain Black, Command and Communication Center."
"C1A0_9"	"Sector C science personnel, report to Anomalous Materials test laboratory."
"C1A0_10"	"Dr. Freeman to Anomalous Materials test laboratory immediately."
"C1A0_11"	"Attention. Experimental Propulsion Laboratory test fire in 90 minutes."
"C1A0_12"	"Hydro Plant now operating at 60%."
"C1A0_13"	"Black Mesa topside temperature is 93 degrees."
"C1A0_14"	"Launch officer reports Alpha Satellite deploy is nominal."
"C1A0_15"	"Dr. Birdwell reports superconducting interchange is activated."
"C1A0_16"	"Attention. Report any security violation to Administration Sub-Level 1."
"C1A0_17"	"Attention. Service personnel, please clear Helicopter Hangar 1."
"C1A0_18"	"Shield Inspection Crew reports primary reactor nominal."
"C1A0_19"	"Transportation Control reports all systems on time."
"C1A0_20"	"Dr. Victor, report to Supercooled Laser Laboratory please."
"C1A0_21"	"Sergeant Guthrie, report to Topside Motorpool immediately."
"C1A0_22"	"Uranium Shipment Inspection Team to Sector D."
"C1A1_0"	"Warning. High energy detonation detected in Materials Laboratory."
"C1A1_1"	"Attention. Security personnel to Sector C immediately."
"C1A1_2"	"Warning. Unauthorized biological forms detected in Sector C."
"C1A1_3"	"Warning. Unauthorized biological forms detected in Coolant Maintenance Area."
"C1A1_4"	"Any Damage Control Team to Sector C immediately."
"C1A1_5"	"Warning. Sector C elevator failure. Do not use."
"C1A1_6"	"Biohazard warning in Sector B and C."
"C1A1_7"	"Attention. Sector C science personnel, evacuate area immediately."
"C1A1_8"	"Warning. Flooding detected on Sub-Level 3, Sector B."
"C1A1_9"	"Warning. Anomalous energy field detected in Administration Center."
"C1A1_10"	"Attention. Any Sector C science personnel, please report status."
"C1A1_11"	"Attention. Sector C science personnel, please report status immediately."
"C1A3_0"	"Attention. All science personnel, report topside for immediate questioning."
"C1A3_1"	"All personnel evacuate High Security Materials Storage Facility."
"C1A3_2"	"Emergency Uranium Containment Team to Sector D."
"C1A3_3"	"Turret maintenance team to Central Command and Communication Center."
"C1A3_4"	"Military personnel, prosecute Kilo-India-Lima with extreme force."
"C1A3_5"	"Attention. This announcement system now under military command."
"C1A3_6"	"Search and Destroy Force Bravo reports secondary objective terminated."
"C1A3_7"	"Bravo Force reports Hotel-Sierra-Mike facility is secured."
"C1A3_8"	"Attention. All military personnel, atomic biological chemical alert."
"C1A3_9"	"Attention. All military personnel, extreme atomic biological chemical alert."
"C1A3_10"	"Attention. Black Mesa Announcement System now under military command."
"C1A3_warn"	"Attention. Security lockout alert. Security door will engage."
"C1A3_lock	"	"Security door engaged. Five. Four. Three. Two. One. Lockout activated."
"POWER_OFF"	"Main power is not on."
"C3A1_8"	"All personnel evacuate Lambda Complex, extreme dimensional malfunction detected."
"C3A2_0"	"Warning. Cross-dimensional power field activity detected."
"C3A2_1"	"Warning. Unauthorized biological force detected in cross-dimensional power field."
"C3A2_2"	"All personnel evacuate Lambda Complex, extreme dimensional malfunction detected."
"C3A2_3"	"Unauthorized activity detected in Main Reactor Core."
"C3A2_4"	"Danger. High energy exchange detected in Radioactive Materials Handling Bay."
"C3A2_5"	"Biological force detected in Primary Coolant System."
"C3A2_6"	"Lambda Complex reports dimensional contamination."
"C3A2_7"	"Lambda Complex reports dimensional containment system failure."
"DC0"	"Danger. Chemical leak. Area now a high health hazard."
"DC1"	"Danger. Chemical coolant leak. Health hazard zone."
"DC2"	"Danger. Chemical containment breach. All personnel evacuate this area."
"DC3"	"Supercooled chemical leak."
"DC4"	"Danger. Supercooled helium leak."
"DR0"	"Danger. Radiation leak detected."
"DR1"	"Danger. Radiation hazard detected."
"DR2"	"Danger. High radiation level detected."
"DR3"	"Danger. Severe radiation hazard. Evacuate area immediately."
"DR4"	"Danger. Safety violation. Extreme radiation level detected."
"NA0"	"Access denied."
"NA1"	"Access is denied."
"NA2"	"Unauthorized access."
"NA3"	"Illegal access."
"NA4"	"This door is locked."
"NA5"	"Unauthorized access."
"NA6"	"Entry forbidden."
"NA7"	"Entry not permitted."
"NA8"	"No unauthorized personnel."
"NA9"	"You do not have access to this facility."
"NA10"	"Sorry, you may not enter."
"NA11"	"Sorry, this door is locked."
"NA12"	"Please, move away from this area."
"NA13"	"Please, move away from door."
"NA14"	"You will not get in."
"NA15"	"Entry is not an option."
"NA16"	"Will we do this all day?"
"NA17"	"Move on immediately."
"NA18"	"No, no, and no."
"NF0"	"Emergency blast door activated."
"NF1"	"Emergency blast shield activated."
"NG0"	"Sorry, this door is inoperative."
"NG1"	"Sorry, door out of service."
"NG2"	"Door damage detected. Please call service personnel."
"NFIRE0"	"Fire containment door is down"
"NCON0"	"Emergency containment door engaged."

//H.E.V
"HEV_AAx"	"Welcome to the HEV Mark 4 Protective System, for use in hazardous environment conditions.\nHigh-impact reactive armor activated.\nAtmospheric contaminant sensors activated.\nVital signs monitoring activated.\nAutomatic medical systems engaged.\nDefensive weapon selection system activated.\nMunition level monitoring activated.\nCommunications interface online.\nHave a very safe day."
"HEV_A0"	"Welcome to the HEV Mark 4 Protective System, for use in hazardous environment conditions."
"HEV_A1"	"Power-assist movement activated."
"HEV_A2"	"High-impact reactive armor activated."
"HEV_A3"	"Atmospheric contaminant sensors activated."
"HEV_A4"	"Vital signs monitoring activated."
"HEV_A8"	"Automatic medical systems engaged."
"HEV_A7"	"Defensive weapon selection system activated."
"HEV_A5"	"Munition level monitoring activated."
"HEV_A6"	"Communications interface online."
"HEV_A10"	"Have a very safe day."
"HEV_HLTH1"	"Vital signs are dropping."
"HEV_HLTH2"	"Warning: Vital signs critical."
"HEV_HLTH3"	"Emergency. User death imminent."
"HEV_HLTH4"	"Vital signs are dropping. Evacuate area."
"HEV_HLTH5"	"Warning: Vital signs critical. Evacuate area."
"HEV_HLTH6"	"Warning: Vital signs critical. Evacuate area immediately."
"HEV_DMG7"	"Seek medical attention."
"HEV_SHOCK"	"Warning: Electrical damage detected."
"HEV_FIRE"	"Warning: Extreme heat damage detected."
"HEV_DMG3"	"Warning: Blood toxin levels detected."
"HEV_DMG0"	"Minor lacerations detected."
"HEV_DMG1"	"Major lacerations detected."
"HEV_DMG4"	"Minor fracture detected."
"HEV_DMG5"	"Major fracture detected."
"HEV_DMG6"	"Blood loss detected."
"HEV_DMG2"	"Internal bleeding detected."
"HEV_HEAL7"	"Morphine administered."
"HEV_DET2"	"Warning: Hazardous radiation levels detected."
"HEV_DET1"	"Warning: Hazardous chemical detected."
"HEV_DET0"	"Warning: Biohazard detected."
"HEV_0P"	"Warning: HEV power level below # percent."
"HEV_1P"	"Power: 10%"
"HEV_2P"	"Power: 15%"
"HEV_3P"	"Power: 20%"
"HEV_4P"	"Power: 25%"
"HEV_5P"	"Power: 30%"
"HEV_6P"	"Power: 35%"
"HEV_7P"	"Power: 40%"
"HEV_8P"	"Power: 45%"
"HEV_9P"	"Power: 50%"
"HEV_10P"	"Power: 55%"
"HEV_11P"	"Power: 60%"
"HEV_12P"	"Power: 65%"
"HEV_13P"	"Power: 70%"
"HEV_14P"	"Power: 75%"
"HEV_15P"	"Power: 80%"
"HEV_16P"	"Power: 85%"
"HEV_17P"	"Power: 90%"
"HEV_18P"	"Power: 95%"
"HEV_19P"	"Power level is one hundred percent."
"HEV_AMO0"	"Ammunition depleted."
"HEV_MED1"	"Automatic medical systems engaged."


//Hazard Course
"tr_sci_goodwork"	"Good work! Those new suits can be tricky. Please proceed to the next area."
"tr_sci_hardlynoticed"	"Very good! I hardly noticed you. Move on to the next area."
"tr_sci_nextstation"	"Good work! You look prepared for the next station."
"tr_sci_use"	"Yes. I will follow you, if you wish."
"tr_sci_unuse"	"Okay. I will wait here."
"tr_ba_use"	"Sure! I'll follow you."
"tr_ba_unuse"	"OK, I'll wait here."

//Scientist
"absolutely"	"Absolutely."
"absolutelynot"	"Absolutely not."
"administrator"	"I suspected this could happen but the Administrator just would not listen."
"afellowsci"	"A fellow scientist."
"ahfreeman"	"Ah, Freeman."
"alienapeal"	"Do you think we should appeal to the alien authorities?"
"alientrick"	"Do you suspect some alien subterfuge behind this failure?"
"allnominal"	"Yes, this all looks nominal."
"alright"	"Alright."
"analysis"	"I am rather looking forward to this analysis, aren't you?"
"announcer"	"Did you understand that last announcement?"
"areyouthink"	"Are you thinking what I'm thinking?"
"asexpected"	"As I expected."
"beenaburden"	"Have I been that much of a burden?"
"beverage"	"Have you been able to get the beverage machine to work yet?"
"bloodsample"	"Wouldn't you like to get one of these blood samples under a microscope?"
"c1a0_sci_bigday"	"Big day today, Freeman."
"c1a0_sci_crit1a"	"Quick! It's about to go critical!"
"c1a0_sci_crit2a"	"What the hell is going on with our equipment?"
"c1a0_sci_crit3a"	"It wasn't meant to do this in the first place!"
"c1a0_sci_ctrl1a"	"Ah, Gordon, here you are. We just sent the sample down to the Test Chamber."
"c1a0_sci_ctrl2a"	"We've boosted the Anti-Mass Spectrometer to 105 percent. Bit of a gamble, but we need the extra resolution."
"c1a0_sci_ctrl3a"	"The Administrator is very concerned that we get a conclusive analysis of today's sample. I gather they went to some lengths to get it."
"c1a0_sci_ctrl4a"	"They're waiting for you, Gordon. In the Test Chamber."
"c1a0_sci_dis1a"	"All right, Gordon, your suit should keep you comfortable through all this. The specimen will be delivered to you in a few moments. If you would be so good as to climb up and start the rotors, we can bring the Anti-Mass Spectrometer to eighty percent and hold it there until the carrier arrives."
"c1a0_sci_dis1b"	"Gordon, are you not hearing me? Climb up and start the rotors, please."
"c1a0_sci_dis1c"	"Climb up and start the rotors."
"c1a0_sci_dis1d"	"Very good. We'll take it from here."
"c1a0_sci_dis2a"	"Power to stage one emitters in three... two... one..."
"c1a0_sci_dis3a"	"I'm seeing predictable phase arrays."
"c1a0_sci_dis5a"	"Stage two emitters activating... now."
"c1a0_sci_dis6a"	"I have just been informed that the sample is ready, Gordon. It should be coming up to you any moment now. Look to the delivery system for your specimen."
"c1a0_sci_dis7a"	"Standard insertion for a nonstandard specimen. Go ahead, Gordon. Slot the carrier into the analysis port."
"c1a0_sci_dis9a"	"Overhead capacitors to one oh five percent."
"c1a0_sci_dis10a"	"Gordon, we cannot predict how long the system can operate at this level, nor how long the reading will take. Please work as quickly as you can."
"c1a0_sci_dis11a"	"Uh... it's probably not a problem... probably... but I'm showing a small discrepancy in... well, no, it's well within acceptable bounds again. Sustaining sequence."
"c1a0_sci_dis12a"	"Nothing you need to worry about, Gordon. Go ahead."
"c1a0_sci_dis13a"	"Wha-what's he doing in there?"
"c1a0_sci_dis14a"	"Get him out of there! Shut down the equipment and someone get him out!"
"c1a0_sci_dis15a"	"Shutting down. Attempting shut down. It's not... it's-it's not... it's not shutting down... it's not..."
"c1a0_sci_dis16a"	"Gordon! Get away from the beams!"
"c1a0_sci_disa"	"Testing... testing... Everything seems to be in order."
"c1a0_sci_getaway"	"Get away from there, Freeman! I'm expecting an important message!"
"c1a0_sci_gm"	"Good morning, Gordon."
"c1a0_sci_gm1"	"Good morning, Gordon."
"c1a0_sci_lock1a"	"I'm afraid we'll be deviating a bit from standard analysis procedures today, Gordon."
"c1a0_sci_lock2a"	"Yes, but with good reason. This is a rare opportunity for us. This is the purest sample we've seen yet."
"c1a0_sci_lock3a"	"And potentially the most unstable!"
"c1a0_sci_lock4a"	"Now, now, if you follow standard insertion procedures, everything will be fine."
"c1a0_sci_lock5a"	"I don't know how you can say that. Although I will admit that the possibility of a resonance cascade scenario is extremely unlikely..."
"c1a0_sci_lock6a"	"Gordon doesn't need to hear all this. He's a highly trained professional. We have assured the Administrator that nothing will go wrong."
"c1a0_sci_lock7a"	"Ah yes, you're right. Gordon, we have complete confidence in you."
"c1a0_sci_lock8a"	"Well, go ahead. Let's let him in now"
"c1a0_sci_samp"	"The sample was just delivered to the test chamber."
"c1a0_sci_stayback"	"No, stay back! Gordon!"
"c1a1_sci_1scan"	"Why didn't they listen!"
"c1a1_sci_2scan"	"We tried to warn them."
"c1a1_sci_3scan"	"I never thought I'd see a Resonance Cascade, let alone create one."
"c1a1_sci_4scan"	"Gordon, you're alive! Thank God for that hazard suit. I'm afraid to move him, and all our phones are out. Please, get to the surface as soon as you can, and let someone know we're stranded down here. You'll need me to activate the retinal scanners. I'm sure the rest of the science team will gladly help you."
"c1a2_sci_dangling"	"I... I can't hold on much... longer..."
"c1a2_sci_darkroom"	"I'm not so sure I want to get to the surface. What if the world finds out what we were doing down here?"
"c1a2_sci_lounge"	"Gordon! If I'd known it was you, I'd have let you in! Everyone's heading for the surface, but I think they're crazy not to stay put. Someone is bound to come by and rescue us."
"c1a2_sci_transm"	"I just overheard a secure access transmission... soldiers have arrived and they're coming to rescue us. Of course, I have my doubts that we'll live long enough to greet them."
"c1a3_sci_1man"	"Take me with you! I'm the one man who knows everything!"
"c1a3_sci_rescued"	"Rescued at last! Thank God you're here!"
"c1a3_sci_silo1a"	"For God's sake, open the silo door! They're coming for us; it's our only way out!"
"c1a3_sci_silo2a"	"Oh my God... we're doomed!"
"c1a3_sci_team"	"Don't shoot! I'm with the science team!"
"c1a4_sci_gener"	"This is my hiding spot, and I'm not moving until the situation is drastically improved. Now go away and don't tell anyone I'm here."
"c1a4_sci_pwr"	"Excellent! Someone has restored all power! We'll have the engine up again in no time!"
"c1a4_sci_pwroff"	"I hope no one expects me to start up the generator. Smithers went down there and never came back."
"c1a4_sci_rocket"	"Fire the... rocket engine. Destroy the damned thing before it grows any larger!"
"c1a4_sci_tent"	"No... No! No! Get it off me! Get it off! Get it off!"
"c1a4_sci_trust"	"Well, so much for the government. Their idea of containment is to kill everyone associated with the project! Judging from your hazard suit, I'd say you were part of what went wrong—isn't that right? Now look... if anyone can end this catastrophe, it's the science team in the Lambda Complex, at the opposite end of the base. With the transit system out, I couldn't tell you how to get there. But there's an old decommissioned rail system somewhere through here—beyond the silo complex. If you can make it through the rocket test labs, you might be able to worm your way through the old tunnels to track down whatever's left of the Lambda team. You can trust them. You can trust all of us. Good luck."
"c2a3_sci_icky"	"Did you see it? They said it was hauled from the Challenger Deep, but I'm positive that beast never swam in terrestrial waters until a week ago. There's a tranquilizer gun in the shark cage, but I'm not sure it would work on this species. You're welcome to try."
"c2a3_sci_track"	"Gordon Freeman—it is you, isn't it? The science team has been tracking your progress with the Black Mesa security system. Unfortunately, so has the military. That suit of yours is full of tracking devices. Still, it's better than going naked in this place. It's cold in there and you'll have to hurry. It could sap your suit power in a matter of moments. If you're bent on reaching the Lambda complex, then you'll want to keep to the older industrial areas, where the security system is full of holes. It's worked for me so far."
"c2a4_sci_2tau"	"Put that down—it's a prototype."
"c2a4_sci_4tau"	"It's much too unpredictable. Don't let it overcharge!"
"c2a4_sci_letout"	"Well, I'll let you out, but I'm warning you... it's hell out there. It's completely under military control. You'll have to sneak and fight your way from one end to the other, and I don't expect you'll meet many of our peers along the way. But if you do survive and somehow make it across the base, you'll end up at the Lambda Complex, where the rest of the science team has taken shelter. I wouldn't venture there myself, but I will let them know that you are coming."
"c2a4_sci_scanner"	"We all have retinal scanner access. Escort us to the lobby, and we can get out of the lab."
"c2a4_sci_sugicaloff"	"You'll have to shut down the surgical unit first. Peters switched it on but I'm afraid he never made it back."
"c2a4_sci_surgury"	"A scientist, thank God! Get us out of here before those military drones figure out where we're hiding!"
"c2a5_sci_boobie"	"You're heading for the Lambda Complex, aren't you? I was heading there myself, until I wound up here and... well, simply lost my nerve. Take one look through that door and you'll see what I mean. I'm just going to wait out the catastrophe in here. If you intend to go on, then I beg of you... proceed with extreme caution."
"c3a2_sci_1surv"	"Gordon Freeman! You finally found us!"
"c3a2_sci_2glu"	"Were you in weapons research, too? I built the Gluon Gun, but I just can't bring myself to use it on a living creature. You don't look as if you have any trouble killing things."
"c3a2_sci_3surv"	"This is the supply depot for our first survey team. Quite a few handsome specimens were collected from the borderworld and brought back this way—uhh, before the survey members started being collected themselves, that is. We suspect there is an immense portal over there, created by the intense concentration of a single powerful being. You will know it when you see it. I hate to say this, Gordon, but you must kill it, if you can."
"c3a2_sci_5surv"	"Of course, you owe us nothing, Mr. Freeman. But you've come this far. You know as much about these creatures as anyone."
"c3a2_sci_7surv"	"Yes. So... if you're willing, my colleague is waiting for you at the main portal controls. He will open the gates for you, Mr. Freeman. Do hurry."
"c3a2_sci_flood"	"Freeman, isn't it? You'll need to activate both pumps to flood the reactor, and then that access pipe down there will take you to the core. Time is short!"
"c3a2_sci_fool"	"Freeman, you fool!"
"c3a2_sci_forever"	"Hurry up, Freeman, I can't keep it open forever!"
"c3a2_sci_linger"	"Don't linger, Mr. Freeman! You've turned on the pumps. Now take the access pipe, flood the core, and get on up to the labs without delay!"
"c3a2_sci_ljump"	"This, Mr. Freeman, is a Long Jump Module, created expressly for navigation in the world beyond. I certainly hope you received Long-Jump Training, because once you're in Xen, you will need it. I would advise you to practice before crossing over."
"c3a2_sci_notyet"	"Not yet, Freeman!"
"c3a2_sci_portal"	"All right, I can open the portal now. The process is complicated, and once it's begun I must not be interrupted or I will have to start all over again. Don't enter the beam until I give the okay, understood? I will begin."
"c3a2_sci_portopen"	"It's ready! You must go! Now!"
"c3a2_sci_position"	"We're almost there, Freeman. Get yourself in position."
"c3a2_sci_straws"	"I apologize, Mr. Freeman, but I couldn't risk opening that door until I was sure you'd scoured the area. This is the last entrance to the Lambda Complex—every other has been sealed off to contain the invasion. When we realized that you might actually make it here, we drew straws to see who should stay behind to let you through. Obviously, I drew the short one. My colleagues are waiting at the tip of the Lambda reactor... waiting for you, I mean. The reactor is shut down right now, but you can activate it on your way up. You'll have to flood the core anyway to get into the teleportation labs. You're not authorized to know about those... but I can see you already know a great deal more than any one man is supposed to."
"c3a2_sci_uphere"	"Hello, Freeman—I'm up here. Practice your Long-Jump if you must, but hurry up!"
"cantbeserious"	"You can't be serious."
"cantbeworse"	"It can't get any worse than this."
"canttakemore"	"I can't take much more of this."
"cascade"	"Aren't you a bit worried about that exponential cascade scenario we discussed?"
"catchone"	"Shouldn't we try to capture a specimen?"
"chaostheory"	"Do you still say there's nothing to chaos theory?"
"checkatten"	"Are you sure you checked the Eigen attenuators?"
"completelywrong"	"You are completely wrong."
"containfail"	"It appears the containment system has completely failed."
"correcttheory"	"Are you one hundred percent sure that theory of yours is correct?"
"delayagain"	"Do you think we should delay for another recalibration?"
"didyouhear"	"Did you hear that?"
"dinner"	"Are you seriously suggesting that all of these beings are here to dine on us?"
"dontconcur"	"I don't concur."
"dontgothere"	"No, don't go that way!"
"dontknow"	"I really don't know."
"dontwantdie"	"No, I don't want to die!"
"donuteater"	"Do you know who ate all the donuts?"
"doyousmell"	"Do you smell what I smell?"
"evergetout"	"Will we ever make it out of here?"
"erseen"	"Have you ever seen anything like this?"
"excellentteam"	"With my brains and your brawn we'll make an excellent team."
"excuse"	"Excuse me, Gordon."
"fascinating"	"Don't you find this all rather fascinating?"
"fellowscientist"	"Glad to oblige a fellow scientist."
"fine"	"Fine. You won't even know I'm here."
"freeman"	"Freeman."
"freemanalive"	"Freeman! Who would have thought you'd still be alive?"
"fusionshunt"	"I certainly hope those backup fusion shunts are in good shape today."
"getoutalive"	"I just want to get out of this alive."
"getoutofhere"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"goodpaper"	"I believe this will make for a notable paper, don't you?"
"goodtoseeyou"	"Ah, it's good to see you."
"gottogetout"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"greetings"	"Greetings!"
"greetings2"	"Greetings."
"headcrab"	"These crab creatures have a unique parasitic strategy, don't you think?"
"heal1"	"Let me take care of that wound for you."
"heal2"	"This should make you feel better."
"heal3"	"Allow me to treat that injury."
"heal4"	"I can give you something for the pain."
"heal5"	"Don't worry, I am a doctor."
"scientisthearsomething"	"Did you hear something?" //tag
"hello"	"Hello."
"hello2"	"Hello."
"hellofreeman"	"Ah, hello, Gordon Freeman. It's good to see you."
"hellofromlab"	"You are from the Anomalous Materials Lab. Yes, I recognize you."
"hellothere"	"Hello there."
"hideglasses"	"Someone has hidden my glasses again."
"holdstill"	"Hold still, this won't hurt a bit."
"hopenominal"	"I hope those containment parameters are still nominal."
"hopeyouknow"	"I certainly hope you know what you're doing."
"howinteresting"	"How interesting, just look at that."
"hungryyet"	"Is anyone else getting hungry?"
"ibelieveso"	"I believe so."
"idontthinkso"	"I don't think so."
"ihearsomething"	"I hear something."
"scientistillwait"	"I'll wait." //tag
"illwaithere"	"I'll wait right here."
"importantspecies"	"Another important species revealed in action."
"improbable"	"A failure of this magnitude is extremely improbable."
"imsure"	"I'm sure of it."
"inconclusive"	"It's inconclusive."
"inmesstoo"	"Ah, Freeman. I see you are in this mess too."
"ipredictedthis"	"I predicted all of this, you know. All of it!"
"istay"	"I'll stay here."
"iwounded"	"I seem to be wounded... but I can keep going."
"iwounded2"	"Well, I seem to be seriously wounded."
"iwoundedbad"	"I don't think I can last much longer."
"justasked"	"Didn't you just ask me that?"
"lambdalab"	"I hope those people in the Lambda Lab can get this under control."
"leadtheway"	"Lead the way."
"leavingme"	"What? You're leaving me here?"
"letmehelp"	"Let me help you."
"scientistletsgo"	"Let's go." //tag
"letstrythis"	"Let's try this."
"letyouin"	"Wait a minute and I'll let you in."
"limitsok"	"This is all within theoretical limits."
"lowervoice"	"Kindly lower your voice."
"luckwillchange"	"It's highly probable that our luck will change, don't you agree?"
"madness"	"This is madness! I'm getting out of here!"
"needsleep"	"I'd give my right hemisphere for a few hours of sleep."
"neverseen"	"Fascinating. I never suspected such things could be."
"newhevsuit"	"Ah, you have one of the new HEV suits. That should be very useful."
"newsample"	"Any ideas on the origin of that new sample?"
"nodoubt"	"I have no doubt."
"nogrant"	"Well, there goes our grant money."
"noguess"	"I couldn't even venture a guess."
"noidea"	"You have no idea what is going on, do you?"
"noo"	"No."
"nooo"	"No!"
"noplease"	"No! Please!"
"notcertain"	"I'm not certain."
"nothostile"	"The alien species can't possibly all be hostile, can they?"
"notsure"	"I am not at all sure."
"odorfromyou"	"I hope that odor isn't coming from you."
"ofcourse"	"Of course!"
"ofcoursenot"	"Of course not!"
"okgetout"	"Okay, let's get out of here."
"okihope"	"Okay, I hope you know what you're doing."
"organicmatter"	"Well, the dimensional breach is definitely transmitting organic matter."
"peculiarmarks"	"Why just look at those peculiar markings."
"peculiarodor"	"Hm, what a peculiar odor."
"perfectday"	"This analysis is going to run perfectly today, don't you think?"
"perhaps"	"Perhaps."
"positively"	"Positively."
"purereadings"	"Wouldn't it be fantastic to get some pure readings for a change?"
"recalculate"	"Don't you think we should recalculate those resonance dampening factors again?"
"reconsider"	"I don't suppose you'd reconsider?"
"repeat"	"You know, you repeat yourself sometimes."
"reportflux"	"I must remember to report that fluctuation."
"rescueus"	"Surely someone will come and rescue us."
"ridiculous"	"Don't be ridiculous!"
"right"	"Right!"
"rightwayout"	"Are you sure this is the right way?"
"rumorclean"	"The military cleanup is just a paranoid rumor, isn't it?"
"runtest"	"I wonder if I should run that test again."
"sci_aftertest"	"You'll just have to wait until after the test."
"sci_alone"	"Please, leave me alone until after the experiment."
"sci_bother"	"I can't be bothered right now."
"sci_busy"	"Excuse me, Gordon, but I'm rather busy now."
"sci_fear6"	"Oh no!"
"sci_fear7"	"Oh dear!"
"sci_fear11"	"Oh my!"
"sci_fear12"	"My goodness!"
"sci_fear13"	"No!"
"sci_fear14"	"Get back!"
"sci_pain3"	"No!"
"sci_pain6"	"No!"
"sci_pain7"	"No!"
"sci_pain8"	"No!"
"sci_pain9"	"Stop!"
"sci_pain10"	"No!"
"sci_somewhere"	"Weren't you supposed to be in the test chamber half an hour ago?"
"scream10"	"No!"
"scream11"	"Stop!"
"scream12"	"Stop!"
"scream13"	"No!"
"seencup"	"Have you seen my coffee cup?"
"shakeunification"	"This should shake up those grand unification boys, hm?"
"shutdownchart"	"Now where did I leave that shutdown procedure chart?"
"shutup"	"Shut up."
"shutup2"	"Shut up."
"simulation"	"Most of the simulation results are perfectly acceptable, you know."
"slowingyou"	"I'm slowing you down, am I?"
"smellburn"	"Do you smell something burning?"
"softethics"	"You aren't going soft on that ethics issue again, are you?"
"sorryimleaving"	"Sorry, I'm leaving now."
"somethingfoul"	"I believe something smells quite foul here."
"startle5"	"Oh no."
"startle6"	"Oh no."
"startle7"	"Oh no."
"startle8"	"Oh no."
"startle9"	"Oh no."
"statusreport"	"Did you submit your status report to the Administrator today?"
"scientiststench"	"What is that stench?" //tag
"stimulating"	"I think it's rather stimulating, don't you?"
"scientiststop1"	"This is as far as I go." //tag
"scientiststop2"	"I refuse to go another step." //tag
"stop3"	"You're going to have to leave me here, Gordon."
"stop4"	"I'm going to stay here and wait for my colleagues."
"stopasking"	"Stop asking that question."
"stopattacking"	"Stop attacking, he's a friend!"
"survival"	"Do you recall any of those emergency survival procedures?"
"thatsodd"	"That's odd."
"theoretically"	"Theoretically."
"thiswillhelp"	"This should help."
"tunedtoday"	"All displacement modulators were tuned today, weren't they?"
"tunnelcalc"	"Are you running those tunneling lattice calculations again?"
"uselessphd"	"Fat lot of good that Ph.D. does me now, hm?"
"weartie"	"Why do we all have to wear these ridiculous ties?"
"whatnext"	"Well, do you have any idea what to do next?"
"whatyoudoing"	"My God, what are you doing?"
"whocansay"	"Who can say?"
"whoresponsible"	"Who is responsible for this mess?"
"whyaskme"	"Why are you asking me?"
"whyleavehere"	"Why are you leaving me here?"
"yees"	"Yes."
"yes"	"Yes."
"yes2"	"Yes."
"yes3"	"Yes."
"yesletsgo"	"Yes, let's go."
"youinsane"	"Are you insane? Stop attacking, immediately!"
"youlookbad"	"You look terrible."
"youlookbad2"	"You look terrible."
"scientistyouneedmedic"	"It appears that you need medical attention right away." //tag
"youwounded"	"Ah, you've been wounded."

//Uplink Scientist
"c1a4_sci_blind"	"Is someone there? I can't see a thing."
"c3a1_sci_2sat"	"I'm sorry, but those doors will not open until we send the all-clear."
"c3a1_sci_4sat"	"I would love to do that, but the area bombardment has made a wreck of my transmitter, the cables are separate, we have to aim it by hand and I'm getting high radiation levels in the transmitter dome. Nobody but a fool would go in there."
"c3a1_sci_6sat"	"Yes. You could survive in that suit of yours. Very well. I will lower security on the satellite access elevator, and you can go up into the dome. I'll try to help you over the intercom."
"c3a1_sci_dome"	"Freeman. You want to work quickly. Tune the transmitter to US NRC. I repeat! Tune to the US NRC."
"c3a1_sci_done"	"Excellent. I'm sending the all-clear and the door should open now. We'll meet you down below."

//Barney
"aimforhead"	"Aim for the head, if you can find it."
"aintgoin"	"I'm not going anywhere."
"aintscared"	"You aren't scared, are you?"
"alreadyasked"	"Didn't you already ask me that?"
"ambush"	"I smell an ambush. We'd better be careful."
"ba_another"	"Ha ha, got another one!"
"ba_attack1"	"Freeze!"
"ba_bring"	"Bring it on!"
"ba_buttugly"	"That's one less horror in the world."
"ba_close"	"Whoa, that was close."
"ba_dontmake"	"Don't make me do this."
"ba_dotoyou"	"Hey, what did I ever do to you?"
"ba_duty"	"Sorry, I'm on duty, Mr. Freeman."
"ba_endline"	"End of the line for you."
"ba_firepl"	"Heh, that'll look nice in my trophy room."
"ba_friends"	"Hmpf, with friends like you... man!"
"ba_gotone"	"Got one!"
"ba_iwish"	"I wish it hadn't come to this."
"ba_later"	"Hey, catch me later, I'll buy you a beer."
"ba_pissme"	"Don't tick me off, Gordon."
"ba_post"	"Sorry, sir, I've got to stay at my post."
"ba_raincheck"	"Can we do this later?"
"ba_seethat"	"Man, did you see that shot?"
"ba_somuch"	"I only take so much and no more."
"ba_stepoff"	"Hey, step off, buddy!"
"ba_tomb"	"What do you want on your tombstone?"
"ba_uwish"	"Heh, you're gonna wish you hadn't done that."
"ba_watchit"	"Watch it with that thing!"
"ba_whatyou"	"What are you trying to do?"
"ba_whoathere"	"Watch it with that thing!"
"badarea"	"This area just doesn't feel right."
"badfeeling"	"I have a bad feeling about this."
"beertopside"	"You think there's a cold beer for us at the end of all this?"
"bequiet"	"Would you be quiet?"
"bigmess"	"Now I wonder if those boys could have made a bigger mess."
"bigplace"	"This place is a lot bigger than I thought."
"c1a0_ba_button"	"Come on, Gordon! You trying to get me into trouble?"
"c1a0_ba_desk"	"Hey, Mr. Freeman. I had a bunch of messages for you, but we had a system crash about twenty minutes ago and I'm still trying to find my files. Just one of those days I guess. They were having some problems down in the test chamber, too, but I think that's all straightened out. They told me to make sure you headed down there as soon as you got into your hazard suit."
"c1a0_ba_headdown"	"Hey, you've got the wrong airlock, Mr. Freeman. You know I can't let you through here."
"c1a0_ba_hevno"	"Sorry, Mr. Freeman, I got explicit orders not to let you through without your hazard suit on."
"c1a0_ba_hevyes"	"Go right on through, sir. Looks like you're in the barrel today."
"c1a0_ba_late"	"Morning, Mr. Freeman. Looks like you're running late."
"c1a1_ba_glad"	"Gordon! Man, am I glad to see you! What the hell are these things? And why are they wearing science team uniforms?"
"c1a2_ba_bullsquid"	"Hey, what the hell are you doing down here? Get topside! I hear troops are coming in to save us!"
"c1a2_ba_climb"	"Elevators are out of order, but we can still climb."
"c1a2_ba_slew"	"Word is, once we get to the surface, the military has made arrangements for us."
"c1a2_ba_surface"	"Hey, don't count on the cavalry finding us down here. Head for the surface."
"c1a2_ba_top"	"Maybe help is on its way, but I'm not waiting around for it. We've got to get topside."
"c1a4_ba_octo1"	"Hey, over here! Eat lead, you outer space octopus!"
"c1a4_ba_wisp"	"Be quiet! This thing hears us!"
"c2a1_ba_hub1a"	"Mister, if you can get the power on, that train'll take us straight to the surface. I would try it myself, but it's a long way down to the generator room. And there are... things in the way."
"c2a1_ba_hub2a"	"I'm never gonna make it. You better go on without me."
"c2a2_ba_launch"	"Freeman, I've been waiting for you. One of your scientist pals said to give you a message. You're supposed to take this old rail system up to some kind of satellite delivery rocket. I don't know where it is exactly, and the old guy was so worried about getting out of here alive he didn't tell me. The main thing is, the military aborted the launch, so when you do find the rocket, you'll have to get up to the control room and launch it yourself. He said something about a Lambda team needing the satellite in orbit if they were ever going to clean up this mess."
"c2a3_ba_assn"	"Freeman, right? I've got a message for you. Make sure you don't-"
"c2a4_ba_1tau"	"What is this thing? Some kinda weapon?"
"c2a4_ba_3tau"	"Man! Why aren't we using it?"
"c2a4_ba_5tau"	"What do you mean, overcharge?"
"c2a4_ba_alive"	"Hey, it's no good up there. It's all sealed off. The only way out would be to find someone with scanner access who can open the front door. I'm pretty sure there's a few scientists hiding somewhere in the labs. Maybe with both of us looking, we can track them down and get them to let us out."
"c2a5_ba_helpme"	"Help... Help me... Somebody please help me... I'm dying out here... Please help me..."
"c3a2_ba_2surv"	"So this is the guy. We thought you'd never make it."
"c3a2_ba_4surv"	"Yeah, you'd better kill it."
"c3a2_ba_6surv"	"Enough to know that if you don't wipe it out, there won't be much for you to come home to."
"c3a2_ba_8surv"	"Don't forget to gear up. And I'll cover you while you're waiting for that portal to warm up."
"c3a2_ba_stay"	"I'm gonna stay down here. If I see anything looks like it doesn't belong, I'll start shooting."
"cantfigure"	"I can't figure it out."
"checkwounds"	"I'll bet that stings a bit."
"coldone"	"I would really like a cold one right now."
"crewdied"	"Any idea how many of our crew have died?"
"diebloodsucker"	"Die, you bloodsucker!"
"dobettertogether"	"Okay, we might live longer if we work together."
"dontaskme"	"Don't ask me."
"dontbet"	"Don't bet on it."
"dontbuyit"	"I don't buy it."
"dontfigure"	"I don't see it that way."
"dontguess"	"I don't think so."
"donthurtem"	"Hey, stop that!"
"dontreckon"	"I doubt it."
"getanyworse"	"It can't get any worse than this, can it?"
"gettingcloser"	"Think we're getting any closer?"
"gladof38"	"Bet you're glad I got this old sidearm on me, aren't ya?"
"gladtolendhand"	"Okay, why not? Didn't want to die alone anyway."
"guyresponsible"	"I'd like to get my hands on the guy responsible for this mess."
"hardtosay"	"It's hard to say."
"haybuddy"	"Hey, Gordon."
"hayfella"		"Sir."
"hearsomething"	"I hear something."
"hearsomething2"	"Hey, I hear something."
"hellonicesuit"	"Hello."
"helpothers"	"Okay, I'll wait here and help anyone else who comes by."
"heybuddy"	"Hey, Gordon."
"heyfella"	"Sir."
"hitbad"	"Well, I got hit pretty hard."
"howdy"	"Hey, Mr. Freeman."
"howyoudoing"	"Hello, sir."
"icanhear"	"That doesn't sound right."
"iguess"	"I guess so."
"illwait"	"Yeah, I'll wait here."
"imdead"	"Sorry, sir, but I can't take much more of this."
"imhit"	"Took a little damage, but I can make it."
"imwithyou"	"Let's get the hell out of here."
"ireckon"	"I reckon."
"iwaithere"	"You go on without me."
"justdontknow"	"I just don't know."
"leavealone"	"Are you crazy? Leave him alone!"
"letsgo"	"Yeah, let's go."
"letsmoveit"	"Roger that. Let's run like hell."
"luckwillturn"	"Our luck has to change sooner or later."
"maybe"	"Maybe."
"missingleg"	"Did you see that thing, with the... the missing leg?"
"mrfreeman"	"Mr. Freeman."
"nodrill"	"You don't still think this is a drill, do you?"
"nope"	"Nope."
"nosir"	"No, sir."
"notelling"	"I can't really tell."
"noway"	"No way."
"openfire"	"Open fire, Gordon! Open fire!"
"realbadwound"	"Well, sir, I hate to say it, but you're in bad shape."
"rightway"	"You sure we're going the right way?"
"seeya"	"See you later."
"slowingyoudown"	"Okay, I'll secure this area."
"somethingdied"	"Phew, something died down here!"
"somethingmoves"	"Did you see something move?"
"somethingstinky"	"What is that smell?"
"soundsbad"	"Man, that sounded bad."
"soundsright"	"Sounds right."
"standback"	"Stand back!"
"standguard"	"I'll stay here and guard this area."
"stench"	"Ew, what's that stench?"
"stop1"	"This is as far as I go."
"stop2"	"I'm gonna stay here and keep a lookout for anyone that needs help."
"stophere"	"I don't know if we should go any further. This doesn't look right."
"survive"	"I'll be happy to survive this with all my parts."
"targetpractice"	"Yep, all that target range time is gonna pay off today."
"teamup1"	"Yeah, we might stand a better chance if we team up."
"teamup2"	"Okay, I'll cover you."
"thinking"	"Are you thinking what I'm thinking?"
"waitin"	"I'm waiting right here for you."
"wayout"	"You think this is the right way out?"
"whatgood"	"I don't know what good we could do here."
"whatisthat"	"What the hell is this?"
"whatsgoingon"	"You have any idea what's going on?"
"workingonstuff"	"Did you have any idea they were working on this kind of stuff?"
"yessir"	"Yes, sir."
"youbet"	"You bet."
"youeverseen"	"You ever seen anything like this?"
"yougotit"	"You got it."
"youhearthat"	"Hey, did you hear something?"
"youneedmedic"	"Sir, that injury may need some attention soon."
"youtalkmuch"	"You talk too much."
"yup"	"Yup."

//Barney Scientist Specific
"c3a2_ba_stay"	"I'm gonna stay down here. If I see anything looks like it doesn't belong, I'll start shooting."
"c1a4_ba_octo4"	"Hey, eat this you bastard!"
"c3a1_ba_1sat"	"Open up the Reactor Complex so we can get down to safety."
"c3a1_ba_3sat"	"So send it already!"
"c3a1_ba_5sat"	"What about this guy?"


//Train Ride
"c0a0_tr_gmorn"	"Good morning and welcome to the Black Mesa Transit System. This automated train is provided for the security and convenience of the Black Mesa Research Facility personnel."
"c0a0_tr_time"	"The time is 08:47 AM. Current topside temperature is 93 degrees, with an estimated high of one hundred and five. The Black Mesa compound is maintained at a pleasant 68 degrees at all times."
"c0a0_tr_dest"	"This train is inbound from Level 3 Dormitories to Sector C Test Labs and Control Facilities. If your intended destination is a high-security area beyond Sector C, you will need to return to the Central Transit Hub in Area 9 and board a high security train. If you have not yet submitted your identity to the retinal clearance system, you must report to Black Mesa Personnel for processing before you will be permitted into the high security branch of the transit system."
"c0a0_tr_noeat"	"Due to the high toxicity of material routinely handled in the Black Mesa compound, no smoking, eating, or drinking are permitted within the Black Mesa Transit System."
"c0a0_tr_emerg"	"Please keep your limbs inside the train at all times. Do not attempt to open the doors until the train has come to a complete halt at the station platform. In the event of an emergency, passengers are to remain seated and await further instruction. If it is necessary to exit the train, disabled personnel should be evacuated first. Please stay away from electrified rails, and proceed to an emergency station until assistance arrives."
"c0a0_tr_tourn"	"A reminder that the Black Mesa Hazard Course decathlon will commence this evening at nineteen hundred hours in the Level 3 Facility. The semifinals for high-security personnel will be announced in a separate Secure Access transmission. Remember, more lives than your own may depend on your fitness."
"c0a0_tr_jobs"	"Do you have a friend or relative who would make a valuable addition to the Black Mesa team? Immediate openings are available in the areas of Materials Handling and Low-Clearance Security. Please contact Black Mesa Personnel for further information. If you have an associate with a background in the areas of theoretical physics, biotechnology or other high tech disciplines, please contact our Civilian Recruitment Division. The Black Mesa Research Facility is an equal opportunity employer."
"c0a0_tr_haz"	"A reminder to all Black Mesa Personnel: Regular radiation and biohazard screenings are a requirement of continued employment in the Black Mesa Research Facility. Missing a scheduled urinalysis or radiation check-up is grounds for immediate termination. If you feel you have been exposed to radioactive or other hazardous materials in the course of your duties, contact your Radiation Safety Officer immediately. Work safe, work smart. Your future depends on it."
"c0a0_tr_arrive"	"Now arriving at Sector C Test Labs and Control Facilities."
"c0a0_tr_exit"	"Please stand back from the automated door and wait for the security officer to verify your identity. Before exiting the train, be sure to check your area for personal belongings. Thank you and have a very safe and productive day."

//G-Man
"gman_suit"	"Gordon Freeman in the flesh. Or rather, in the hazard suit. I took the liberty of relieving you of your weapons; most of them were government property. As for the suit, I think you’ve earned it."
"gman_nasty"	"The borderworld, Xen, is in our control for the time being, thanks to you. Quite a nasty piece of work you managed over there. I am impressed."
"gman_potential"	"That’s why I’m here, Mr. Freeman. I have recommended your services to my employers, and they have authorized me to offer you a job. They agree with me that you have limitless potential."
"gman_stepin"	"You’ve proved yourself a decisive man, so I don’t expect you’ll have any trouble deciding what to do. If you’re interested, just step into the portal and I will take that as a yes."
"gman_otherwise"	"Otherwise... well... I can offer you a battle you have no chance of winning. Rather an anticlimax, after what you’ve just survived."
"gman_choose1"	"Time to choose."
"gman_choose2"	"It's time to choose."
"gman_wise"	"Wisely done, Mr. Freeman. I will see you up ahead."
"gman_nowork"	"Well, it looks like we won't be working together."
"gman_noreg"	"No regrets, Mr. Freeman."

//HECU Common
"HG_GREN0"	"Grenade!"
"HG_GREN1"	"Take cover!"
"HG_GREN2"	"Oh shit!"
"HG_GREN3"	"Get down!"
"HG_GREN4"	"Oh God!"
"HG_GREN5"	"No!"
"HG_GREN6"	"Move!"
"HG_ALERT0"	"Squad, we got hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT1"	"Target!"
"HG_ALERT2"	"Movement!"
"HG_ALERT3"	"Shit! We got hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT4"	"Squad, neutralize hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT5"	"Squad, neutralize Freeman!"
"HG_ALERT6"	"Move in!"
"HG_MONST0"	"Bogies, my sector!"
"HG_MONST1"	"We got bogies!"
"HG_MONST2"	"Alien alert!"
"HG_MONST3"	"Alien movement!"
"HG_COVER0"	"Take cover!"
"HG_COVER1"	"I need suppressing fire!"
"HG_COVER2"	"We need backup!"
"HG_COVER3"	"Too hot here!"
"HG_COVER4"	"Fall out!"
"HG_COVER5"	"Clear this area!"
"HG_COVER6"	"God damn!"
"HG_COVER7"	"Cover fire!"
"HG_THROW0"	"Fire in the hole!"
"HG_THROW1"	"Take this!"
"HG_THROW2"	"Fire in the hole!"
"HG_THROW3"	"Squad, stay down!"
"HG_TAUNT0"	"Uhh, we got heavy fire."
"HG_TAUNT1"	"Roger, hold position."
"HG_TAUNT2"	"We will kick your ass!"
"HG_TAUNT3"	"Mister, you are going down."
"HG_TAUNT4"	"You got nothing."
"HG_TAUNT5"	"Request backup!"
"HG_CHARGE0"	"Go, recon!"
"HG_CHARGE1"	"Move in!"
"HG_CHARGE2"	"Go!"
"HG_CHARGE3"	"Let's go!"
"HG_QUEST0"	"Stay alert, people."
"HG_QUEST1"	"Radio check, over."
"HG_QUEST2"	"Maintain lookout."
"HG_QUEST3"	"Squad, quiet down."
"HG_QUEST4"	"Hold position."
"HG_QUEST5"	"Sweep that sector."
"HG_QUEST6"	"Uhh, go tango sweep formation."
"HG_QUEST7"	"Echo mission is go."
"HG_QUEST8"	"Fire team, weapons check okay."
"HG_QUEST9"	"Fire team, objective foxtrot niner."
"HG_QUEST10"	"Okay mission, zero niner."
"HG_QUEST11"	"Squad, stay alert for hostiles, over."
"HG_ANSWER0"	"Uhh, roger that."
"HG_ANSWER1"	"Yes sir."
"HG_ANSWER2"	"Affirmative, sir."
"HG_ANSWER3"	"Negative."
"HG_ANSWER4"	"Roger."
"HG_ANSWER5"	"Okay control."
"HG_ANSWER6"	"That is, uhh, affirmative."
"HG_CLEAR0"	"All clear, sir."
"HG_CLEAR1"	"Bravo post, clear."
"HG_CLEAR2"	"Delta Team, clear."
"HG_CLEAR3"	"No sign hostiles, sir, over."
"HG_CLEAR4"	"No sign objective, sir, over."
"HG_CLEAR5"	"No movement this level."
"HG_CLEAR6"	"Sir, sector secure, over."
"HG_CLEAR7"	"Command post, team in position, over."
"HG_CLEAR8"	"Recon, in position, all quiet."
"HG_CLEAR9"	"Lookout post, all quiet, over."
"HG_CLEAR10"	"Sir, I hear something."
"HG_CLEAR11"	"Sir, uhh, zero movement, over."
"HG_CLEAR12"	"Area secure, sir, over."
"HG_CHECK0"	"Okay, check in."
"HG_CHECK1"	"Squad, are hostiles clear?"
"HG_CHECK2"	"Check in, people."
"HG_CHECK3"	"Lookout, check in."
"HG_CHECK4"	"Recon team, check in."
"HG_CHECK5"	"Movement check, over."
"HG_CHECK6"	"Check your zone, over."
"HG_CHECK7"	"Everything okay there."
"gr_pain1"	"Is that all you got?"
"gr_pain2"	"You got nothin'!"
"gr_pain3"	"I'm hit!"
"gr_pain4"	"Uh, oh!"
"gr_pain5"	"Argh, medic!"

//HECU Specific
"c2a2_hg_chat1a"	"So who is this guy Freeman?"
"c2a2_hg_chat2a"	"They say he was at ground zero."
"c2a2_hg_chat3a"	"Science team? You think he was responsible? Sabotage, maybe?"
"c2a2_hg_chat4a"	"Yeah, maybe. All I know for sure is he's been killing my buddies."
"c2a2_hg_chat5a"	"Oh yeah, he'll pay. He will definitely pay."
"c2a3_ambush_vox"	"Get him! Heh, nice hit. Uh, all right, we got him."
"c2a3_hg_1drag"	"Where we taking this Freeman guy?"
"c2a3_hg_2drag"	"Topside for questioning."
"c2a3_hg_3drag"	"What the hell for? We got him. Let's kill him now!"
"c2a3_hg_4drag"	"Uh, and if they find the body?"
"c2a3_hg_5drag"	"Body? What body?"
"c2a5_hg_lebuz"	"Come in, Cooper. Do you copy? Forget about Freeman. We're abandoning the base. If you have any last bomb targets, mark them on the tactical map. Otherwise, get the hell out of there. Repeat, we are pulling out and commencing airstrikes. Give us targets or get below."
"c2a5_hg_abandon"	"Forget about Freeman! We are cutting our losses and pulling out. Anyone left down there now is on his own. Repeat, if you weren't already, you are now..."
"hg_sucks"	"I killed twelve dumb ass scientists and not one of 'em fought back. This sucks."
"hg_civvies"	"I didn't sign on for this shit. Monsters, sure, but civilians? Who ordered this operation anyway?"

//Hazard Course
"tr_holo_intro"	"Hello and welcome to the Black Mesa Hazard Course, where you'll be trained in the use of a hazardous environment suit. I am your holographic assistant. Let's begin by stepping into your suit. You can see it suspended up ahead of you."
"tr_holo_button"	"If you see one of these buttons, press it and I will appear to demonstrate certain moves."
"tr_holo_move"	"Moving around in your HEV suit can be slightly disorienting at first. Take a moment to familiarize yourself with basic movement and soon it will fit you like a second skin. I will see you just around the corner."
"tr_holo_jump"	"The first move we will practice in the hazard course is basic jumping. You will attempt to get over this set of pipes, using only your run and jump commands. It helps to get a running start. Watch me and then try it yourself."
"tr_holo_duck"	"You will now duck under the next set of obstacles. Please note that crouching will automatically shift your suit into stealth mode, minimizing movement noise."
"tr_holo_jduck"	"Now we will combine skills. You will need to jump, duck, and then jump again. This will prepare you for the next room, where you will have to do both moves at the same time."
"tr_holo_pipeduck"	"To get into these pipes, you'll have to signal your suit to make a duck jump. You'll want to stand right at the mouth of the pipe and continue to press forward, then jump up and while you're in mid air, go into a crouch. It's tricky, but you'll find it comes in handy."
"tr_holo_retry"	"Give it another try. Remember to move forward, jump and while in mid air, crouch."
"tr_holo_ladder"	"Walk directly into the ladder, look up and continue moving forward. If you want to come back down, just move backward."
"tr_holo_3jumps"	"The next three jumps get harder each time, but they are quite possible. Don't be surprised, if you miss the last one a time or two. If you can make all three in a continuous run, you are doing well."
"tr_holo_keeptrying"	"Keep trying! You'll get it."
"tr_holo_fallshort"	"If you keep falling short, you might be jumping too soon."
"tr_holo_greatwork"	"Great work! Now there is one more style of jumping you need to learn."
"tr_holo_longjump"	"Long jumping requires its own charging module, seen here. To activate your long jump, you will have to duck and move forward and then launch into a jump. Once you are up on the platform, press the button and I will demonstrate the move."
"tr_holo_nicejob"	"Nice job!"
"tr_holo_startlift"	"Please start the lift by moving up to the button, looking at it and pressing the use key."
"tr_holo_jumpdown"	"Now that you're up here, there is only one way down. Find the target on the floor below and do your best to hit it. If you take any damage from the fall, we will administer medical care at the next station."
"tr_holo_medkit"	"You will find medkits like this one throughout the Black Mesa compound. To restore your health, walk up to a medkit and press your use key. Your health will recover gradually, until you are at full health or the kit is depleted. Once the light goes out, a medkit can not be reused."
"tr_holo_spinbridge"	"To spin that bridge, walk up to the control wheel and press the use key."
"tr_holo_fantastic"	"Fantastic!"
"tr_holo_jumpgap"	"Sometimes you'll need to rely on more than just your suit to get through a tight place. Try jumping this gap on your own."
"tr_holo_pushbox"	"What you really need to do is push that box down into the pit. Pushing is easy. Just move forward against the box and you can push it into position."
"tr_holo_pullbox"	"If you can't push the obstacle out of your way, you might try pulling it. To pull a box, move up to it and press your use key. While holding down the use key to keep a grip on a box, move slowly backward. The box will come along with you."
"tr_holo_breakbox"	"Finally, if nothing else works you can try breaking the objects in your path. Make sure you picked up the crowbar, than simply smash your way through the debris."
"tr_holo_flashlight"	"Activate your suit flashlight for the next area."
"tr_holo_lightoff"	"Great! Remember, your flashlight drains power, so switch it off, when you don't need it."
"tr_holo_target"	"Welcome to the Black Mesa target range, where you'll receive training in firing a weapon, reloading and firing the attached grenade launcher. Please pick up your weapon and advance to the firing station."
"tr_holo_hitall"	"You'll have to hit every target in order to complete the course. But if you miss the first time, don't worry, it will come around again. Try to reload during pauses, rather than waiting to run out of ammunition at a critical time."
"tr_holo_grenade"	"To fire your grenade launcher, use your alternate fire button. Certain targets will break only when hit by grenades."
"tr_holo_commencing"	"Commencing sequence in five, four, tree, two, one."
"tr_holo_congrats"	"Congratulations! You have completed the Black Mesa target range. Please advance to the next area."
"tr_holo_drown"	"Your HEV suit monitors blood oxygen levels, warning you when you need to find an air supply. As you swim through this course, your oxygen levels will begin to drop. At the midpoint you'll be given an opportunity to surface for air."
"tr_holo_breath"	"Come up and catch your breath. You will see the blood oxygen indicator on your suit heads-up display returning to its previous level. You are free to swim on to the end of the course."
"tr_holo_charger"	"This is the charging unit for your hazardous environment suit. When you are running low on power, step up to any charger and press your use key. Your suit will recharge gradually, until the charge unit is depleted. Individual batteries may also be used to charge your suit."
"tr_holo_steam"	"If you pass through fire or steam, you will see a heat damage icon lighting up. Directional indicators at the center of your display show you where damage is coming from."
"tr_holo_radiation"	"Proximity to radiation activates a geiger counter and radiation display. Biohazards are also indicated with the luminous icon."
"tr_holo_injury"	"Please advance to the next area."
"tr_holo_leadguard"	"Lead the security guard into the next room. He will let you back into the transit system. You must approach a guard and press your use key. He will follow you until you face him and press the use key again."
"tr_holo_usetrain"	"Press your use key to engage the train. Press your forward and backward keys to increase or decrease the speed of the train. Press your use key again to disengage from the train."
"tr_holo_done"	"Congratulation on completing the Black Mesa Hazard Course. You are now fully certified for use of the HEV Mark 4 protective system."

//Nihilliant
"nil_thieves"	"Thieves... you all are thieves... you all are..."
"nil_comes"	"Comes another..."
"nil_done"	"Done... what have you done..."
"nil_die"	"Die... you all die... you all die..."
"nil_alone"	"Alone... not you alone... not you alone..."
"nil_thelast"	"The last... I am the last..."
"nil_freeman"	"Freeman!"
"nil_thetruth"	"The truth... you can never know... the truth..."
"nil_deceive"	"Deceive you... will deceive you..."
"nil_now_die"	"Now die... now die... now..."
}
}