"lang"
{
"Language""english"
"Tokens"
{
//Neccessities
"CaptionMod_GameSaved"	"Game Saved..."
"HalfLife_Hologram"		"[Hologram] "
"HalfLife_Scientist"	"[Scientist] "
"HalfLife_HEV_Voice"	"[HEV] "
"HalfLife_Announcer"	"[Announcer] "
"HalfLife_HECU"	"[HECU] "
"HalfLife_Radio"	"[Radio] "
"HalfLife_Security"	"[Security Officer] "
"HalfLife_Train"	"[Train] "
"HalfLife_Rosenberg" "[Rosenberg] "

//Messages
"CR27"	"Black Mesa Research Facility\nBlack Mesa, New Mexico"
"ENDCHEAT"	"THE END"
"INTRO1"	"SUBJECT:\nB. Calhoun"
"CR29"	"EDUCATION:\n2 years Martinson College\nUndecided Major"
"CR30"	"EMPLOYER:\nBlack Mesa Research Facility"
"CR31"	"POSITION:\nSecurity Officer"
"CR32"	"ASSIGNMENT:\nArea 3 Security"
"CR33"	"CLEARANCE:\nLevel 3"
"CR34"	"DISASTER RESPONSE PRIORITY:\nPreservation of facility\nequipment and materials."
"CR35"	"SECONDARY PRIORITY:\nWelfare of research personnel."
"CR36"	"LOW PRIORITY:\nPersonal safety."
"GAMEOVER"	"SUBJECT:  CALHOUN\n\nSTATUS:  EMPLOYMENT TERMINATED\n\nREASON FOR TERMINATION:\nImproper handling of a firearm\nin the facility."
"XEN1FAILURE"	"SUBJECT:  CALHOUN\n\nSTATUS:  UNKNOWN\n\nEmployee is assumed to have perished with\nremaining personnel during Lambda incident."
"BSGAMEEND"	"SUBJECT:  CALHOUN\n\nSTATUS:  OUT OF RANGE\n\nNO FURTHER COMMENT"
"ROSENDEAD"	"SUBJECT:  CALHOUN\n\nSTATUS:  UNKNOWN\n\nEmployee is assumed to have perished with\nremaining personnel during Lambda incident."
"T0A0TITLE"	"HAZARD COURSE"
"BA_TRAMTITLE"	"LIVING QUARTERS OUTBOUND"
"BA_SECURITYTITLE"	"INSECURITY"
"BA_CANALSTITLE"	"DUTY CALLS"
"BA_YARDTITLE"	"CAPTIVE FREIGHT"
"BA_XENTITLE"	"FOCAL POINT"
"BA_POWERTITLE"	"POWER STRUGGLE"
"BA_TELEPORTTITLE"	"A LEAP OF FAITH"
"CHUMTOAD"	"CHUMTOAD'S LAIR"
"BSTITLE"	"Half-Life: Blue Shift"
"HZBUTTON1"	"PRESS YOUR USE KEY TO PUSH A BUTTON"
"HZBUTTON2"	"PRESS YOUR USE KEY TO PUSH A BUTTON"
"HZMOVE"	"MOVE FORWARD BY PRESSING FORWARD KEY\nMOVE BACKWARD BY PRESSING BACKWARD KEY\nMOVE LEFT BY PRESSING MOVELEFT\nMOVE RIGHT BY PRESSING MOVERIGHT"
"HZJUMP"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO RUN FORWARD\nPRESS JUMP KEY TO JUMP"
"HZDUCK"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO RUN FORWARD\nPRESS DUCK KEY TO DUCK\nPRESS FORWARD + DUCK KEYS TOGETHER\nTO MOVE IN STEALTH MODE"
"HZCOMBO"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO RUN FORWARD\nPRESS JUMP KEY TO JUMP\nPRESS DUCK KEY TO DUCK\nPRESS JUMP KEY TO JUMP"
"HZDUCKJUMP"	"PRESS FORWARD + JUMP TOGETHER,\nTHEN THE DUCK KEY"
"HZLADDER"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO MOVE UP LADDERS\nPRESS BACKWARD KEY TO MOVE DOWN LADDERS"
"HZLJUMP"	"WHILE MOVING FORWARD,\nHOLD DOWN DUCK KEY--\nTHEN PRESS JUMP"
"HZLMOD"	"BE SURE YOU PICKED UP THE LONG-JUMP MODULE\nAT THE BEGINNING OF THE OBSTACLE"
"HZMEDKIT"	"USE MED-KITS BY HOLDING DOWN THE USE KEY\nHOLD DOWN USE KEY UNTIL HEALTH IS\nAT 100 OR KIT IS DEPLETED"
"HZMOMENT"	"ACTIVATE WHEELS AND DIALS \nBY HOLDING DOWN THE USE KEY\nHOLD USE KEY UNTIL BRIDGE IS IN POSITION"
"HZPUSH"	"PRESS FORWARD KEY TO MOVE AGAINST BOX\nKEEP PRESSING FORWARD TO PUSH BOX"
"HZPULL"	"PRESS USE + BACKWARD KEYS TOGETHER\nTO PULL BOX BACKWARD"
"HZCROWBAR"	"MOVE UP TO CROWBAR\nPRESS ATTACK1 KEY TO BREAK OBJECTS"
"HZLITEON"	"PRESS FLASHLIGHT KEY\nTO TURN FLASHLIGHT ON"
"HZLITEOFF"	"PRESS FLASHLIGHT KEY AGAIN \nTO TURN FLASHLIGHT OFF"
"HZWEAPON"	"MOVE UP TO WEAPON TO PICK IT UP"
"HZFIREWEAP"	"PRESS ATTACK1 KEY FOR PRIMARY ATTACK\nPRESS ATTACK2 KEY FOR ALTERNATE ATTACK\nPRESS RELOAD KEY TO RELOAD AT WILL"
"HZARMOR"	"PRESS AND HOLD YOUR USE KEY\nHOLD DOWN UNTIL SUIT ARMOR IS CHARGED\nOR CHARGER IS DEPLETED"
"HZSWIM"	"PRESS YOUR FORWARD KEY\nAIM WITH THE MOUSE AS YOU SWIM\nFIND AIR IF YOU BEGIN TO LOSE HEALTH\nWAIT IN THE AIR UNTIL HEALTH \nRETURNS TO FORMER LEVEL"
"HZDAMAGE"	"CERTAIN TYPES OF DAMAGE WILL REGISTER \nON YOUR HEADS-UP DISPLAY.\nDIRECTION OF DAMAGE IS INDICATED BY RED \nFLASHES IN THE CENTER OF YOUR SCREEN"
"HZHAZARD"	"RADIATION HAZARDS \nACTIVATE A GEIGER COUNTER"
"HZSCIENTIST"	"APPROACH SCIENTIST\nPRESS USE KEY TO RECEIVE HEALTH FROM SCIENTIST"
"HZBARNEY"	"APPROACH SCIENTIST\nPRESS YOUR USE KEY TO GET HIS HELP\nWALK TOWARD DOOR AND SCIENTIST\nWILL ACTIVATE THE RETINAL SCANNER"
"HZTRAIN"	"PRESS USE KEY TO ENGAGE TRAIN\nPRESS FORWARD KEY TO ACCELERATE\nPRESS BACKWARD KEY TO DECELERATE\nPRESS USE KEY AGAIN TO DISENGAGE"
"HZDONE"	"CONGRATULATIONS!\nYOU HAVE COMPLETED\nTHE BLACK MESA HAZARD COURSE.\nCOME BACK ANY TIME."
"HZWEAPONSTRIP"	"ENTERING CIVILIAN AREA\nREMOVING WEAPONS NOW"

//Barney Common
"aimforhead"	"Aim for the head, if you can find it."
"aintgoin"	"I'm not going anywhere."
"aintscared"	"You aren't scared, are you?"
"alreadyasked"	"Didn't you already ask me that?"
"ambush"	"I smell an ambush. We'd better be careful."
"ba_another"	"Ha ha, got another one!"
"ba_attack1"	"Freeze!"
"ba_bring"	"Bring it on!"
"ba_buttugly"	"That's one less horror in the world."
"ba_close"	"Whoa, that was close."
"ba_dontmake"	"Don't make me do this."
"ba_dotoyou"	"Hey, what did I ever do to you?"
"ba_duty"	"Sorry, I'm on duty, Mr. Freeman."
"ba_endline"	"End of the line for you."
"ba_firepl"	"Heh, that'll look nice in my trophy room."
"ba_friends"	"Hmpf, with friends like you...man!"
"ba_gotone"	"Got one!"
"ba_iwish"	"I wish it hadn't come to this."
"ba_later"	"Hey, catch me later, I'll buy you a beer."
"ba_pissme"	"Don't tick me off, Gordon."
"ba_post"	"Sorry, sir, I've got to stay at my post."
"ba_raincheck"	"Can we do this later?"
"ba_seethat"	"Man, did you see that shot?"
"ba_somuch"	"I only take so much and no more."
"ba_stepoff"	"Hey, step off, buddy!"
"ba_tomb"	"What do you want on your tombstone?"
"ba_uwish"	"Heh, you're gonna wish you hadn't done that."
"ba_watchit"	"Watch it with that thing!"
"ba_whatyou"	"What are you trying to do?"
"ba_whoathere"	"Watch it with that thing!"
"badarea"	"This area just doesn't feel right."
"badfeeling"	"I have a bad feeling about this."
"beertopside"	"You think there's a cold beer for us at the end of all this?"
"bequiet"	"Would you be quiet?"
"bigmess"	"Now I wonder if those boys could have made a bigger mess."
"bigplace"	"This place is a lot bigger than I thought."
"cantfigure"	"I can't figure it out."
"checkwounds"	"I'll bet that stings a bit."
"coldone"	"I would really like a cold one right now."
"crewdied"	"Any idea how many of our crew have died?"
"diebloodsucker"	"Die, you bloodsucker!"
"dobettertogether"	"Okay, we might live longer if we work together."
"dontaskme"	"Don't ask me."
"dontbet"	"Don't bet on it."
"dontbuyit"	"I don't buy it."
"dontfigure"	"I don't see it that way."
"dontguess"	"I don't think so."
"donthurtem"	"Hey, stop that!"
"dontreckon"	"I doubt it."
"getanyworse"	"It can't get any worse than this, can it?"
"gettingcloser"	"Think we're getting any closer?"
"gladof38"	"Bet you're glad I got this old sidearm on me, aren't ya?"
"gladtolendhand"	"Okay, why not? Didn't want to die alone anyway."
"guyresponsible"	"I'd like to get my hands on the guy responsible for this mess."
"hardtosay"	"It's hard to say."
"hearsomething"	"I hear something."
"hearsomething2"	"Hey, I hear something."
"hellonicesuit"	"Hello."
"helpothers"	"Okay, I'll wait here and help anyone else who comes by."
"heybuddy"	"Hey, Gordon."
"heyfella"	"Sir."
"hitbad"	"Well, I got hit pretty hard."
"howdy"	"Hey, Mr. Freeman."
"howyoudoing"	"Hello, sir."
"icanhear"	"That doesn't sound right."
"iguess"	"I guess so."
"illwait"	"Yeah, I'll wait here."
"imdead"	"Sorry, sir, but I can't take much more of this."
"imhit"	"Took a little damage, but I can make it."
"imwithyou"	"Let's get the hell out of here."
"ireckon"	"I reckon."
"iwaithere"	"You go on without me."
"justdontknow"	"I just don't know."
"leavealone"	"Are you crazy? Leave him alone!"
"letsgo"	"Yeah, let's go."
"letsmoveit"	"Roger that. Let's run like hell."
"luckwillturn"	"Our luck has to change sooner or later."
"maybe"	"Maybe."
"missingleg"	"Did you see that thing, with the... the missing leg?"
"mrfreeman"	"Mr. Freeman."
"nodrill"	"You don't still think this is a drill, do you?"
"nope"	"Nope."
"nosir"	"No, sir."
"notelling"	"I can't really tell."
"noway"	"No way."
"openfire"	"Open fire, Gordon! Open fire!"
"realbadwound"	"Well, sir, I hate to say it, but you're in bad shape."
"rightway"	"You sure we're going the right way?"
"seeya"	"See you later."
"slowingyoudown"	"Okay, I'll secure this area."
"somethingdied"	"Phew, something died down here!"
"somethingmoves"	"Did you see something move?"
"somethingstinky"	"What is that smell?"
"soundsbad"	"Man, that sounded bad."
"soundsright"	"Sounds right."
"standback"	"Stand back!"
"standguard"	"I'll stay here and guard this area."
"stench"	"Ew, what's that stench?"
"stop1"	"This is as far as I go."
"stop2"	"I'm gonna stay here and keep a lookout for anyone that needs help."
"stophere"	"I don't know if we should go any further. This doesn't look right."
"survive"	"I'll be happy to survive this with all my parts."
"targetpractice"	"Yep, all that target range time is gonna pay off today."
"teamup1"	"Yeah, we might stand a better chance if we team up."
"teamup2"	"Okay, I'll cover you."
"thinking"	"Are you thinking what I'm thinking?"
"waitin"	"I'm waiting right here for you."
"wayout"	"You think this is the right way out?"
"whatgood"	"I don't know what good we could do here."
"whatisthat"	"What the hell is this?"
"whatsgoingon"	"You have any idea what's going on?"
"workingonstuff"	"Did you have any idea they were working on this kind of stuff?"
"yessir"	"Yes, sir."
"youbet"	"You bet."
"youeverseen"	"You ever seen anything like this?"
"yougotit"	"You got it."
"youhearthat"	"Hey, did you hear something?"
"youneedmedic"	"Sir, that injury may need some attention soon."
"youtalkmuch"	"You talk too much."
"yup"	"Yup."

//Scientist Common
"absolutely"	"Absolutely."
"absolutelynot"	"Absolutely not."
"administrator"	"I suspected this could happen but the Administrator just would not listen."
"afellowsci"	"A fellow scientist."
"ahfreeman"	"Ah, Freeman."
"alienappeal"	"Do you think we should appeal to the alien authorities?"
"alientrick"	"Do you suspect some alien subterfuge behind this failure?"
"allnominal"	"Yes, this all looks nominal."
"alright"	"Alright."
"analysis"	"I am rather looking forward to this analysis, aren't you?"
"announcer"	"Did you understand that last announcement?"
"areyouthink"	"Are you thinking what I'm thinking?"
"asexpected"	"As I expected."
"beenaburden"	"Have I been that much of a burden?"
"beverage"	"Have you been able to get the beverage machine to work yet?"
"bloodsample"	"Wouldn't you like to get one of these blood samples under a microscope?"
"cantbeserious"	"You can't be serious."
"cantbeworse"	"It can't get any worse than this."
"canttakemore"	"I can't take much more of this."
"cascade"	"Aren't you a bit worried about that exponential cascade scenario we discussed?"
"catchone"	"Shouldn't we try to capture a specimen?"
"chaostheory"	"Do you still say there's nothing to chaos theory?"
"checkatten"	"Are you sure you checked the Eigen attenuators?"
"completelywrong"	"You are completely wrong."
"containfail"	"It appears the containment system has completely failed."
"correcttheory"	"Are you one hundred percent sure that theory of yours is correct?"
"delayagain"	"Do you think we should delay for another recalibration?"
"didyouhear"	"Did you hear that?"
"dinner"	"Are you seriously suggesting that all of these beings are here to dine on us?"
"dontconcur"	"I don't concur."
"dontgothere"	"No, don't go that way!"
"dontknow"	"I really don't know."
"dontwantdie"	"No, I don't want to die!"
"donuteater"	"Do you know who ate all the donuts?"
"doyousmell"	"Do you smell what I smell?"
"evergetout"	"Will we ever make it out of here?"
"everseen"	"Have you ever seen anything like this?"
"excellentteam"	"With my brains and your brawn we'll make an excellent team."
"excuse"	"Excuse me, Gordon."
"fascinating"	"Don't you find this all rather fascinating?"
"fellowscientist"	"Glad to oblige a fellow scientist."
"fine"	"Fine. You won't even know I'm here."
"freeman"	"Freeman."
"freemanalive"	"Freeman! Who would have thought you'd still be alive?"
"fusionshunt"	"I certainly hope those backup fusion shunts are in good shape today."
"getoutalive"	"I just want to get out of this alive."
"getoutofhere"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"goodpaper"	"I believe this will make for a notable paper, don't you?"
"goodtoseeyou"	"Ah, it's good to see you."
"gottogetout"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"greetings"	"Greetings!"
"greetings2"	"Greetings."
"headcrab"	"These crab creatures have a unique parasitic strategy, don't you think?"
"heal1"	"Let me take care of that wound for you."
"heal2"	"This should make you feel better."
"heal3"	"Allow me to treat that injury."
"heal4"	"I can give you something for the pain."
"heal5"	"Don't worry, I am a doctor."
"scientisthearsomething"	"Did you hear something?" //tag
"scientisthello"	"Hello." //Added scientist tag
"scientisthello2"	"Hello." //Added scientist tag
"hellofreeman"	"Ah, hello, Gordon Freeman. It's good to see you."
"hellofromlab"	"You are from the Anomalous Materials Lab. Yes, I recognize you."
"hellothere"	"Hello there."
"hideglasses"	"Someone has hidden my glasses again."
"holdstill"	"Hold still, this won't hurt a bit."
"hopenominal"	"I hope those containment parameters are still nominal."
"hopeyouknow"	"I certainly hope you know what you're doing."
"howinteresting"	"How interesting, just look at that."
"hungryyet"	"Is anyone else getting hungry?"
"ibelieveso"	"I believe so."
"idontthinkso"	"I don't think so."
"ihearsomething"	"I hear something."
"scientistillwait"	"I'll wait." //tag
"illwaithere"	"I'll wait right here."
"importantspecies"	"Another important species revealed in action."
"improbable"	"A failure of this magnitude is extremely improbable."
"imsure"	"I'm sure of it."
"inconclusive"	"It's inconclusive."
"inmesstoo"	"Ah, Freeman. I see you are in this mess too."
"ipredictedthis"	"I predicted all of this, you know. All of it!"
"istay"	"I'll stay here."
"iwounded"	"I seem to be wounded... but I can keep going."
"iwounded2"	"Well, I seem to be seriously wounded."
"iwoundedbad"	"I don't think I can last much longer."
"justasked"	"Didn't you just ask me that?"
"lambdalab"	"I hope those people in the Lambda Lab can get this under control."
"leadtheway"	"Lead the way."
"leavingme"	"What? You're leaving me here?"
"letmehelp"	"Let me help you."
"scientistletsgo"	"Let's go." //Added scientist tag
"letstrythis"	"Let's try this."
"letyouin"	"Wait a minute and I'll let you in."
"limitsok"	"This is all within theoretical limits."
"lowervoice"	"Kindly lower your voice."
"luckwillchange"	"It's highly probable that our luck will change, don't you agree?"
"madness"	"This is madness! I'm getting out of here!"
"needsleep"	"I'd give my right hemisphere for a few hours of sleep."
"neverseen"	"Fascinating. I never suspected such things could be."
"newhevsuit"	"Ah, you have one of the new HEV suits. That should be very useful."
"newsample"	"Any ideas on the origin of that new sample?"
"nodoubt"	"I have no doubt."
"nogrant"	"Well, there goes our grant money."
"noguess"	"I couldn't even venture a guess."
"noidea"	"You have no idea what is going on, do you?"
"noo"	"No."
"nooo"	"No!"
"noplease"	"No! Please!"
"notcertain"	"I'm not certain."
"nothostile"	"The alien species can't possibly all be hostile, can they?"
"notsure"	"I am not at all sure."
"odorfromyou"	"I hope that odor isn't coming from you."
"ofcourse"	"Of course!"
"ofcoursenot"	"Of course not!"
"okgetout"	"Okay, let's get out of here."
"okihope"	"Okay, I hope you know what you're doing."
"organicmatter"	"Well, the dimensional breach is definitely transmitting organic matter."
"peculiarmarks"	"Why just look at those peculiar markings."
"peculiarodor"	"Hm, what a peculiar odor."
"perfectday"	"This analysis is going to run perfectly today, don't you think?"
"perhaps"	"Perhaps."
"positively"	"Positively."
"purereadings"	"Wouldn't it be fantastic to get some pure readings for a change?"
"recalculate"	"Don't you think we should recalculate those resonance dampening factors again?"
"reconsider"	"I don't suppose you'd reconsider?"
"repeat"	"You know, you repeat yourself sometimes."
"reportflux"	"I must remember to report that fluctuation."
"rescueus"	"Surely someone will come and rescue us."
"ridiculous"	"Don't be ridiculous!"
"right"	"Right!"
"rightwayout"	"Are you sure this is the right way?"
"rumorclean"	"The military cleanup is just a paranoid rumor, isn't it?"
"runtest"	"I wonder if I should run that test again."
"sci_aftertest"	"You'll just have to wait until after the test."
"sci_alone"	"Please, leave me alone until after the experiment."
"sci_bother"	"I can't be bothered right now."
"sci_busy"	"Excuse me, Gordon, but I'm rather busy now."
"sci_fear6"	"Oh no!"
"sci_fear7"	"Oh dear!"
"sci_fear11"	"Oh my!"
"sci_fear12"	"My goodness!"
"sci_fear13"	"No!"
"sci_fear14"	"Get back!"
"sci_pain3"	"No!"
"sci_pain6"	"No!"
"sci_pain7"	"No!"
"sci_pain8"	"No!"
"sci_pain9"	"Stop!"
"sci_pain10"	"No!"
"sci_somewhere"	"Weren't you supposed to be in the test chamber half an hour ago?"
"scream10"	"No!"
"scream11"	"Stop!"
"scream12"	"Stop!"
"scream13"	"No!"
"seencup"	"Have you seen my coffee cup?"
"shakeunification"	"This should shake up those grand unification boys, hm?"
"shutdownchart"	"Now where did I leave that shutdown procedure chart?"
"shutup"	"Shut up."
"shutup2"	"Shut up."
"simulation"	"Most of the simulation results are perfectly acceptable, you know."
"slowingyou"	"I'm slowing you down, am I?"
"smellburn"	"Do you smell something burning?"
"softethics"	"You aren't going soft on that ethics issue again, are you?"
"sorryimleaving"	"Sorry, I'm leaving now."
"somethingfoul"	"I believe something smells quite foul here."
"startle5"	"Oh no."
"startle6"	"Oh no."
"startle7"	"Oh no."
"startle8"	"Oh no."
"startle9"	"Oh no."
"statusreport"	"Did you submit your status report to the Administrator today?"
"scientiststench"	"What is that stench?" //changed
"stimulating"	"I think it's rather stimulating, don't you?"
"scientiststop1"	"This is as far as I go." //changed
"scientiststop2"	"I refuse to go another step." //changed
"scientiststop3"	"You're going to have to leave me here, Gordon." //changed
"scientiststop4"	"I'm going to stay here and wait for my colleagues." //changed
"stopasking"	"Stop asking that question."
"stopattacking"	"Stop attacking, he's a friend!"
"survival"	"Do you recall any of those emergency survival procedures?"
"thatsodd"	"That's odd."
"theoretically"	"Theoretically."
"thiswillhelp"	"This should help."
"tunedtoday"	"All displacement modulators were tuned today, weren't they?"
"tunnelcalc"	"Are you running those tunneling lattice calculations again?"
"uselessphd"	"Fat lot of good that Ph.D. does me now, hm?"
"weartie"	"Why do we all have to wear these ridiculous ties?"
"whatnext"	"Well, do you have any idea what to do next?"
"whatyoudoing"	"My God, what are you doing?"
"whocansay"	"Who can say?"
"whoresponsible"	"Who is responsible for this mess?"
"whyaskme"	"Why are you asking me?"
"whyleave"	"Why are you leaving me here?"
"yees"	"Yes."
"yes"	"Yes."
"yes2"	"Yes."
"yes3"	"Yes."
"yesletsgo"	"Yes, let's go."
"youinsane"	"Are you insane? Stop attacking, immediately!"
"youlookbad"	"You look terrible."
"youlookbad2"	"You look terrible."
"scientistyouneedmedic"	"It appears that you need medical attention right away." //changed
"youwounded"	"Ah, you've been wounded."

//VOX
"VOX_ELEV1"	"Warning. Main power failure in Levels 3, 5 and 8."
"VOX_ELEV2"	"Warning. Extreme electromagnetic field hazard in Sector C."
"NA0"	"Access denied."
"NA1"	"Access granted."

//Rosenberg
"ro_calhoun"	"Calhoun!"
"ro_cure0"	"You look terrible."
"ro_cure1"	"You seem to be wounded."
"ro_cure2"	"You're going to need medical attention, right away."
"ro_fear1"	"Oh my."
"ro_heal0"	"Let me take care of that wound for you."
"ro_heal1"	"This should make you feel better."
"ro_heal2"	"You need medical attention. Here."
"ro_heal3"	"Let me give you something for the pain."
"ro_heal4"	"Allow me to treat that injury."
"ro_inside_car"	"Hello! I'm in here! Can anyone hear me?"
"ro_letstrythis"	"Let's try this."
"ro_mortal0"	"I'm not sure how much longer I can last."
"ro_mortal1"	"I don't think I can last much longer."
"ro_ok0"	"Let's get going."
"ro_ok1"	"I'll be right behind you."
"ro_ok2"	"Let's hurry. There is no time to waste."
"ro_ok3"	"All right. Let's hope we don't run into anymore of those soldiers."
"ro_ok4"	"All right. Let's stick together."
"ro_ok5"	"All right. You won't even know I'm here."
"ro_ok6"	"Yes. We'll have a better chance if we stick together."
"ro_ok7"	"Lead the way, Calhoun."
"ro_ok8"	"Let's go."
"ro_ok9"	"Yes. Let's go."
"ro_outro1"	"Ah there he is! Calhoun, you've arrived! When you didn't come through right away we thought of the... Oh no, there is something wrong here. Simmons! Come look at Calhoun! His body seems to be in some sort of resonance displacement and I..."
"ro_outro2"	"Oh thank God, you've made it. I was worried that a malfunction occurred at the last moment and you might have been caught in an infinite harmonic reflux. If that's the case, then you're lucky to be standing here. Then again, we're all lucky. Thanks to you, however, we were actually able to pull of this half-brained idea. We made it, Mr. Calhoun. We made it."
"ro_plfear0"	"What are you doing?"
"ro_plfear1"	"I can't take this anymore."
"ro_plfear2"	"This is madness!"
"ro_plfear3"	"No, please! I don't want to die!"
"ro_plfear4"	"Get out of here!"
"ro_scared0"	"My God! What are you doing?"
"ro_scared1"	"Stop attacking! Immediately!"
"ro_scared2"	"Are you insane? He's a friend!"
"ro_stop0"	"Wait up, Calhoun. I'm afraid I need to rest."
"ro_stop1"	"Hold on, Calhoun. I need to take a break."
"ro_stop2"	"I need to rest a bit before I could go on."
"ro_stop3"	"Slow down, Calhoun. I can't keep up at this pace."
"ro_stop4"	"Hold on, Calhoun. You'll have to slow down a bit."
"ro_tele_almost1"	"We're almost there."
"ro_tele_almost2"	"We're almost there."
"ro_tele_final01"	"Calhoun, you did it! We've already begun preparing the device with the fresh power cell you sent up. This time, however, the process is going to bit more complex. So I'll need you to help me in the main room. Let's hurry, there is no time to waste."
"ro_tele_final02"	"All right. I'll stay down here to monitor the system levels, and direct the procedure. I need you to climb up to the control room, and activate the main power. Once the process has started, you'll also need to release the dampen locks each time the system has charged in order to open the displacement field. Don't worry, Mr. Calhoun, the process is simple, and I'll let you know when you need to do something."
"ro_tele_final03"	"What are you waiting for, Calhoun? Get up to the control room, and locate the main power switch."
"ro_tele_final04"	"Please hurry, Mr. Calhoun! We don't have much time!"
"ro_tele_final05"	"Very good. Stand by, Calhoun. Once the system initialized, it will take few moments for the interpolating resonance coils to archive focus."
"ro_tele_final06"	"Everything is looking nom... Oh no, the primary cooling line has been raptured. Calhoun, go to the valve located on the catwalk, and release the pressure! Hurry, before the system overheats!"
"ro_tele_final07"	"This is no time for games, Calhoun! If the secondary cooling pipe bursts the machine will explode. You must crank the valve on the catwalk now!"
"ro_tele_final08"	"Good. Now, keep turning the crank, until the pressure level reaches normal."
"ro_tele_final09"	"Don't let the pressure reach critical, Calhoun! You must continue cranking until the level reaches nominal!"
"ro_tele_final10"	"Good work, Calhoun. That was close. The system has been stabilized, and main capacitors are charging. When main charger meter reaches full, I'll need you to open the displacement field from the control room."
"ro_tele_final11"	"Simmons, can you hear me? Get the rest of the team together, and prepare to teleport. Remember, we can only send one person at a time, so be patient."
"ro_tele_final12"	"Wait for it, Calhoun! You can't open the displacement field until the charger reaches its maximum."
"ro_tele_final13"	"I told you to wait until the system is fully charged! Be patient, Calhoun!"
"ro_tele_final14"	"Okay, the system is fully charged. Throw the switch located at the window of the control room!"
"ro_tele_final15"	"Go ahead, Calhoun. Throw the displacement field switch. What are you waiting for?"
"ro_tele_final16"	"Calhoun, our time is running out! Go to the window of the control room, and throw the switch."
"ro_tele_final17"	"It's too late, the system is collapsing! You've killed us all, Calhoun!"
"ro_tele_final18"	"Very good, Calhoun. I'll begin charging the system for the next teleport event."
"ro_tele_final19"	"Almost there. All right, we've reached full charge again. Open the field, Calhoun!"
"ro_tele_final20"	"Excellent. The next jump can go through now."
"ro_tele_final21"	"Let's keep going. The main capacitors are charging."
"ro_tele_final22"	"Okay, it's ready. Throw the switch again!"
"ro_tele_final23"	"You must go now, Simmons!"
"ro_tele_final24"	"Oh no!	"
"ro_tele_final25"	"I'm going to go through next, but don't worry, Mr. Calhoun. I've set the system to automatically start the charging sequence once I've made it through. Just wait for the levels to reach full again, and open the field like you've been doing."
"ro_tele_final26"	"All right, it's ready."
"ro_tele_final27"	"Good luck, Mr. Calhoun. I'll see you on other side!"
"ro_tele_final28"	"There, the field is open. Go now, Walter!"
"ro_tele_nocell"	"I'm glad to see you're all right, Mr. Calhoun, but we really need another power cell if we expect to get out of here. You'll have to go back down there, find a power cell, and send it back up to us fully charged. We're all depending on you."
"ro_tele_power1"	"Good job, Mr. Calhoun. We begin to worry when you didn't come back for some time, but it looks though you were able to get the device operational. The signal we're getting is very strong, but I'm afraid I have some bad news. The power reservoirs were just enough to open a field for your trip to the borderworld. If we plan on keeping the teleporter open long enough to calculate a safe exit point, and allow time for everyone to go through, someone will have to go to the lower level, and retrieve another power cell."
"ro_tele_power2"	"A few of our colleagues went down there while ago, but we haven't heard them from since. I can only fear for the worst."
"ro_tele_power3"	"I hate to keep putting you in this position, but you must realize that if someone doesn't go down there, then no one us will get out of here alive. Besides, you're the best equipped to deal with any dangers that may be waiting. Here, I'll show you to the access elevator that leads to the power generator. Follow me."
"ro_tele_power4"	"Calhoun! Where are you? We need you to go down below, and find us another power cell!"
"ro_tele_power5"	"Ah, here we are. Down below, the old power generators that we used to service this lab. You should find what we're looking for down there. Once you locate a new power cell, make sure it's charged, and send it up to the freight lift. Good luck."
"ro_tele_xen01"	"Excellent, Walter. Finish aligning the power cell matrix, and I'll see if I can get the system online in the main room. Now, there's no time to waste."
"ro_tele_xen02"	"Well, looks like the equipment is in better shape than expected."
"ro_tele_xen03a"	"Unfortunately, this older technology does not have the ability to target an Earth destination in its current state. You see, Mr. Calhoun, teleportation isn't as easy as going from point A to point B. We've discovered a strange borderworld that was somehow involved in the process which kept us from accurately predicting where any given teleportation event would lead to back on Earth."
"ro_tele_xen03b"	"Some of the more promising research on the matter led to a device that could be attached to strange crystalline structures we found on this borderworld. Now, this device, could then be used as a focal point and relay to aid in the teleportation. Well, in theory that is."
"ro_tele_xen04"	"We lost contact with the survey group shortly after the device was in place. We later discovered other methods of aiming the field, but all the equipment in this lab uses the older technology. In order for any of us to get out of here alive, someone will have to go to the borderworld, and activate the device."
"ro_tele_xen05"	"I'm afraid you're the only one who can do this. Seeing as how everyone else will be needed to operate the equipment."
"ro_tele_xen06"	"We should be able to get you fairly close to where the survey team had setup, but I fear the likelihood of running into alien creatures is very high. Once you find the device, simply power it on, and line the emitters until the signal reaches maximum strength. We'll reopen the teleport for your return, once we receive the signal, but you must hurry back. As we can keep it open for a short amount of time."
"ro_tele_xen07"	"All right. I'm going to initiate the teleporting charging sequence now. Be ready Mr. Calhoun. Once the field is open, it will become unstable very quickly."
"ro_tele_xen08"	"The primary capacitors have reached fully charge. Simmons! Release the dampen locks, and open the field."
"ro_tele_xen09"	"The field, it's open! Calhoun, enter to the teleporter!"
"ro_tele_xen10"	"You must make the jump now, Calhoun. The displacement field can't sustain itself much longer."
"ro_tele_xen11"	"You fool, you've taken too long! The impulse reflection rotors are burning up. I can't shut it down. Run!"
"ro_tele_xen12"	"Simmons, can you hear me? It's ready."
"ro_to_teleport"	"We should've choosen the Lambda Reactor for an escape, but the crew there is bent on fighting the creatures, with all their hopes set on someone named Freeman. Let those fools try and fight a battle they can't win. I just want to get out of here."
"ro_too_slow"	"You fool, you taken too long!"
"ro_wait0"	"Don't leave me here, Calhoun. We need to stick together."
"ro_wait1"	"This is no time to rest. We must keep going."
"ro_wait2"	"I'll wait here."
"ro_wait3"	"I'll stay here, but hurry back."
"ro_wait4"	"Yes, maybe you should go on ahead for a bit. Just don't forget about me."
"ro_wait5"	"I may be slowing you down, but you'll need me to get in to the lab."
"ro_wait6"	"We have no time to take a break. We must keep going."
"ro_wait7"	"Please don't leave me here, Calhoun. I'll be defenseless if those soldiers find me."
"ro_wound0"	"I seem to be wounded, but I can keep going."
"ro_wound1"	"I'm not doing too well, but I can make it."
"ro_xen_call1"	"Calhoun, you must hurry! We can't keep the portal open much longer!"
"ro_xen_call2"	"If you can hear me Calhoun, you must hurry! The teleporter charge is running out!"
"ro_xen_call3"	"It's too late, the field is collapsing. Calhoun!"
"ro_yard_access1"	"Yes, here it is. We'll need to break through this to get to the elevator."
"ro_yard_access2"	"I see you already found the elevator. Let's hurry then."
"ro_yard_almost2"	"Follow me."
"ro_yard_almost3"	"Let's stick together. We're almost there."
"ro_yard_follow1"	"Follow me."
"ro_yard_follow2"	"Calhoun. Follow me."
"ro_yard_hurry02"	"Please hurry, Mr. Calhoun."
"ro_yard_notime"	"Now, there's no time to waste."
"ro_yard_rose1"	"Yes, I'm Dr. Rosenberg. Although I'm not very proud to admit it, seen as though I'm partially responsible for all of this."
"ro_yard_rose2"	"How did you know my name? Oh I see, poor Harold.\nYes, our plan was to get to one of the the old prototype labs. It involved something that very few people in the facility authorized to know about. The same technology that brought about this catastrophe could also be our only way out. You see, I was involved in the very early work on teleporter technology. Long before the Lambda Complex was even built. There may be enough equipment in the old lab to piece together a device that would allow us to teleport outside out of the facility. As improbable as that might sound to someone like yourself. Of course, none of that does us a whole lot of good while we're stuck in here."
"ro_yard_rose3"	"Hmm. Perhaps I could help boost you through that vent in the ceiling. If you're lucky, you might be able to take those soldiers by surprise."
"ro_yard_rose4"	"All right. Now, we'll need head back to area where you met Harold. The access to the old lab should still be there, but we may have to break through some of the newer construction to get through it."
"ro_yard_scanner"	"Well, I hope the old security system is still active. With any luck my fingerprint ID is still valid and on file."

//BS Scientist Specific
"sc_accident1"	"Well, it's about time! We don't pay you people to mosey around at your own convenience. Make this thing work, so we can get on with this miserable day!"
"sc_accident2"	"Oh no. It's probably those Anomalous Materials people again. Always pushing their equipment too hard, dabbling in who knows what. I'd be surprised if there's one good brain among them!"
"sc_accident3"	"Well, don't just stand there. Do something!"
"sc_canals2"	"Calhoun, how did you get through the power lock? Well, it doesn't matter. The only other way out of here is through the canal. If you do make it to the surface, don't tell anyone I'm down here. I think they're trying to kill us all. Now get out of here! The canal is where you want to be."
"sc_canals4"	"Please, leave me alone. I don't want them to hear us. If you want to escape, go through the canal."
"sc_hello0"	"Thank god, a security guard!"
"sc_hello1"	"Thank god, someone with a weapon."
"sc_hello2"	"It's good to see another living human being."
"sc_hello3"	"Can you help me get out of here?"
"sc_hello4"	"Excellent, someone who knows how to use a gun."
"sc_hello5"	"Oh my, for a second I thought you were one of them."
"sc_maint"	"If you're waiting for the tram to Sector G, then you're probably better off walking it. I overheard someone say that all the trams on this end of the facility are having problems."
"sc_ok0"	"Yes. You seem like someone I can trust."
"sc_ok1"	"I suppose a security guard should know what he's doing. Let's go."
"sc_ok2"	"I'll be right behind you."
"sc_ok3"	"Well, if you think I can help."
"sc_pok0"	"Please, leave me alone! I have very important work to do."
"sc_pok1"	"Don't you have your own job to be doing?"
"sc_pok2"	"Excuse me, but I'm rather busy right now."
"sc_pok3"	"Don't you have more important things to be doing than keeping me from my work?"
"sc_pok4"	"Why do you security guards always insist on bothering us?"
"sc_pok5"	"Shouldn't you be guarding something right now?"
"sc_pok6"	"Shouldn't you be guarding some donuts and coffee right about now?"
"sc_power1"	"Those things, they're everywhere! We've got to get out of here!"
"sc_power2"	"Look out!"
"sc_sec2_admin1"	"I can't access my files. I can't answer my mail. I haven't even able to get into my office."
"sc_sec2_admin2"	"Time? I don't have anymore time! If I'm not able to get my report to the administrator in the next hour, then my job will be in serious jeopardy, and I'll make sure that mine is not the only one."
"sc_stop3"	"You're going to have to leave me here."
"sc_tele_work2"	"Doctor Rosenberg, thank God you made it! We've managed to piece together some of the larger equipment, but you'll need to oversee the rest of the construction."
"sc_yard_box1"	"No. I'm afraid I'm not Dr. Rosenberg, but you'll still help me, won't you?"
"sc_yard_box1a"	"No. I'm afraid I'm not Dr. Rosenberg."
"sc_yard_box1b"	"I'm not Dr. Rosenberg."
"sc_yard_box2"	"Okay. I'll wait out here and watch for trouble."
"sc_yard_box3"	"Help! Someone let us out of here!"
"sc_yard_box4"	"Hello? Can anyone hear me?"
"sc_yard_wound1"	"I appreciate your help, but I'm afraid those bastards did their damage already. If you were trying to reach the freight yards in hope of escaping, then just forget about it. The military is rounding up everyone and everything they can find, and either killing them or bringing them up here for questioning."
"sc_yard_wound2"	"A colleague and I came up with our plan for escape, and we were on our way to one of the old prototype labs when we ran into them. But listen to me, if you still want to get out of here alive, your only hope may be to find my friend. If you can get pass the soldiers, find Dr. Rosenberg. With him, you may have a chance to get out of this place."
"c1a0_sci_gm"	"Good morning, Gordon."
"c1a3_sci_rescued"	"Rescued at last! Thank God you're here!"

//BS Barney Specific
"ba_crazy"	"Are you crazy?"
"ba_hello1"	"How's it going?"
"ba_hello2"	"Hey, Calhoun."
"ba_hello3"	"Hey, how are ya?"
"ba_hello4"	"Looks like we're in for a long day today."
"ba_hello5"	"How's it going, Calhoun?"
"ba_openfire"	"Open fire!"
"ba_pok0"	"Shouldn't you be on duty by now?"
"ba_pok1"	"Can't this wait 'till we're off duty?"
"ba_pok2"	"I'm a little busy right now, Calhoun."
"ba_pok3"	"Sorry, Calhoun, I'm on duty."
"ba_power1"	"Hold yourself together! If we don't get the power cell charged, we're all going to die."
"ba_power2"	"Get outta here, I can take it!"
"ba_power3"	"It's okay sir, I can take him."
"ba_power_wound1"	"I was hoping you'd show up. You have to get this power cell charged and back up to Dr. Rosenberg. I'd help, but I'm hurt pretty bad."
"ba_power_wound2"	"You can probably push the power cell through the fence into the charging station behind me. Lemme see if I can get outta the way."
"ba_security1_door1"	"Hold on a minute. The door is not responding to your pass ID. Lemme see if I can get it open on this side."
"ba_security1_door2"	"Okay, I think I got it."
"ba_security1_door3"	"Sorry about that, Calhoun. We've been having problems all over the facility this morning. System crashes, security malfunctions. It's a wonder this whole place hasn't shut down yet."
"ba_security2_admin"	"I know, sir, I know. We're doing everything we can to get the problem under control. Just give us some time to-"
"ba_security2_desk1"	"Nice of you to show up this morning, Calhoun. Yeah, yeah, I know, problems with the access system. Hope you're ready for a long shift."
"ba_security2_desk2"	"Uh oh, now what? Looks like some people are having problems with the main access lift in Sector G. Why don't you go over there and see what you can do?"
"ba_security2_nopass"	"Calhoun, you know you can't go on duty without your sidearm and uniform!"
"ba_security2_pass"	"Have a good one, Calhoun."
"ba_security2_range1"	"Here you go, Calhoun."
"ba_security2_range2"	"I know you're not on the schedule for a couple more days, but if you want to squeeze in few shots in the range, there's plenty of room."
"ba_shot1"	"Watch it, Calhoun!"
"ba_shot2"	"Don't piss me off, Calhoun!"
"ba_shot3"	"Check your fire, Calhoun!"
"ba_shot4"	"Watch where you shootin'!"
"ba_shot5"	"Watch where you point that thing!"

//Otis
"OT_CHAT1"	"Hell if I know."
"mmmm"	"Mmmm."
"ot_intro_hello1"	"Hey, Calhoun."
"ot_intro_hello2"	"Looks like we're in for a long day today."
"ot_intro_seeya"	"Have a good one, Calhoun."

//Train
"ba_tram0"	"Good morning and welcome to the Black Mesa Transit System. This automated train is provided for the comfort and convenience of Black Mesa residents and visitors to the Black Mesa Research Facility."
"ba_tram1"	"The time is 08:42 AM. Current topside temperature is 91 degrees with an estimated high today of one hundred and five. The Black Mesa Compound is maintained at 68 degrees at all times."
"ba_tram2"	"This train is inbound from the Area 8 Topside Dormitories to the Central Transit Hub in Area 9."
"ba_tram3"	"Please keep your limbs inside the train at all times. Do not attempt to open the doors until the train has come to a complete halt at the station platform. In the event of an emergency, passengers are to remain seated and await further instruction. If it is necessary to exit the train, disabled personnel should be evacuated first. Please stay away from electrified rails, and proceed to an emergency station until assistance arrives."
"ba_tram4"	"If your intended destination is a high-security area beyond Sector C, you will need to board a high security train at the Central Transit Hub. If you have not yet submitted your identity for the retinal clearance system, you must report to Black Mesa Personnel for processing before you will be admitted to the high-security branch of the transit system."
"ba_tram5"	"If you wish to transfer to the Sector B or C medium-security lines, you may do so before you reach the Central Transit Hub, at the Area 9 Security Checkpoint. Access to the medium-security branch of the transit system is for employees of the Black Mesa Research Facility and authorized visitors only and requires that you wear your security badge at all times."
"ba_tram6"	"This train is now transferring to the Sector C line of the transit system. This is a medium security area of the Black Mesa facility. Be sure to wear your identification badge at all times."
"ba_tram7"	"Now arriving at Area 3 Security Facilities."
"ba_tram8"	"Please stand back from the automated door until it has fully opened. Before exiting the train, be sure to check your area for personal belongings. Thank you and have a safe and productive day."

//Grunt Specific
"hg_canal1"	"Man, these civvies are gettin' heavy!"
"hg_canal2"	"Yeah, why are we on disposal duty, anyway? Just because Shephard's team didn't make it, we have to do the crap jobs?"
"hg_canal3"	"Well, let's get on with it."
"hg_got_barney"	"All right, we got that bastard. What's the status on Freeman?"
"c2a3_hg_1drag"	"Where we taking this Freeman guy?"
"c2a3_hg_2drag"	"Topside for questioning."
"c2a3_hg_3drag"	"What the hell for? We got him. Let's kill him now!"
"c2a3_hg_4drag"	"Uh, and if they find the body?"
"c2a3_hg_5drag"	"Body? What body?"


//Holo
"tr_sci_use"	"Yes, I will follow you if you wish."
"tr_sci_unuse"	"Okay, I will wait here."
"tr_sci_hardlynoticed"	"Very good! I hardly noticed you. Move on to the next area."
"tr_sci_nextstation"	"Good work! You look prepared for the next station."
"tr_sci_gwbarney"	"Good work! Please proceed to the next area."
"tr_holo_intro"	"Welcome to the Black Mesa Hazard Course for security guard training. I'll be your holographic guide to assist you in your training. Begin by putting on your vest and helmet. You'll find this equipment in the next room."
"tr_holo_button"	"Whenever you see one of these buttons, press it, and I'll repeat instructions or show you how things are done."
"tr_holo_armor"	"Here you'll find your standard armor vest and helmet. These will help protect you against any physical threat you may encounter while performing your duties. When your armor becomes too damaged to be useful, you'll need to find a fresh vest or helmet to protect yourself."
"tr_holo_move"	"Moving around in your armor may be a little tricky at first. Take a moment to get a feel for moving around. Once you get comfortable with this, proceed to the next section just around the corner."
"tr_holo_jump"	"The first move you'll need to practice is jumping. You'll have to get over all three of these obstacles in order to proceed. It helps to get a running start. Watch me do it, then try it yourself."
"tr_holo_duck"	"You'll need to duck under the next set of obstacles. When you crawl in a crouch position, you can move very silently. This can be very useful when you don't want to be heard."
"tr_holo_jduck"	"Now, try combining moves. You'll need to jump, duck, and then jump again. This should get you prepared for the next room where you'll have to do both moves at the same time."
"tr_holo_pipeduck"	"To get into the these pipes, you'll need to perform a duck jump. You'll wanna stand right at the mouth of the pipe. While moving forward, jump up and hold the jump button to go into a crouch in midair. It may be tricky at first, but you'll find it comes in handy to be able to jump and duck into tight areas."
"tr_holo_retry"	"Give it another try. Remember to move forward, jump, and while in midair, crouch."
"tr_holo_nicejob"	"Nice work."
"tr_holo_ladder"	"Walk directly into the ladder, look up, and continue moving forward. If you wanna climb back down, just move backward."
"tr_holo_4jumps"	"The next four jumps get more difficult each time. Don't worry if you miss the last one a few times. Just climb up and do it again. If you can make all the jumps in a continuous run, you're doing just fine."
"tr_holo_keeptrying"	"Keep trying and you'll get it."
"tr_holo_fallshort"	"If you keep falling short, you may be jumping too soon."
"tr_holo_startlift"	"To start the lift, walk up to the button and press the use key while facing it."
"tr_holo_jumpdown"	"Now that you're up here, there's only one way down. Find the target on the floor below and do your best to hit it. You may take some damage from the fall, but don't worry about it. We'll give you some first aid in the next section."
"tr_holo_medkit"	"You'll find medical kits like this one throughout the Black Mesa Research Facility. To restore your health, walk up to a medkit, then press and hold your use key. Your health will recover gradually until you're at full health or until the kit is depleted. Once the light go out, a medkit cannot be reused."
"tr_holo_hevnouse"	"You may also find HEV charging stations such as this one throughout the facility. These stations, however, can only be used by qualified science personnel wearing Powered Hazardous Environment equipment, so they will be inaccessible to you during your duties."
"tr_holo_spinbridge"	"To spin that bridge, walk up to the control wheel and press the use key."
"tr_holo_fantastic"	"Great job."
"tr_holo_jumpgap"	"Sometimes you'll need to rely on quick reflexes to get around. Try jumping this gap on your own."
"tr_holo_pushbox"	"What you really need to do is push the box down into the pit. Pushing is easy. Just move forward into the box and you can push it into position."
"tr_holo_pullbox"	"If you can't push an obstacle out of the way, you might try pulling it. To pull a box, move up to it and press your use key. While holding down the use key, move backwards, and the box will be pulled with you."
"tr_holo_breakbox"	"If nothing else works, you can try breaking things that block your path. Pick up the crowbar and smash your way through the boxes."
"tr_holo_flashlight"	"You'll need to use your flashlight for the next area."
"tr_holo_lightoff"	"Great! Remember, your flashlight will lose power over time, so switch it off when you don't need it. When the flashlight is off, it will recharge itself."
"tr_holo_target"	"Welcome to the Black Mesa Training Target Range. You'll get a chance to fire your weapon, reload, and fire the attached grenade launcher. Collect your equipment and proceed to the firing station."
"tr_holo_hitall"	"You'll need to hit every target to complete the course. If you miss, don't worry about it. The targets will keep moving until you manage to score a hit. If you want to get through the target range as quickly as possible, try reloading during pauses instead of letting your gun run out of ammunition at a critical time."
"tr_holo_grenade"	"To fire the grenade launcher, use the alternate fire button. Some targets can only be destroyed by lobbing grenades."
"tr_holo_commencing"	"I'll start the sequence in five, four, three, two, one."
"tr_holo_congrats"	"Congratulations! You've completed the Black Mesa Training Target Range. You may advance to the next area."
"tr_holo_drown"	"Your heads-up display will let you know when oxygen becomes critical. That means you'll need to find some clean air to breath. As you swim through this course, your blood oxygen levels will begin to drop. At the midpoint, you'll be given an opportunity to surface for air."
"tr_holo_breath"	"Swim up to the surface to catch your breath. You'll regain health lost from holding your breath too long once you've made it to the surface for air. Go ahead and swim on to the next section."
"tr_holo_steam"	"If you pass through fire or steam, you'll see damage icons come up in your heads-up display. Directional indicators at the center of your display will show you from what direction damage is coming."
"tr_holo_radiation"	"Proximity to radiation activates a Geiger counter and radiation display in your helmet. Many other biological and chemical hazards are also indicated in your heads-up display."
"tr_holo_injury"	"Please proceed to the next section."
"tr_holo_leadguard"	"Lead a scientist into the next room. He will open the door that leads back into the transit system. To have someone follow you, approach the person and press your use key. He will then follow you until you face him and press the use key again."
"tr_holo_usetrain"	"Press your use key to engage the train. Once engaged, move forward or backward to increase or decrease the speed of the train. Press the use key a second time to disengage from the train."
"tr_holo_done"	"Congratulations on completing the Black Mesa Hazard Course for security guards. You're now certified to join the Blue Shift high security unit."

//HL HECU
"HG_GREN0"	"Grenade!"
"HG_GREN1"	"Take cover!"
"HG_GREN2"	"Oh shit!"
"HG_GREN3"	"Get down!"
"HG_GREN4"	"Oh God!"
"HG_GREN5"	"No!"
"HG_GREN6"	"Move!"
"HG_ALERT0"	"Squad, we got hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT1"	"Target!"
"HG_ALERT2"	"Movement!"
"HG_ALERT3"	"Shit! We got hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT4"	"Squad, neutralize hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT5"	"Squad, neutralize Freeman!"
"HG_ALERT6"	"Move in!"
"HG_MONST0"	"Bogies, my sector!"
"HG_MONST1"	"We got bogies!"
"HG_MONST2"	"Alien alert!"
"HG_MONST3"	"Alien movement!"
"HG_COVER0"	"Take cover!"
"HG_COVER1"	"I need suppressing fire!"
"HG_COVER2"	"We need backup!"
"HG_COVER3"	"Too hot here!"
"HG_COVER4"	"Fall out!"
"HG_COVER5"	"Clear this area!"
"HG_COVER6"	"God damn!"
"HG_COVER7"	"Cover fire!"
"HG_THROW0"	"Fire in the hole!"
"HG_THROW1"	"Take this!"
"HG_THROW2"	"Fire in the hole!"
"HG_THROW3"	"Squad, stay down!"
"HG_TAUNT0"	"Uhh, we got heavy fire."
"HG_TAUNT1"	"Roger, hold position."
"HG_TAUNT2"	"We will kick your ass!"
"HG_TAUNT3"	"Mister, you are going down."
"HG_TAUNT4"	"You got nothing."
"HG_TAUNT5"	"Request backup!"
"HG_CHARGE0"	"Go, recon!"
"HG_CHARGE1"	"Move in!"
"HG_CHARGE2"	"Go!"
"HG_CHARGE3"	"Let's go!"
"HG_QUEST0"	"Stay alert, people."
"HG_QUEST1"	"Radio check, over."
"HG_QUEST2"	"Maintain lookout."
"HG_QUEST3"	"Squad, quiet down."
"HG_QUEST4"	"Hold position."
"HG_QUEST5"	"Sweep that sector."
"HG_QUEST6"	"Uhh, go tango sweep formation."
"HG_QUEST7"	"Echo mission is go."
"HG_QUEST8"	"Fire team, weapons check okay."
"HG_QUEST9"	"Fire team, objective foxtrot niner."
"HG_QUEST10"	"Okay mission, zero niner."
"HG_QUEST11"	"Squad, stay alert for hostiles, over."
"HG_ANSWER0"	"Uhh, roger that."
"HG_ANSWER1"	"Yes sir."
"HG_ANSWER2"	"Affirmative, sir."
"HG_ANSWER3"	"Negative."
"HG_ANSWER4"	"Roger."
"HG_ANSWER5"	"Okay control."
"HG_ANSWER6"	"That is, uhh, affirmative."
"HG_CLEAR0"	"All clear, sir."
"HG_CLEAR1"	"Bravo post, clear."
"HG_CLEAR2"	"Delta Team, clear."
"HG_CLEAR3"	"No sign hostiles, sir, over."
"HG_CLEAR4"	"No sign objective, sir, over."
"HG_CLEAR5"	"No movement this level."
"HG_CLEAR6"	"Sir, sector secure, over."
"HG_CLEAR7"	"Command post, team in position, over."
"HG_CLEAR8"	"Recon, in position, all quiet."
"HG_CLEAR9"	"Lookout post, all quiet, over."
"HG_CLEAR10"	"Sir, I hear something."
"HG_CLEAR11"	"Sir, uhh, zero movement, over."
"HG_CLEAR12"	"Area secure, sir, over."
"HG_CHECK0"	"Okay, check in."
"HG_CHECK1"	"Squad, are hostiles clear?"
"HG_CHECK2"	"Check in, people."
"HG_CHECK3"	"Lookout, check in."
"HG_CHECK4"	"Recon team, check in."
"HG_CHECK5"	"Movement check, over."
"HG_CHECK6"	"Check your zone, over."
"HG_CHECK7"	"Everything okay there."
"gr_pain1"	"Is that all you got?"
"gr_pain2"	"You got nothin'!"
"gr_pain3"	"I'm hit!"
"gr_pain4"	"Uh, oh!"
"gr_pain5"	"Argh, medic!"
}
}