"lang"
{
"Language""english"
"Tokens"
{
//Neccessities
"CaptionMod_GameSaved"	"Game Saved..."
"HalfLife_Hologram"	"[Hologram] "
"HalfLife_Scientist"	"[Scientist] "
"HalfLife_HEV_Voice"	"[HEV] "
"HalfLife_VOX"	"[Announcer] "
"HalfLife_HECU"	"[HECU] "
"HalfLife_Radio"	"[Radio] "
"HalfLife_Security"	"[Security Officer] "
"HalfLife_Train"	"[Train] "

//Messages
"GAMETITLE"	"Half-Life: Opposing Force"
"CR28"	"SUBJECT:\nAdrian Shephard\nMale, age 22"
"CR29"	"TRAINING:\nUnited States Marine Corps,\nSpecial Forces"
"CR30"	"RANK:\nCorporal"
"CR31"	"Commanding Officer:\nSergeant Dwight T. Barnes"
"CR32"	"CURRENT ASSIGNMENT:\nHazardous Environment Combat Unit\nSantego Military Base, Arizona"
"CR33"	"MISSION:\nClassified"
"GFOLLOW_LOSER"	"SUBJECT:  SHEPHARD\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubject attempted to create\ntemporal paradox."
"GAMEOVER"	"SUBJECT:  SHEPHARD\n\nSTATUS:  DETAINED\n\nFURTHER EVALUATION PENDING"
"BC_FAILURE"	"SUBJECT:  SHEPHARD\n\nSTATUS:  AWAITING COURT MARTIAL"
"OFGAMEOVER"	"SUBJECT:  CPL. SHEPHARD\n\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION DECLINED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubject failed to effectively utilize\nhuman assets in achievement of goal."
"DISP_LOSER"	"SUBJECT:  SHEPHARD\n\nSTATUS:  ACCIDENTAL DEATH\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nDISPLACER SELF-TELEPORT MISHAP"
"OF_BOOT0TITLE"	"Boot Camp"
"OF0A0"	"OPPOSING FORCE"
"OF1A1TITLE"	"INCOMING"
"OF1A3TITLE"	"WELCOME TO BLACK MESA"
"OF1A5TITLE"	"\"WE ARE PULLING OUT\""
"OF2A1TITLE"	"MISSING IN ACTION"
"OF2A4TITLE"	"FRIENDLY FIRE"
"OF3A1TITLE"	"WE ARE NOT ALONE"
"OF3A3TITLE"	"CRUSH DEPTH"
"OF4A1TITLE"	"VICARIOUS REALITY"
"OF4A4TITLE"	"PIT WORM'S NEST"
"OF5A1TITLE"	"FOXTROT UNIFORM"
"OF6A1TITLE"	"\"THE PACKAGE\""
"OF6A4TITLE"	"WORLDS COLLIDE"
"OF7A0TITLE"	"CONCLUSION"
"C4A1TITLE"	"XEN"
"BCROPES01"	"TOUCH ROPES TO ATTACH TO THEM\nCLIMB UP AND DOWN ROPES BY LOOKING IN \nTHE DIRECTION YOU WISH TO TRAVEL AND \nPRESSING THE FORWARD KEY\nPRESS THE JUMP KEY OR CLIMB OFF THE\nBOTTOM TO DETACH FROM THE ROPE"
"BCROPES02"	"ONCE ATTACHED TO ROPES\nPRESS THE MOVEMENT KEYS TO AFFECT\nDIRECTION OF SWINGING MOVEMENT\nPRESS THE JUMP KEY TO DETACH AT ANY TIME"
"BCROPES03"	"WHEN SWINGING ON ROPES PRESS THE JUMP\nKEY TO LET GO AND TRAVEL IN THE DIRECTION\nOF SWINGING MOVEMENT"
"BCROPES04"	""
"BCPISTOL01"	"TO INCREASE THE ACCURACY OF THE DESERT\nEAGLE PRESS THE ATTACK2 KEY TO ACTIVATE\nAND DEACTIVATE THE LASER SIGHT"
"BCRIFLE01"	"PRESS ATTACK2 KEY TO ACTIVATE THE ZOOM\nFUNCTION OF THE SNIPER RIFLE"
"BCNVISION"	"PRESS THE NIGHT VISION GOGGLE KEY\nTO ACTIVATE NIGHT VISION GOGGLES"


//Scientist Common
"absolutely"	"Absolutely."
"absolutelynot"	"Absolutely not."
"administrator"	"I suspected this could happen but the Administrator just would not listen."
"afellowsci"	"A fellow scientist."
"ahfreeman"	"Ah, Freeman."
"alienapeal"	"Do you think we should appeal to the alien authorities?"
"alientrick"	"Do you suspect some alien subterfuge behind this failure?"
"allnominal"	"Yes, this all looks nominal."
"alright"	"Alright."
"analysis"	"I am rather looking forward to this analysis, aren't you?"
"announcer"	"Did you understand that last announcement?"
"areyouthink"	"Are you thinking what I'm thinking?"
"asexpected"	"As I expected."
"beenaburden"	"Have I been that much of a burden?"
"beverage"	"Have you been able to get the beverage machine to work yet?"
"bloodsample"	"Wouldn't you like to get one of these blood samples under a microscope?"
"cantbeserious"	"You can't be serious."
"cantbeworse"	"It can't get any worse than this."
"canttakemore"	"I can't take much more of this."
"cascade"	"Aren't you a bit worried about that exponential cascade scenario we discussed?"
"catchone"	"Shouldn't we try to capture a specimen?"
"chaostheory"	"Do you still say there's nothing to chaos theory?"
"checkatten"	"Are you sure you checked the Eigen attenuators?"
"completelywrong"	"You are completely wrong."
"containfail"	"It appears the containment system has completely failed."
"correcttheory"	"Are you one hundred percent sure that theory of yours is correct?"
"delayagain"	"Do you think we should delay for another recalibration?"
"didyouhear"	"Did you hear that?"
"dinner"	"Are you seriously suggesting that all of these beings are here to dine on us?"
"dontconcur"	"I don't concur."
"dontgothere"	"No, don't go that way!"
"dontknow"	"I really don't know."
"dontwantdie"	"No, I don't want to die!"
"donuteater"	"Do you know who ate all the donuts?"
"doyousmell"	"Do you smell what I smell?"
"evergetout"	"Will we ever make it out of here?"
"erseen"	"Have you ever seen anything like this?"
"excellentteam"	"With my brains and your brawn we'll make an excellent team."
"excuse"	"Excuse me, Gordon."
"fascinating"	"Don't you find this all rather fascinating?"
"fellowscientist"	"Glad to oblige a fellow scientist."
"fine"	"Fine. You won't even know I'm here."
"freeman"	"Freeman."
"freemanalive"	"Freeman! Who would have thought you'd still be alive?"
"fusionshunt"	"I certainly hope those backup fusion shunts are in good shape today."
"getoutalive"	"I just want to get out of this alive."
"getoutofhere"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"goodpaper"	"I believe this will make for a notable paper, don't you?"
"goodtoseeyou"	"Ah, it's good to see you."
"gottogetout"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"greetings"	"Greetings!"
"greetings2"	"Greetings."
"headcrab"	"These crab creatures have a unique parasitic strategy, don't you think?"
"heal1"	"Let me take care of that wound for you."
"heal2"	"This should make you feel better."
"heal3"	"Allow me to treat that injury."
"heal4"	"I can give you something for the pain."
"heal5"	"Don't worry, I am a doctor."
"scientisthearsomething"	"Did you hear something?" //tag
"scientisthello"	"Hello." //Added scientist tag
"scientisthello2"	"Hello." //Added scientist tag
"hellofreeman"	"Ah, hello, Gordon Freeman. It's good to see you."
"hellofromlab"	"You are from the Anomalous Materials Lab. Yes, I recognize you."
"hellothere"	"Hello there."
"hideglasses"	"Someone has hidden my glasses again."
"holdstill"	"Hold still, this won't hurt a bit."
"hopenominal"	"I hope those containment parameters are still nominal."
"hopeyouknow"	"I certainly hope you know what you're doing."
"howinteresting"	"How interesting, just look at that."
"hungryyet"	"Is anyone else getting hungry?"
"ibelieveso"	"I believe so."
"idontthinkso"	"I don't think so."
"ihearsomething"	"I hear something."
"illwait"	"I'll wait."
"illwaithere"	"I'll wait right here."
"importantspecies"	"Another important species revealed in action."
"improbable"	"A failure of this magnitude is extremely improbable."
"imsure"	"I'm sure of it."
"inconclusive"	"It's inconclusive."
"inmesstoo"	"Ah, Freeman. I see you are in this mess too."
"ipredictedthis"	"I predicted all of this, you know. All of it!"
"istay"	"I'll stay here."
"iwounded"	"I seem to be wounded... but I can keep going."
"iwounded2"	"Well, I seem to be seriously wounded."
"iwoundedbad"	"I don't think I can last much longer."
"justasked"	"Didn't you just ask me that?"
"lambdalab"	"I hope those people in the Lambda Lab can get this under control."
"leadtheway"	"Lead the way."
"leavingme"	"What? You're leaving me here?"
"letmehelp"	"Let me help you."
"scientistletsgo"	"Let's go." //Added scientist tag
"letstrythis"	"Let's try this."
"letyouin"	"Wait a minute and I'll let you in."
"limitsok"	"This is all within theoretical limits."
"lowervoice"	"Kindly lower your voice."
"luckwillchange"	"It's highly probable that our luck will change, don't you agree?"
"madness"	"This is madness! I'm getting out of here!"
"needsleep"	"I'd give my right hemisphere for a few hours of sleep."
"neverseen"	"Fascinating. I never suspected such things could be."
"newhevsuit"	"Ah, you have one of the new HEV suits. That should be very useful."
"newsample"	"Any ideas on the origin of that new sample?"
"nodoubt"	"I have no doubt."
"nogrant"	"Well, there goes our grant money."
"noguess"	"I couldn't even venture a guess."
"noidea"	"You have no idea what is going on, do you?"
"noo"	"No."
"nooo"	"No!"
"noplease"	"No! Please!"
"notcertain"	"I'm not certain."
"nothostile"	"The alien species can't possibly all be hostile, can they?"
"notsure"	"I am not at all sure."
"odorfromyou"	"I hope that odor isn't coming from you."
"ofcourse"	"Of course!"
"ofcoursenot"	"Of course not!"
"okgetout"	"Okay, let's get out of here."
"okihope"	"Okay, I hope you know what you're doing."
"organicmatter"	"Well, the dimensional breach is definitely transmitting organic matter."
"peculiarmarks"	"Why just look at those peculiar markings."
"peculiarodor"	"Hm, what a peculiar odor."
"perfectday"	"This analysis is going to run perfectly today, don't you think?"
"perhaps"	"Perhaps."
"positively"	"Positively."
"purereadings"	"Wouldn't it be fantastic to get some pure readings for a change?"
"recalculate"	"Don't you think we should recalculate those resonance dampening factors again?"
"reconsider"	"I don't suppose you'd reconsider?"
"repeat"	"You know, you repeat yourself sometimes."
"reportflux"	"I must remember to report that fluctuation."
"rescueus"	"Surely someone will come and rescue us."
"ridiculous"	"Don't be ridiculous!"
"scientistright"	"Right!" //tag
"rightwayout"	"Are you sure this is the right way?"
"rumorclean"	"The military cleanup is just a paranoid rumor, isn't it?"
"runtest"	"I wonder if I should run that test again."
"sci_aftertest"	"You'll just have to wait until after the test."
"sci_alone"	"Please, leave me alone until after the experiment."
"sci_bother"	"I can't be bothered right now."
"sci_busy"	"Excuse me, Gordon, but I'm rather busy now."
"sci_fear6"	"Oh no!"
"sci_fear7"	"Oh dear!"
"sci_fear11"	"Oh my!"
"sci_fear12"	"My goodness!"
"sci_fear13"	"No!"
"sci_fear14"	"Get back!"
"sci_pain3"	"No!"
"sci_pain6"	"No!"
"sci_pain7"	"No!"
"sci_pain8"	"No!"
"sci_pain9"	"Stop!"
"sci_pain10"	"No!"
"sci_somewhere"	"Weren't you supposed to be in the test chamber half an hour ago?"
"scream10"	"No!"
"scream11"	"Stop!"
"scream12"	"Stop!"
"scream13"	"No!"
"seencup"	"Have you seen my coffee cup?"
"shakeunification"	"This should shake up those grand unification boys, hm?"
"shutdownchart"	"Now where did I leave that shutdown procedure chart?"
"shutup"	"Shut up."
"shutup2"	"Shut up."
"simulation"	"Most of the simulation results are perfectly acceptable, you know."
"slowingyou"	"I'm slowing you down, am I?"
"smellburn"	"Do you smell something burning?"
"softethics"	"You aren't going soft on that ethics issue again, are you?"
"sorryimleaving"	"Sorry, I'm leaving now."
"somethingfoul"	"I believe something smells quite foul here."
"startle5"	"Oh no."
"startle6"	"Oh no."
"startle7"	"Oh no."
"startle8"	"Oh no."
"startle9"	"Oh no."
"statusreport"	"Did you submit your status report to the Administrator today?"
"stench"	"What is that stench?"
"stimulating"	"I think it's rather stimulating, don't you?"
"stop1"	"This is as far as I go."
"stop2"	"I refuse to go another step."
"stop3"	"You're going to have to leave me here, Gordon."
"stop4"	"I'm going to stay here and wait for my colleagues."
"stopasking"	"Stop asking that question."
"stopattacking"	"Stop attacking, he's a friend!"
"survival"	"Do you recall any of those emergency survival procedures?"
"thatsodd"	"That's odd."
"theoretically"	"Theoretically."
"thiswillhelp"	"This should help."
"tunedtoday"	"All displacement modulators were tuned today, weren't they?"
"tunnelcalc"	"Are you running those tunneling lattice calculations again?"
"uselessphd"	"Fat lot of good that Ph.D. does me now, hm?"
"weartie"	"Why do we all have to wear these ridiculous ties?"
"whatnext"	"Well, do you have any idea what to do next?"
"whatyoudoing"	"My God, what are you doing?"
"whocansay"	"Who can say?"
"whoresponsible"	"Who is responsible for this mess?"
"whyaskme"	"Why are you asking me?"
"whyleave"	"Why are you leaving me here?"
"yees"	"Yes."
"scientistyes"	"Yes." //tag
"yes2"	"Yes."
"yes3"	"Yes."
"yesletsgo"	"Yes, let's go."
"youinsane"	"Are you insane? Stop attacking, immediately!"
"youlookbad"	"You look terrible."
"youlookbad2"	"You look terrible."
"youneedmedic"	"It appears that you need medical attention right away."
"youwounded"	"Ah, you've been wounded."


//Intro
"g3_copy"	"Roger that, we copy."
"g7_copy_hq"	"Copy that, HQ."
"g7_goose3_down"	"Holy shit! Goose 3 is down! Goose 3 is down!"
"g7_view_lz"	"Anyone out there got a good view of the LZ yet?"
"g7_watch_vector"	"Watch your vector, Goose 3. It's getting little tight in here."
"hq_proceed"	"Okay, Goose 7. Proceed to sector 112 LZ and rendezvous with Alpha Bravo Tango. Over."
"hq_the_hell"	"What the hell is going on out there?"
"w6_cant_see"	"Negative, Goose 7. I can see some activity up there, but I can't tell what it is."
"w6_watchit"	"Watch it Goose 7, you've got something coming up on your-"
"intro_FG01"	"Man, if this is another 'Search and Rescue' operation I’m gonna be pissed."
"intro_FG02"	"Yeah, I'm gonna be pissed too when I gotta search and rescue your sorry ass."
"intro_FG03"	"Hey, Shephard! I think Jackson here's got the hots for you."
"intro_FG04"	"Screw you, Tower!"
"intro_FG05"	"Hey man, where the hell are we anyway?"
"intro_FG06"	"Well, the pilot thought we were headin' to your mother's house, heh. So far this all looks familiar."
"intro_FG07"	"Yeah, that's real cute, Jackson."
"intro_FG08"	"Anytime, anywhere!"
"intro_FG09"	"Hey man, you smell that?"
"intro_FG10"	"Smell what?"
"intro_FG11"	"Smells like... smells like another babysittin' job to me, man!"
"intro_FG12"	"Heh heh, no shit, man!"
"intro_FG13"	"Babysittin' job my ass. This has training mission written all over it. Why else would they have kept our orders from us for so long, huh?"
"intro_FG14"	"Yeah, what the hell is that all about? Throwin' our asses in this hunk of junk and not even tellin' us what we're goin' in for, man."
"intro_FG15"	"Sir, yes, sir!"
"intro_FG16"	"Well, I don't really give a damn what we're going in for. Long as I get to kill me somethin'."
"intro_FG17"	"I heard that."
"intro_FG18"	"Hey you sleepin’ over there? You want me to fluff your pillow for ya?"
"intro_FG19"	"What the hell kind of mission is this anyway? We didn’t even get a briefing before take-off!"

//Opposing-Force Scientist Specific
"advance"	"Killing me will in no way advance this situation."
"scientistcorporal"	"Hello. Uh, you're a corporal, aren't you?" //tag
"fix"	"Hello, soldier. I hope you're here to fix this mess."
"getalong"	"Oh no, you're one of the... them. Can't we just get along?"
"please"	"Please! Don't kill me."
"saved"	"A soldier! I'm saved at last!"
"of1a1_sc01"	"Three, four, five... One, two..."
"of1a1_sc02"	"Three, four, five..."
"of1a1_sc03"	"Oh, you've woken up. Corporal Shephard, is it? I've read the tag on your uniform. I'm glad to see my life saving efforts weren't in vain. I can't say the same for him. I'm afraid you have been through a serious accident. Most of your friends didn't make it. I was hoping that you soldiers had come to rescue us, but now it seems we are all in the same situation. I think I saw a radio near the crash site where I found you. Perhaps you can go there and radio for help?"
"of1a1_sc04"	"I'm afraid these troops aren't going to make it. I hope you have better luck out there, or I fear none of us will get through this alive."
"of1a1_sc05"	"Have you ever seen such a magnificent species? These crabs can completely control their hosts' nervous system. Can you imagine what the next stage of mutation looks like?"
"of1a5_sc01"	"No, I haven't, but a friend of mine..."
"of1a5_sc02"	"I don't know! I've never seen that species before!"
"of1a6_sc01"	"You've got to believe me. Freeman could be anywhere!"
"of2a2_sc01"	"I don't know what's worse. You soldiers under orders to silence the facility or these vile aliens."
"of2a3_sc01"	"When all the fighting started, I hid myself here. I don't think any of them above have survived."
"of3a2_sc01"	"Put that thing down! Why must you security guards always insist on playing with our prototypes."
"of3a2_sc02"	"Be careful. No, not again!"
"of3a4_sc01"	"I'm afraid I've trapped myself here to escape those beasts. Would you be so kind as to operate that transporter?"
"of3a4_sc02"	"Thank you for releasing me. I can help you access any secured area in this lab."
"of4a1_sc01"	"Ah, yes, Walter. We were finally able to successfully detach one of the Barnacle creatures from its point of gestation. As before, we were still only able to coerce the creature into latching onto organic materials. Unfortunately, the Administrator has called me down to the Anomalous Materials lab this morning for an important experiment, so I don't have any time to further my analysis. Take specimen number 1176 and log anything else you can find."
"c1a3_sci_rescued"	"Rescued at last! Thank God you're here!"
"c3a2_sci_portopen"	"It's ready! You must go! Now!"
"c3a2_sci_forever"	"Hurry up, Freeman, I can't keep it open forever!"
"tr_holo_pipeduck"	"To get into these pipes, you'll have to signal your suit to make a duck jump. You'll want to stand right at the mouth of the pipe and continue to press forward, then jump up and while you're in mid air, go into a crouch. It's tricky, but you'll find it comes in handy."

//Otis
"aliencombat"	"So, do you guys train for alien combat, or is this just a special occasion?"
"aliens"	"Fighting aliens is not in my job description!"
"otisalright"	"All right, all right." //tag
"another"	"That's right! I got another one!"
"otisass"	"Oh man, do you smell that?"
"beer"	"I tell you, wouldn't you just love a cold beer right about now? I know I would."
"behind"	"Hey, I'm right behind you!"
"bigboned"	"Oh no, I'm not fat! I'm just what you call big-boned."
"breath"	"Don't hold your breath."
"bridge"	"And I was supposed to play bridge tonight!"
"bring"	"You just think it's all about you!"
"bully"	"You know, nobody likes a bully!"
"buttugly"	"I think I got a ripe one!"
"candy"	"Mmm... candy!"
"cantfigure"	"Whoa, I can't wrap my brain around it."
"chili"	"It smells worse than a chili cook off!"
"chump"	"Watch where you aim that thing, pally!"
"close"	"Oh, that was way too close for comfort!"
"closet"	"Maybe I should guard that closet over there."
"cousin"	"Huh, my cousin is the one that got me this job!"
"damn"	"Damn! Cut it out!"
"dejavu"	"Now, either I have déjà vu, or you repeat yourself."
"die"	"Die! Die! Die!"
"diealone"	"Okay, heh, I don't wanna die alone!"
"dontask"	"Now, I'm probably not the one you wanna ask."
"dontguess"	"I don't think so."
"donthurtem"	"I knew we couldn't trust you guys!"
"dontmake"	"Now don't make me go and throw down or something!"
"doubt"	"Huh, I very much doubt it."
"firepl"	"Hmm, I'd love to hang that over my fireplace! Y'know, if I had one."
"friends"	"Hey, I thought we were becoming friends."
"getanyworse"	"Eh, how much worse can it get?"
"gladof"	"Hey, I bet you're glad you got me with ya, huh?"
"go_on"	"Yeah, I think I'll stay here, and die!"
"gotone"	"Ha ha, I can't believe I got that guy!"
"hearsomething"	"Hey, do you hear something?"
"otishell"	"Hell if I know." //tag
"otishello"	"Hello, soldier, sir."
"help"	"Okay, if you're sure you don't want my help."
"hey"	"Hey, soldier!"
"otishitbad"	"Okay, now see, heh, that one's going to slow me down. Yeah, ow."
"hiya"	"Hiya, sir."
"otisillwait"	"I'll just wait here."
"imdead"	"Damn it! I knew I was gonna be the one killed!"
"otisimhit"	"Eh, it's only a flesh wound."
"insurance"	"I hope the military has good medical insurance."
"janitor"	"I'm so glad I didn't take the janitor job. Yuck!"
"job"	"This job is not worth dyin' for!"
"joinyou"	"Sure, I have nothing better to do!"
"leavealone"	"Hey, what did they ever do to you?"
"leftovers"	"I'll get the leftovers!"
"letsgo"	"All right, let's go!"
"live"	"I have a better chance of survival with you!"
"mall"	"I gotta say, that mall security job is looking pretty good right now."
"maybe"	"Maybe so, maybe no."
"otismedic"	"Medic! See, now I always wanted to say that." //tag
"mom"	"My mom is gonna worry when I don't make it home tonight!"
"otisno"	"Uh... no, no." //tag
"noise"	"Did you hear that weird noise?"
"nope"	"Nope."
"nosir"	"No, sir."
"notalone"	"Don't leave me alone here!"
"noway"	"No way."
"of1a1_ot01"	"Sorry, uh, Shephard, sir, uh. See, now I was told not to open this door for ya until you agreed to help us. Besides, you wouldn't wanna go out there without your armor vest anyway. I left it for you where the other soldiers are getting treated. Just, uh, you know, come on back here when you've found it."
"of1a1_ot02"	"Okay, Shephard, I see you found your power vest. That should keep you safe out there. See, now I've heard rumors that you troops may not actually be here to rescue us. Just don't forget about us out there, all righty? Okay, I'll let you through now."
"of1a1_ot03"	"Good luck, sir."
"of1a1_ot04"	"Personally, I think if we could find more soldiers like you, we may come out of this a-okay."
"of1a5_ot01"	"Those poor bastards."
"of2a6_ot01"	"I'm not sure I can trust you, but I don't know what else to do at this point. If you make it out of here, don't forget me."
"of3a2_ot01"	"Huh! What's this? Some sort of transporter gun?"
"of6a3_ot01"	"Now, now, don't hurt me, and I'll tell you a secret. I've been hiding up here listening. These Black Ops have some sort of bomb. I think they're plannin' on blowin' up the base. Now-now, why do you think they would do such a thing?"
"onry"	"I can get pretty ornery when I'm angry."
"quarter"	"Hey, uh, you wouldn't have a quarter I can borrow, would ya?"
"quitit"	"Hey, quit it now! I mean it!"
"reputation"	"So, my reputation precedes me."
"rightdirection"	"Are you leading us in the right direction?"
"scar"	"Aw, that's going to leave a scar."
"seethat"	"Oh yeah, baby, did you see that?"
"seeya"	"Okay, um, I'll see you later then?"
"slowingyoudown"	"You go on. I'm just slowing you down!"
"soldier"	"All right, a soldier! I'm saved!"
"somethingmoves"	"Oh man. Did you see somethin' move?"
"somuch"	"I'm only willin' to take so much abuse."
"soundsbad"	"That definitely sounds alien."
"standguard"	"I'll, uh, I'll stay here and pretend to guard this area."
"stupidmachines"	"Stupid machines! Why don't these ever seem to work?"
"suppose"	"I suppose."
"talkmuch"	"Do you speak English much?"
"teamup"	"Oh yeah, sure, we'll work better as a team."
"together"	"See, now, we have a better chance if we stay together."
"tomb"	"That's it, I've had it!"
"tooyoung"	"I'm too young to die! Okay, I'm not, but I got a lot of meals left to eat."
"virgin"	"I don't wanna die a virgin."
"otiswatchit"	"Hey, control your weapon, buddy!" //tag
"wuss"	"Believe it or not, I was a wuss in high school! I know, it's hard to believe."
"yeah"	"Yeah, sure."
"otisyes"	"Ye, uh-huh." //tag
"otisyessir"	"Yes, sir." //tag
"youbet"	"You betcha."
"yourback"	"I got your back!"
"yourside"	"Hey, I'm on your side! Don't kill me!"
"yup"	"Yup."

//Radio
"bootcamp0"	"I hear you loud and clear. We'll move to your position."
"of1a2_rd01"	"Shephard you're alive! Listen, we've been cut off pretty bad and orders are coming down to pull out. Repeat! Pull out! Apparently, they've got other plans for Black Mesa now. If you can make your way through the transit system, you can probably reach the surface where we are pulling out. Good luck! Over."
"of1a2_rd02"	"Get through the transit system to the extraction point. Don't-"
"of1a6_rd01"	"All units, retreat to the rally point. I say, retreat to the rally point. Orders have been changed. We are pulling out. The safety of any units left behind cannot be guaranteed."
"of2a3_rd01"	"Corporal Shephard, we've been left behind as well. We are onto your position now. Stand back from the maintenance door. We're gonna blow it!"
"of2a5_rd01"	"Mayday! Mayday! Anyone copy? This is Tango Charlie Four Zero Niner and we are under attack. Repeat! Black Operators... have opened fire on us. Request backup immediately! Over!"
"of4a3_rd01"	"X-Ray Zulu, are you there? We need backup in the waste sector! It's some sort of worm creature. Tower and Eddy are down, and I've lost contact with the rest of the squad. We need backup now! Now, damn it, now!"
"of6A2_rd01"	"Adrian? Is that you? Listen, we're hold up across the mortar field, but we're pinned down by a group of Black Ops. We'll open the bunker door, but you better get over here quick."

//Train
"broken_tram1"	"This train is-s-s...inbound from-from-from...Sector C. Please keep your limbs in-in-in-inside the train at all times."
"broken_tram2"	"...associate...associate...associate with a background in the areas of theo-theo-theo-theoretical physics-s-s, biotechnology or other high-tech d-d-disciplines, please contact our Civilian Recruitment D-d-division."
"broken_tram3"	"...a-a-a...a reminder to all B-Black Mesa Personnel: Regular radiation and biohazard s...creenings are a requirement of continued employment in-in-in the Black Mesa Research Facility."
"broken_tram4"	"Do-do-do not...do not attempt to open the doors until the tr-tr-train has come to a complete halt at-t-t the station platform.	"
"broken_tram5"	"Now arriving a-a-at..."

//Barney OF
"armedforces"	"Hi. What part of the armed forces are you with?"
"easily"	"You're not going to kill me that easily."
"OF1A5_BA01"	"Have you seen the new IG-88?"
"OF1A5_BA02"	"What the he... What is that, doc?"
"of6a4_ba01"	"Are you crazy? I'm not opening this door until someone turns that bomb off."
"of6a4_ba02"	"Phew, that was a close one! You better get in here."
"of6a4_ba03"	"It's not gonna be easy from here on out. The only way out is through the Level 4 Storage Unit, but it's a mess down there. The Black Ops were using it as a staging point until the aliens came in. If you do make it through, make sure you have them come back for us."
"of6a4_ba04"	"I guess you're a good guy, Corporal. Listen, you've got to get down below. There's something coming through and it's the nastiest looking thing yet. Some of your buddies went down there a while ago and I haven't seen them since. I've got some weapons I've piled up in here, you better take as much as you can carry, 'cause I think this is it. Good luck, Corporal."
"barneysir"	"Hello, soldier, sir."
"barneysoldier"	"All right, a soldier! Now we're gonna see some action."
"c1a2_ba_2zomb"	"It's okay, sir, I can take him!"
"c1a2_ba_4zomb"	"Argh, oh shit!"
"teamup2"	"Okay, I'll cover you."
"dobettertogether"	"Okay, we might live longer if we work together."
"imwithyou"	"Let's get the hell out of here."
"teamup1"	"Yeah, we might stand a better chance if we team up."
"gladtolendhand"	"Okay, why not? Didn't want to die alone anyway."
"barneyletsgo"	"Yeah, let's go."
"letsmoveit"	"Roger that. Let's run like hell."
"helpothers"	"Okay, I'll wait here and help anyone else who comes by."
"iwaithere"	"You go on without me."
"barneyslowingyoudown"	"Okay, I'll secure this area."
"barneyillwait"	"Yeah, I'll wait here."
"barneyseeya"	"See you later."
"barneystandguard"	"I'll stay here and guard this area."
"ba_stepoff"	"Hey, step off, buddy!"
"ba_iwish"	"I wish it hadn't come to this."
"ba_uwish"	"Heh, you're gonna wish you hadn't done that."
"ba_somuch"	"I only take so much and no more."
"ba_endline"	"End of the line for you."
"ba_dontmake"	"Don't make me do this."
"ba_tomb"	"What do you want on your tombstone?"

//HECU OF
"of1a6_fg01"	"Come in, Cooper. Do you copy? Forget about Freeman. We're abandoning the base. If you have any last bomb targets, mark them on the tactical map. Otherwise, get the hell out of there. Repeat, we are pulling out and commencing air strikes. Give us targets, or get below!"
"of1a6_fg02"	"Shephard, you've made it. I take it you didn't find Freeman? Forget it, Corporal. We are puling out. The air strike has started. Get to the hangar while we await evac."
"of1a6_fg03"	"I said get to the hangar, Shephard. That is an order."
"of1a6_fg04"	"Where's Freeman? We don't have time to mess around here."
"of1a6_fg05"	"I'm not lettin' you go until you talk."
"of2a1_fg01""You've got the get out of here. Listen to me, Shephard. Those things... they'll kill all of us."
"of2a4_fg01"	"Looks like somebody really screwed up, Corporal. Seems the brass bit off more than they could chew."
"of2a4_fg02"	"Yeah, well, forget about Freeman! We've got to save our own asses."
"of2a4_fg03"	"You with us, Corporal."
"of2a5_fg01"	"Shephard, what the hell were you doing down there? Listen, we need to get our asses down to the extraction point near Lambda sector. With any luck, we'll even get a shot at Freeman on our way out. Now, this transit system should take us there, but the door is sealed up pretty tight. Jeez, where's an engineer when you need one?"
"of2a5_fg02"	"Corporal, I don't think I'm gonna make it. I need a Medic... bad."
"of2a5_fg03"	"Don't worry, soldier. I'll have you fixed up in no time."
"of2a5_fg04"	"Thanks, doc."
"of2a6_fg01"	"Corporal, what the hell is going on here? Nobody told us about Black Operations in the mission briefing."
"of2a6_fg02"	"Yeah, I mean we're all on the same team, right? Right?"
"of2a6_fg03"	"Well, I'm not sure what their mission is, but we need to keep moving. There's gotta be a transit car somewhere on these tracks."
"of3a4_fg01"	"Don't go in there, Corporal. That... monster... wiped out my squad."
"of5a1_fg01"	"Hey, man, good to see ya. Wow, I can't believe you made it pass those masked freaks."
"of5a1_fg02"	"Those snipers have pinned us down here pretty good. We tried making a break for it, but they know we're here. They're just waitin' for their shots, and those bastards are patient."
"of5a1_fg03"	"Yeah, I'd love to turn the table on those guys. Get my hands on one of those rifles, show them a thing or two about patience."
"of5a1_fg04"	"Hey, with you here now we have the element of surprise on our site. They're not expecting three of us. Heh heh heh."
"of5a3_fg01"	"Shephard! Oh man. We thought you made evac already."
"of5a3_fg02"	"It's good to see you, sir. It's a real mess out there. I mean these... things are coming out of the damn walls. Ain't no way around them either. They just keep coming!"
"of5a3_fg03"	"We may just have enough fire power to push through now. At very least, we can give it our best shot."
"of5a3_fg04"	"I heard about some kind of big standoff at the dam up ahead. I say we make our break for it now. It ain't gonna get any better, that's for sure, and I bet they could use our help."
"of5a3_fg05"	"It's Shephard! Hey, stand back, and I'll cut it. We're gonna need your help."
"of6a1_fg01"	"Shephard! I don't know what those Black Ops are up to, but it doesn't involve getting us out of here alive. We've got no choice but to fight our way out!"
"of6a1_fg02"	"Let's go!"
"siryessir"	"Sir, yes, sir!"
"yessir"	"Sir, yes, sir!"
"post"	"This is my post, sir."
"stay"	"I've been ordered to stay here, sir."
"leave"	"Sir, I can't leave my post."

//VOX
"C1A0_0"	"Immediate medical attention required in Sector 27."
"C1A0_1"	"Operations personnel, report to Emergency Control Zone for contamination clean-up, Alpha 7 access required."
"C1A0_2"	"Attention. Supply Team required in Lower Maintenance Chamber Sub-Sector B."
"C1A0_3"	"Security breach detected in Silo 32."
"C1A0_4"	"Warning. Extreme radiation leak detected in Reactor Core 8. Time to reach minimum safe distance: 14 minutes."
"C1A0_5"	"Dr. Guthrie, report to Inspection Laboratory 6 immediately."
"C1A0_6"	"Attention. Dr. Freeman, report to Research Administration Center for questioning."
"C1A0_7"	"Remaining science personnel, report to Medical Laboratory 6 for radiation exposure inspection."
"C1A0_8"	"Warning. Severe damage detected in ventilation systems under Research Laboratory 2, evacuate area immediately."
"NA0"	"Access denied."
"NA1"	"Access is denied."

//Black Ops
"of2a5_bo01"	"Why do we always have to clean up a mess the grunts can't handle?"
"of2a5_bo02"	"Tell me about it. I just wanna deliver the package and get out of here."
"of2a5_bo03"	"Yeah. Sooner or later the grunts are gonna figure it out."
"of6a2_bo01"	"Be careful with that thing! One false move and this whole facility is gone."
"of6a2_bo02"	"I've got it covered. You just keep your eyes open, there are still some targets running around out there."
"of6a2_bo03"	"Get down! I hear something."

//G-Man
"of7a0_gm01"	"So, Corporal Shephard, we meet at last. Please, don't think that I've been avoiding you, a great many matters require my attention in these... troubled times. I do hope you understand, and now I require a further indulgence on your part. I cannot close my report until every loose end has been tied up. The biggest embarrassment has been Black Mesa facility, but I think that's finally taken care of itself..."
"of7a0_gm02"	"Quite so."
"of7a0_gm03"	"But there is still the lingering matter of witnesses. I admit I have a fascination with those who adapt and survive against all odds. They rather remind me of myself. If for no other reason, I have argued to preserve you for a time."
"of7a0_gm04"	"While I believe a civil servant like yourself understands the importance of... discretion, my employers are not quite so trusting, and rather than continually subject you to the irresistible human temptation of telling all, we have decided to... convey you to somewhere where you can do no possible harm, and where no harm can come to you.  I'm sure you can imagine there are worse alternatives."



//Hecu OF
"incoming"	"Incoming!"
"grenade"	"Grenade!"
"alert"	"Alien alert!"
"down"	"Get down!"
"bogies"	"We got bogies!"
"hostiles"	"Squad, we got hostiles!"
"alien"	"Alien movement!"
"clear"	"Clear this area!"
"cover"	"Take cover!"
"staydown"	"Squad, stay down!"
"fire"	"Fire in the hole!"
"damage"	"Sure, we can do more damage that way."
"six"	"I got your six."
"moving"	"Moving out, Corporal."
"gotit"	"You got it, Corporal. I'll be right behind you."
"hellout"	"Let's get the hell outta here."
"sir"	"Affirmative, sir."
"right"	"Right away, sir."
"command"	"At your command, sir!"
"notfail"	"I will not fail you, sir."
"yes"	"Yes, sir."
"hearsome"	"Hey, did you hear something?"
"hear"	"Sir, I heard something."
"secure"	"Okay, I'll secure this area."
"orders"	"I'll stay here and await further orders."
"scout"	"All right, you scout ahead."
"guardduty"	"Guard duty, eh?"
"oneshot"	"One shot, one kill."
"killer"	"I'm a natural born alien killer."
"sniper"	"Heh, sniper school sure paid off today."
"tag"	"I'll tag 'em, you bag 'em."
"corporal"	"Did you see that one, Corporal?"
"talking"	"That's what I'm talking about."
"take"	"Take this!"
"area"	"Area secure, sir."
"check"	"Okay, check in!"
"wantsome"	"You want some of me?"
"zone"	"Check your zone."
"watchit"	"Watch it, Corporal."
"watchfire"	"Watch your fire, sir."
"friendly"	"Friendly fire, friendly fire!"
"seensquad"	"Have you seen any other soldiers from my platoon?"
"current"	"The current situation is looking pretty grim."
"coverup"	"Government cover ups were not in my job description."
"chicken"	"This whole operation is out of control!"
"charge"	"Do you have any idea who's in charge of this operation?"
"bfeeling"	"I got a bad feeling about this mission."
"roger"	"Uh, roger that."
"quiet"	"Squad, quiet down."
"guard"	"I was told to guard this area."
"mission"	"Boy, this is some first mission."
"babysitting"	"I was told this is gonna be a baby sitting job."
"now"	"If only Drill Instructor Barnes could see me now."
"short"	"Just when I thought I was getting short, I've gotta pull this assignment."
"outof"	"Man, if we make it out of here alive, I'm gonna buy you all a round of beers. Hell, I'll buy the whole damn bar!"
"lost"	"I bet you can get lost in this place real easy."
"fubar"	"This mission is way beyond FUBAR."
"dogs"	"Man, my dogs are barking."
"disney"	"This place make boot camp seem like Disneyland."
"checkrecon"	"Recon team, check in!"
"flank"	"Flank 'em!"
"freaks"	"Let's kill these freaks!"
"recon"	"Go, recon!"
"rapidfire"	"Let's go, rapid fire!"
"sweep"	"Sweep that sector!"
"suppressing"	"I need suppressing fire!"
"marines"	"Let's go, marines!"
"moveup"	"Move up!"
"go"	"Let's go!"
"covering"	"Covering fire!"
"fgruntass"	"We're gonna kick your ass!"
"shephard"	"Shephard!"
"sore"	"Shephard! You're a sight for sore eyes."
"tosee"	"Sir! It's good to see another man in uniform."
"hellosir"	"Sir! Hello, sir!"
"imhit"	"I'm hit, but I'll hang tough."
"fwound"	"It's okay, sir. It's just a flesh wound."
"makeit"	"I don't think I can make it, sir."
"hitbad"	"Corporal, I'm hit pretty bad."
"critical"	"That last shot was critical. I can't go on."
"sdamage"	"I've taken serious damage, sir."
"needmedic"	"Sir, I think you may need a medic."
"hurt"	"You look pretty hurt, sir."
"hell"	"Corporal, you look like hell."
"feel"	"Man, Corporal. You look just like I feel."
"mister"	"Mister, you're going down!"
"nothing"	"You got nothing!"
"getsome"	"Get some!"
"corners"	"Watch those corners."
"backup"	"We need backup!"
"allclear"	"All clear, sir."
"busted"	"I'm pretty busted up, Corporal. I think I'm gonna need a medic."
"checkfire"	"Check your fire!"
"corporal_01"	"Corporal!"
"hecuhelp"	"Sir, you need medical attention ASAP."
"medic"	"Medic!"
"medical"	"Keeping you in one piece is proving to be quite a challenge."
"move"	"Move in!"
"no"	"Negative, sir."
"nohostiles"	"No sign of hostiles."
"nomovement"	"No movement on this level."
"retreat"	"Fall back!"
"sir_01"	"Sir!"
"stayalert"	"Stay alert, people."
"takecover"	"Take cover!"
"locksmith"	"Who needs a locksmith, eh, Shephard? Heh heh heh."
"stand"	"Stand back, Corporal. This should only take a minute."
"through"	"I'll have you through here in no time."
"blocked"	"Sorry, Corporal. This door is barricaded from the other side."
"thick"	"That barricade is way too thick."
"cutting"	"Cutting through this door is not a good idea."
"situations"	"Sorry, sir, I'm not trained for situations like this."
"sting"	"This might sting a bit."
"onepiece"	"Keeping you in one piece is proving to be quite a challenge."
"frosty"	"This outta keep you frosty, Corporal."
"nohealth"	"Sorry, sir. That's all I can do for you."
"restricted"	"I'm sorry, Corporal. This is a restricted area."
"restricted2"	"This is a restricted area, soldier!"
"thanks"	"Thanks, Corporal."

//Drill Instructor
"dr2_add01"	"You eyeballin' me, boy?"
"dr2_add02"	"Are you touchin' me, dirtbag?"
"dr2_add03"	"What is your major malfunction, dirtbag?"
"dr2_add04"	"It's time to kick ass and chew bubble gum, and I'm all out of bubble gum!"
"dr2_add05"	"I eat concertina wire and piss napalm!"
"dr2_add06"	"God has a hard-on for Marines."
"dr2_add07"	"I eat Green Berets for breakfast!"
"dr2_add08"	"You'd best get your head on straight!"
"dr2_add09"	"Soldier, you are all ate up!"
"dr2_add10"	"Dirtbag! I will break you down like an M16!"
"dr2_add11"	"I smell smoke! And where there's smoke, there's fire! You better move it, soldier!"
"dr2_add12"	"I will smoke you like a Cuban cigar!"
"dr2_add13"	"Drop and give me twenty!"
"dr2_add14"	"Get down and break them elbows!"
"dr2_add15"	"What's your first general order, dirtbag?"
"dr2_add16"	"Where you from, soldier? Texas! Holy cow! You know what comes from Texas, don't you?"
"dr2_add17"	"Can I be in charge around here? Well, thank you very much!"
"dr2_add18"	"You had better square yourself away, maggot!"
"dr2_add19"	"You better move like you've got a purpose!"
"barracks01"	"Rise and shine, ladies! My name is Senior Drill Instructor Dwight T. Barnes. The first and last words I wanna hear out of your stinkin' holes is 'Sir!' Do I make myself clear?"
"barracks02"	"My goal is simple: As a right now you are all maggots! You will not speak until spoken to, you will not sleep unless told to do so! When I ask you to jump, you will reply with 'How high?!' Do you get me?"
"barracks03"	"What's your name, dirtbag?"
"barracks04"	"Sound off like you got a pair!"
"barracks05"	"Corporal Shephard, huh? Looks more like corporal 'Dog Meat' to me! Seems your name was mysteriously bumped to the top of the advanced training list. My suggestion to you is to get your ass down to the training center and report to Drill Instructor Sharp ASAP. Now move it, Corporal!"
"barracks06"	"One! Two! Three! Four!"
"barracks07"	"You call that a push-up? All the way down!"
"barracks08"	"One! Two! Three! Four! I! Love! The Marine! Corp!"
"fifthroom01"	"Holy sheep shit, you made it! What's that on your vest, soldier? Did that sting a little? Well suck it up and drive on! I'm not through with you yet! Proceed through that door into the small staging room and await my instruction."
"firstroom01"	"All right, maggot, listen up! I don't care what your previous outfit was like, but around here we do things my way! Follow my instructions carefully and by the end of the day I'll have you eating danger and crapping victory! Now move your butt, soldier! I will meet you on the other side in the armory."
"fourthroom01"	"You're gonna have to pick the pace, dirtbag! My beloved Corp does not have the patience to wait around for your worthless butt!"
"fourthroom02"	"The following areas will simulate many of the environmental hazards you are likely to encounter in the field. Run through it as quickly as you can and try to avoid taking too much damage. A dead marine is a worthless marine! I will see you up ahead if you can make it through alive."
"intro01"	"Do you have a problem, private? I will give you your orders when we have reached the LZ. You got that, soldier?"
"intro02"	"Okay, listen up, people! We have an extremely hostile situation on our hand."
"intro03"	"Recon has not been able to determine the amount of opposition, so let's keep this tight. Your mission is to get- Shit! Goddamn it!"
"livefire01"	"Okay, soldier! This is a live fire exercise! This run will give you a taste of what it's like to be in the field. Keep your head low and move between cover! I wanna see your face in the dirt, soldier!"
"livefire02"	"Go! Go! Go!"
"livefire03"	"Climb that rope ladder! Get your ass up there!"
"livefire04"	"Hit the dirt, soldier! Move it! Move it! Move it!"
"livefire05"	"Keep your head down!"
"livefire06"	"You better move like you've got a purpose!"
"livefire07"	"Stay low!"
"livefire08"	"Keep your ass down!"
"livefire09"	"Get your ass down, or it will get blown off!"
"livefire10"	"Well, I'll be damned! You actually managed to make it through my favorite trainin' exercise in one piece!"
"livefire11"	"Very good, soldier! Move on for your next phase of training!"
"oc101"	"Move it! Move it!"
"oc102"	"All right, maggot. Let's see if you can move your butt through my obstacle course."
"oc103"	"On your mark! Get set! Go! Go! Go!"
"oc104"	"Run up and over those platforms! Move! Move! Move!"
"oc105"	"Duck! Now jump! Get your sorry ass moving!"
"oc106"	"Get your ass down that hill! Scale that wall! Hurry it up! My dear sweet grandmother moves faster than you, dirtbag!"
"oc106a"	"Get your ass down that hill!"
"oc106b"	"Scale that wall!"
"oc106c"	"Hurry it up!"
"oc106d"	"My dear sweet grandmother moves faster than you, dirtbag!"
"oc107"	"Do not fall in that water! Get over that beam! Move it maggot!"
"oc107a"	"Do not fall in that water!"
"oc107b"	"Get over that beam!"
"oc107c"	"Move it maggot!"
"oc108"	"I thought we were training soldiers here! Are you trying to embarrass me?"
"oc109"	"Proceed to the next area. Come on, double time it! Move! Move! Move!"
"pistol01"	"Your weapon is your best friend. It is your only friend! And to be more effective, soldier, you must master your weapon!"
"pistol02"	"On the table, you will see your standard issue sidearm. Pick it up and step over to the pistol range. The object of this exercise is to familiarize yourself with the functions and use of your weapon. The goal is for you to place six shots within the inner circle of each target. You may begin!"
"pistol03"	"You may proceed to the next section of the training course."
"rifle01"	"This exercise will train you in the use of a long range sniper rifle. Proceed to the table, pick up the sniper rifle, and position yourself on the firing line."
"rifle02"	"In this exercise, you will be firing at targets both moving and stationary at medium, long, and extreme ranges. As you will notice, your sniper rifle comes equipped with a scope. Use this scope to magnify your view, making the distant targets easier to see."
"rifle03"	"In the distance, you will notice three stationary targets partially concealed. Hit each of these targets to advance to the next stage of targets."
"rifle04"	"Good! Now let's see how you do with simple moving targets at that range, soldier!"
"rifle05"	"Make sure to take careful aim, soldier! Patience is key for those crucial shots."
"rifle06"	"Very good! Now let's see if you can hit the moving targets at long range! Make sure to take your time and line up those shots, soldier."
"rifle07"	"Not bad, not bad at all, soldier! Now let's see if you can do the same at extreme range!"
"rifle08"	"Unbelievable! You can actually shoot! I'd actually consider lettin' you cover my ass in a firefight."
"rifle09"	"I'm finished with you, soldier! Proceed to the next area and report to the next Drill Instructor."
"rope01"	"Let's see if you can climb faster than you can run! Ready?"
"rope02"	"Very good! Maybe there's hope for you yet. Now, do you wanna to come up here and try to knock me off?"
"rope03"	"You can definitely climb better than you can run. Now let's see if you can use these ropes for more than just simple climbing."
"rope04"	"Jump! Catch that rope and use your momentum to swing across that water!"
"rope05"	"What is your problem, soldier? Get back up and try it again!"
"rope05b"	"What is your problem, soldier? Get back up and try again! I do not have all day, ladies!"
"rope06"	"This might take more coordination than you have, soldier. I want you to swing from rope to rope and meet me at the end of the course."
"rope07"	"I'm almost impressed, soldier! Meet me in the next section and let's see if I can shake you up a bit."
"secondroom01"	"Mounted on the wall below me, you will see a PCV. This is a Powered Combat Vest. Use it correctly, and I guarantee it will save your life. Your PCV is able to recharge from battery power, or it can interface and recharge with commercial, military, and HEV charging stations."
"secondroom02"	"What are you waiting for? Grab that PCV and get it fully charged! Trust me, maggot, you're gonna need it! I'll meet you in the next area to demonstrate some of your vest's capabilities."
"seventhroom01"	"Well, I'll be damned! You may just have what it takes to be a soldier. Now double time it over to the next portion of your training."
"sixthroom01"	"In addition to providing protection, your PCV has other capabilities. Once the light goes out, the door in front of you will open. Activate your night vision goggles to navigate this maze and exit on the other side. Now move like you've got a purpose!"
"squad01"	"All right, dirtbag, you've proven yourself a capable grunt! Now let's see if there's any leadership qualities in that sorry carcass of yours. To became an effective leader, you must familiarize yourself with the skill set of each soldier in your platoon."
"squad02"	"The first type of soldier you will meet is the Engineer. Engineers have a knack for getting you in and out of places that are otherwise inaccessible. Take charge and have him follow you to the sealed door."
"squad03"	"As you can see, this soldier may prove quite useful in the field. Once you've breached the room, proceed through the door and meet the next type of soldier."
"squad04"	"The Medic can be one of the most valued soldiers on the field. They have the ability to heal both you and your fellow squad members. To receive medical attention, simply hold down your use key and the Medic will apply first aid. Once the Medic has attended to your wounds, proceed to the next area to complete your training."
"squad05"	"Listen up, soldier! During the course of your missions, you may not be in direct contact with your squad. In these situations, you will need to utilize any available military radios. These radios can be used to call in reinforcements or gain vital military intelligence."
"squad06"	"Approach the radio and use it, soldier!"
"squad07"	"Congratulations, soldier! You're no longer a low life maggot! I'm proud to say you are a soldier! I'm sure you'll be a credit to your unit. Now report to duty, soldier!"
"thirdroom01"	"The armored vest that your military has provided you with will keep you alive. Step onto the mark and this will be demonstrated for you."
"thirdroom02"	"As you can see, you are not dead. Your PCV absorbed the damage at the cost of some of its power.  Keep your PCV charged and your chances of survival in the field are very high. Proceed to the next area."
"add01"	"You eyeballin' me, boy?"
"add02"	"Are you touchin' me, dirtbag?"
"add03"	"What is your major malfunction?"
"add04"	"It's time to kick ass and chew bubble gum, and I'm all out of bubble gum!"
"add05"	"I eat concertina wire and piss napalm!"
"add06"	"God has a hard-on for Marines."
"add07"	"I eat Green Berets for breakfast!"
"add08"	"You had best get your head on straight, maggot!"
"add09"	"Soldier, you are all ate up!"
"add10"	"Son, I will break you down like an M16!"
"add11"	"I smell smoke! And where there's smoke, there's fire! You better move it, soldier!"
"add12"	"I will smoke you like a Cuban cigar!"
"add13"	"Drop and give me twenty, maggot!"
"add14"	"Get down and break them elbows!"
"add15"	"What's your first general order, dirtbag?"
"add16"	"Where you from, soldier? Texas! Holy cow! You know what comes from Texas, don't you?"
"add17"	"Can I be in charge around here? Well, thank you very much!"
"add18"	"You had better square yourself away, Marine!"
"add19"	"You better move like you've got a purpose!"
}
}