"lang"
{
"Language""english"
"Tokens"
{
//Neccessities
"CaptionMod_GameSaved"		"Game Saved..."
"HalfLife_Hologram"			"[Hologram] "
"HalfLife_Scientist"		"[Scientist] "
"HalfLife_HEV_Voice"		"[HEV] "
"HalfLife_VOX"		"[Announcer] "
"HalfLife_HECU"		"[HECU] "
"HalfLife_Rosenberg"		"[Rosenberg] "
"HalfLife_Security"	"[Security Officer] "
"HalfLife_Keller"		"[Keller] "

//Messages
"HTTITLE"	"Half-Life: Decay"
"HTINFOG1"	"SUBJECT:\nGina Cross\nFemale, age 31"
"HTINFOG2"	"EDUCATION:\nPh.D., Cal Tech, Applied Physics"
"HTINFOG3"	"POSITION:\nHazardous Environment Supervisor"
"HTINFOG4"	"ASSIGNMENT:\nAnomalous Materials Laboratory"
"HTINFOG5"	"CLEARANCE:\nLevel 4"
"HTINFOG6"	"ADMINISTRATIVE SPONSOR:\nClassified"
"HTINFOC1"	"SUBJECT:\nColette Green\nFemale, age 37"
"HTINFOC2"	"EDUCATION:\nPh.D., Carnegie Mellon, Electrical Engineering"
"HTINFOC3"	"POSITION:\nResearch Associate"
"HTINFOC4"	"ASSIGNMENT:\nAnomalous Materials Laboratory"
"HTINFOC5"	"CLEARANCE:\nLevel 4"
"HTINFOC6"	"ADMINISTRATIVE SPONSOR:\nClassified"
"GAMEOVER"	"SUBJECTS: CROSS AND GREEN\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubjects failed to effectively utilize\nhuman assets in achievement of goal."
"BOTHDEAD"	"SUBJECTS: CROSS AND GREEN\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nBoth subjects perished during\nthe Black Mesa incident."
"DEADGINA"	"SUBJECTS: CROSS AND GREEN\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubject Dr. Gina Cross perished\nduring the Black Mesa incident."
"DEADCOLETTE"	"SUBJECTS: CROSS AND GREEN\n\nSTATUS:  EVALUATION TERMINATED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nSubject Dr. Colette Green perished \nduring the Black Mesa incident."
"DEADALIEN"	"DRONE SUBJECTS: X-8973 AND R-4913\n\nDRONE STATUS: LIFE FUNCTION OVER\n\nTASK STATUS:\nFailure - material not recovered."
"SUCCESS"	"SUBJECTS: CROSS AND GREEN\n\nSTATUS:  MISSION COMPLETED\n\nPOSTMORTEM:\nHow are you gentlemen !!  You have\nsuccessfully completed this mission."
"DYLOCKED"	"ACCESS DENIED\n\nThe mission is locked ! You have\nto complete them in order starting\nfrom DY_ACCIDENT1\n\nMISSION IS LOCKED"
"HT01COMPLETE"	"DUAL ACCESS\n\nAccident survived.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT02COMPLETE"	"HAZARDOUS COURSE\n\nRosenberg escorted to surface.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT03COMPLETE"	"SURFACE CALL\n\nSatellite uplink established.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT04COMPLETE"	"RESONANCE\n\nDampening field reset attempted.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT05COMPLETE"	"DOMESTIC VIOLENCE\n\nSecurity guard rescued.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT07COMPLETE"	"CODE GREEN\n\nSatellite code uploaded.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT10COMPLETE"	"CROSSFIRE\n\nDisplacement beacon raised.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT11COMPLETE"	"INTENSITY\n\nBeam matrix activated.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT12COMPLETE"	"RIFT\n\nResonance reversal initiated.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT91COMPLETE"	"XEN ATTACKS\n\nXen crystals recovered.\n\nMISSION COMPLETE"
"HT01TITLE"	"DUAL ACCESS"
"HT02TITLE"	"HAZARDOUS COURSE"
"HT03TITLE"	"SURFACE CALL"
"HT04TITLE"	"RESONANCE"
"HT05TITLE"	"DOMESTIC VIOLENCE"
"HT07TITLE"	"CODE GREEN"
"HT10TITLE"	"CROSSFIRE"
"HT11TITLE"	"INTENSITY"
"HT12TITLE"	"RIFT"
"HT91TITLE"	"XEN ATTACKS"

//Scientist Common
"absolutely"	"Absolutely."
"absolutelynot"	"Absolutely not."
"administrator"	"I suspected this could happen but the Administrator just would not listen."
"afellowsci"	"A fellow scientist."
"ahfreeman"	"Ah, Freeman."
"alienapeal"	"Do you think we should appeal to the alien authorities?"
"alientrick"	"Do you suspect some alien subterfuge behind this failure?"
"allnominal"	"Yes, this all looks nominal."
"alright"	"Alright."
"analysis"	"I am rather looking forward to this analysis, aren't you?"
"announcer"	"Did you understand that last announcement?"
"areyouthink"	"Are you thinking what I'm thinking?"
"asexpected"	"As I expected."
"beenaburden"	"Have I been that much of a burden?"
"beverage"	"Have you been able to get the beverage machine to work yet?"
"bloodsample"	"Wouldn't you like to get one of these blood samples under a microscope?"
"cantbeserious"	"You can't be serious."
"cantbeworse"	"It can't get any worse than this."
"canttakemore"	"I can't take much more of this."
"cascade"	"Aren't you a bit worried about that exponential cascade scenario we discussed?"
"catchone"	"Shouldn't we try to capture a specimen?"
"chaostheory"	"Do you still say there's nothing to chaos theory?"
"checkatten"	"Are you sure you checked the Eigen attenuators?"
"completelywrong"	"You are completely wrong."
"containfail"	"It appears the containment system has completely failed."
"correcttheory"	"Are you one hundred percent sure that theory of yours is correct?"
"delayagain"	"Do you think we should delay for another recalibration?"
"didyouhear"	"Did you hear that?"
"dinner"	"Are you seriously suggesting that all of these beings are here to dine on us?"
"dontconcur"	"I don't concur."
"dontgothere"	"No, don't go that way!"
"dontknow"	"I really don't know."
"dontwantdie"	"No, I don't want to die!"
"donuteater"	"Do you know who ate all the donuts?"
"doyousmell"	"Do you smell what I smell?"
"evergetout"	"Will we ever make it out of here?"
"erseen"	"Have you ever seen anything like this?"
"excellentteam"	"With my brains and your brawn we'll make an excellent team."
"excuse"	"Excuse me, Gordon."
"fascinating"	"Don't you find this all rather fascinating?"
"fellowscientist"	"Glad to oblige a fellow scientist."
"fine"	"Fine. You won't even know I'm here."
"freeman"	"Freeman."
"freemanalive"	"Freeman! Who would have thought you'd still be alive?"
"fusionshunt"	"I certainly hope those backup fusion shunts are in good shape today."
"getoutalive"	"I just want to get out of this alive."
"getoutofhere"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"goodpaper"	"I believe this will make for a notable paper, don't you?"
"goodtoseeyou"	"Ah, it's good to see you."
"gottogetout"	"I've got to get out of here!"
"greetings"	"Greetings!"
"greetings2"	"Greetings."
"headcrab"	"These crab creatures have a unique parasitic strategy, don't you think?"
"heal1"	"Let me take care of that wound for you."
"heal2"	"This should make you feel better."
"heal3"	"Allow me to treat that injury."
"heal4"	"I can give you something for the pain."
"heal5"	"Don't worry, I am a doctor."
"hearsomething"	"Did you hear something?"
"hello"	"Hello."
"hello2"	"Hello."
"hellofreeman"	"Ah, hello, Gordon Freeman. It's good to see you."
"hellofromlab"	"You are from the Anomalous Materials Lab. Yes, I recognize you."
"hellothere"	"Hello there."
"hideglasses"	"Someone has hidden my glasses again."
"holdstill"	"Hold still, this won't hurt a bit."
"hopenominal"	"I hope those containment parameters are still nominal."
"hopeyouknow"	"I certainly hope you know what you're doing."
"howinteresting"	"How interesting, just look at that."
"hungryyet"	"Is anyone else getting hungry?"
"ibelieveso"	"I believe so."
"idontthinkso"	"I don't think so."
"ihearsomething"	"I hear something."
"illwait"	"I'll wait."
"illwaithere"	"I'll wait right here."
"importantspecies"	"Another important species revealed in action."
"improbable"	"A failure of this magnitude is extremely improbable."
"imsure"	"I'm sure of it."
"inconclusive"	"It's inconclusive."
"inmesstoo"	"Ah, Freeman. I see you are in this mess too."
"ipredictedthis"	"I predicted all of this, you know. All of it!"
"istay"	"I'll stay here."
"iwounded"	"I seem to be wounded... but I can keep going."
"iwounded2"	"Well, I seem to be seriously wounded."
"iwoundedbad"	"I don't think I can last much longer."
"justasked"	"Didn't you just ask me that?"
"lambdalab"	"I hope those people in the Lambda Lab can get this under control."
"leadtheway"	"Lead the way."
"leavingme"	"What? You're leaving me here?"
"letmehelp"	"Let me help you."
"letsgo"	"Let's go."
"letstrythis"	"Let's try this."
"letyouin"	"Wait a minute and I'll let you in."
"limitsok"	"This is all within theoretical limits."
"lowervoice"	"Kindly lower your voice."
"luckwillchange"	"It's highly probable that our luck will change, don't you agree?"
"madness"	"This is madness! I'm getting out of here!"
"needsleep"	"I'd give my right hemisphere for a few hours of sleep."
"neverseen"	"Fascinating. I never suspected such things could be."
"newhevsuit"	"Ah, you have one of the new HEV suits. That should be very useful."
"newsample"	"Any ideas on the origin of that new sample?"
"nodoubt"	"I have no doubt."
"nogrant"	"Well, there goes our grant money."
"noguess"	"I couldn't even venture a guess."
"noidea"	"You have no idea what is going on, do you?"
"noo"	"No."
"nooo"	"No!"
"noplease"	"No! Please!"
"notcertain"	"I'm not certain."
"nothostile"	"The alien species can't possibly all be hostile, can they?"
"notsure"	"I am not at all sure."
"odorfromyou"	"I hope that odor isn't coming from you."
"ofcourse"	"Of course!"
"ofcoursenot"	"Of course not!"
"okgetout"	"Okay, let's get out of here."
"okihope"	"Okay, I hope you know what you're doing."
"organicmatter"	"Well, the dimensional breach is definitely transmitting organic matter."
"peculiarmarks"	"Why just look at those peculiar markings."
"peculiarodor"	"Hm, what a peculiar odor."
"perfectday"	"This analysis is going to run perfectly today, don't you think?"
"perhaps"	"Perhaps."
"positively"	"Positively."
"purereadings"	"Wouldn't it be fantastic to get some pure readings for a change?"
"recalculate"	"Don't you think we should recalculate those resonance dampening factors again?"
"reconsider"	"I don't suppose you'd reconsider?"
"repeat"	"You know, you repeat yourself sometimes."
"reportflux"	"I must remember to report that fluctuation."
"rescueus"	"Surely someone will come and rescue us."
"ridiculous"	"Don't be ridiculous!"
"right"	"Right!"
"rightwayout"	"Are you sure this is the right way?"
"rumorclean"	"The military cleanup is just a paranoid rumor, isn't it?"
"runtest"	"I wonder if I should run that test again."
"sci_aftertest"	"You'll just have to wait until after the test."
"sci_alone"	"Please, leave me alone until after the experiment."
"sci_bother"	"I can't be bothered right now."
"sci_busy"	"Excuse me, Gordon, but I'm rather busy now."
"sci_fear6"	"Oh no!"
"sci_fear7"	"Oh dear!"
"sci_fear11"	"Oh my!"
"sci_fear12"	"My goodness!"
"sci_fear13"	"No!"
"sci_fear14"	"Get back!"
"sci_pain3"	"No!"
"sci_pain6"	"No!"
"sci_pain7"	"No!"
"sci_pain8"	"No!"
"sci_pain9"	"Stop!"
"sci_pain10"	"No!"
"sci_somewhere"	"Weren't you supposed to be in the test chamber half an hour ago?"
"scream10"	"No!"
"scream11"	"Stop!"
"scream12"	"Stop!"
"scream13"	"No!"
"seencup"	"Have you seen my coffee cup?"
"shakeunification"	"This should shake up those grand unification boys, hm?"
"shutdownchart"	"Now where did I leave that shutdown procedure chart?"
"shutup"	"Shut up."
"shutup2"	"Shut up."
"simulation"	"Most of the simulation results are perfectly acceptable, you know."
"slowingyou"	"I'm slowing you down, am I?"
"smellburn"	"Do you smell something burning?"
"softethics"	"You aren't going soft on that ethics issue again, are you?"
"sorryimleaving"	"Sorry, I'm leaving now."
"somethingfoul"	"I believe something smells quite foul here."
"startle5"	"Oh no."
"startle6"	"Oh no."
"startle7"	"Oh no."
"startle8"	"Oh no."
"startle9"	"Oh no."
"statusreport"	"Did you submit your status report to the Administrator today?"
"stench"	"What is that stench?"
"stimulating"	"I think it's rather stimulating, don't you?"
"stop1"	"This is as far as I go."
"stop2"	"I refuse to go another step."
"stop3"	"You're going to have to leave me here, Gordon."
"stop4"	"I'm going to stay here and wait for my colleagues."
"stopasking"	"Stop asking that question."
"stopattacking"	"Stop attacking, he's a friend!"
"survival"	"Do you recall any of those emergency survival procedures?"
"thatsodd"	"That's odd."
"theoretically"	"Theoretically."
"thiswillhelp"	"This should help."
"tunedtoday"	"All displacement modulators were tuned today, weren't they?"
"tunnelcalc"	"Are you running those tunneling lattice calculations again?"
"uselessphd"	"Fat lot of good that Ph.D. does me now, hm?"
"weartie"	"Why do we all have to wear these ridiculous ties?"
"whatnext"	"Well, do you have any idea what to do next?"
"whatyoudoing"	"My God, what are you doing?"
"whocansay"	"Who can say?"
"whoresponsible"	"Who is responsible for this mess?"
"whyaskme"	"Why are you asking me?"
"whyleave"	"Why are you leaving me here?"
"yees"	"Yes."
"yes"	"Yes."
"yes2"	"Yes."
"yes3"	"Yes."
"yesletsgo"	"Yes, let's go."
"youinsane"	"Are you insane? Stop attacking, immediately!"
"youlookbad"	"You look terrible."
"youlookbad2"	"You look terrible."
"youneedmedic"	"It appears that you need medical attention right away."
"youwounded"	"Ah, you've been wounded."

//HECU Common
"HG_GREN0"	"Grenade!"
"HG_GREN1"	"Take cover!"
"HG_GREN2"	"Oh shit!"
"HG_GREN3"	"Get down!"
"HG_GREN4"	"Oh God!"
"HG_GREN5"	"No!"
"HG_GREN6"	"Move!"
"HG_ALERT0"	"We got two bogies!" //changed
"HG_ALERT1"	"Target!"
"HG_ALERT2"	"Movement!"
"HG_ALERT3"	"Shit! We got hostiles!"
"HG_ALERT4"	"Squad, get heavy!" //changed
"HG_ALERT5"	"Squad, neutralize those two!" //changed
"HG_ALERT6"	"Move in!"
"HG_MONST0"	"Bogies, my sector!"
"HG_MONST1"	"We got bogies!"
"HG_MONST2"	"Alien alert!"
"HG_MONST3"	"Alien movement!"
"HG_COVER0"	"Take cover!"
"HG_COVER1"	"I need suppressing fire!"
"HG_COVER2"	"We need backup!"
"HG_COVER3"	"Too hot here!"
"HG_COVER4"	"Fall out!"
"HG_COVER5"	"Clear this area!"
"HG_COVER6"	"God damn!"
"HG_COVER7"	"Cover fire!"
"HG_THROW0"	"Fire in the hole!"
"HG_THROW1"	"Take this!"
"HG_THROW2"	"Fire in the hole!"
"HG_THROW3"	"Squad, stay down!"
"HG_TAUNT0"	"Uhh, we got heavy fire."
"HG_TAUNT1"	"Roger, hold position."
"HG_TAUNT2"	"We will kick your ass!"
"HG_TAUNT3"	"Mister, you are going down."
"HG_TAUNT4"	"You got nothing."
"HG_TAUNT5"	"Request backup!"
"HG_CHARGE0"	"Go, recon!"
"HG_CHARGE1"	"Move in!"
"HG_CHARGE2"	"Go!"
"HG_CHARGE3"	"Let's go!"
"HG_QUEST0"	"Stay alert, people."
"HG_QUEST1"	"Radio check, over."
"HG_QUEST2"	"Maintain lookout."
"HG_QUEST3"	"Squad, quiet down."
"HG_QUEST4"	"Hold position."
"HG_QUEST5"	"Sweep that sector."
"HG_QUEST6"	"Uhh, go tango sweep formation."
"HG_QUEST7"	"Echo mission is go."
"HG_QUEST8"	"Fire team, weapons check okay."
"HG_QUEST9"	"Fire team, objective foxtrot niner."
"HG_QUEST10"	"Okay mission, zero niner."
"HG_QUEST11"	"Squad, stay alert for anything, over." //changed
"HG_ANSWER0"	"Uhh, roger that."
"HG_ANSWER1"	"Yes sir."
"HG_ANSWER2"	"Affirmative, sir."
"HG_ANSWER3"	"Negative."
"HG_ANSWER4"	"Roger."
"HG_ANSWER5"	"Okay control."
"HG_ANSWER6"	"That is, uhh, affirmative."
"HG_CLEAR0"	"All clear, sir."
"HG_CLEAR1"	"Bravo post, clear."
"HG_CLEAR2"	"Delta Team, clear."
"HG_CLEAR3"	"No sign hostiles, sir, over."
"HG_CLEAR4"	"No sign objective, sir, over."
"HG_CLEAR5"	"No movement this level."
"HG_CLEAR6"	"Sir, sector secure, over."
"HG_CLEAR7"	"Command post, team in position, over."
"HG_CLEAR8"	"Recon, in position, all quiet."
"HG_CLEAR9"	"Lookout post, all quiet, over."
"HG_CLEAR10"	"Sir, I hear something."
"HG_CLEAR11"	"Sir, uhh, zero movement, over."
"HG_CLEAR12"	"Area secure, sir, over."
"HG_CHECK0"	"Okay, check in."
"HG_CHECK1"	"Squad, are hostiles clear?"
"HG_CHECK2"	"Check in, people."
"HG_CHECK3"	"Lookout, check in."
"HG_CHECK4"	"Recon team, check in."
"HG_CHECK5"	"Movement check, over."
"HG_CHECK6"	"Check your zone, over."
"HG_CHECK7"	"Everything okay there."
"gr_pain1"	"Is that all you got?"
"gr_pain2"	"You got nothin'!"
"gr_pain3"	"I'm hit!"
"gr_pain4"	"Uh, oh!"
"gr_pain5"	"Argh, medic!"

//Rosenberg
"ro_01_admin"	"The administrator is a bureaucrat, not a scientist. I did not design this equipment to be run at such high intensity."
"ro_01_alive"	"Keller? Keller, are you alive? Tolman's dead."
"ro_01_assure"	"I can assure you, it is not, Dr. Keller. I... what!"
"ro_01_callhelp"	"Well, we've got to get everyone out of here. Reach the surface, call for help, something!"
"ro_01_chargers"	"I'll get the primary chargers."
"ro_01_dampen"	"I don't understand. The dampening fields..."
"ro_01_danger"	"It's too dangerous. If we fail, who will warn everyone else? We can have soldiers here in two hours who can secure the facility and bring everyone to safety. Our concern must be with the people of Black Mesa."
"ro_01_fields"	"The dampening fields are designed not to fail. The only way this could have happened is if someone turned them off, and even then there should have been a noticeable discrepancy in the displacement flow indicators."
"ro_01_grudge"	"Whatever grudge you may have with me..."
"ro_01_keller"	"Dr. Keller."
"ro_01_leaving"	"I don't like the idea of leaving you here, but it seems we have no choice."
"ro_01_letsgo"	"All right. Let's go."
"ro_01_realize"	"You realize, of course, that the spectrometer is going to overload."
"ro_01_spectrom"	"I've been talking to Harold. He seems to be under the impression that you're planning on running the anti-mass spectrometer at greater than ninety percent. You realize there is a reason for the safety buffer."
"ro_01_survived"	"Oh, thank goodness you've survived. Those HEV suits of yours are well designed, Dr. Cross."
"ro_01_touch"	"No, don't touch that!"
"ro_01_yesright"	"Yes, you're right."
"ro_02_careful"	"Be careful. As long as those sentry guns are active, it's suicide to go out there. But it is the only way to the surface. You're going to have to destroy them."
"ro_02_despite"	"Despite what Dr. Keller believes, our only concern now should be for the people trapped inside Black Mesa. We need to get to the surface to reach the satellite communication equipment. Once they know what's going on, I'm confident they'll immediately send the military in to rescue us. There's an elevator nearby that will take us up to where we need to go. Follow me."
"ro_02_elevator"	"Damn, it seems the elevator controls aren't functioning. There is a maintenance area below us. I think, perhaps, you can get the elevator working from down there. You'll have to make your way through the hazard course to reach the maintenance area. I know I don't have to remind you that your hazard suit will protect you, but I'll think I'll be safer if I wait here."
"ro_02_follow"	"Okay, I'll follow you."
"ro_02_madeit"	"We made it! Now at the end of this tunnel is an access shaft that leads right to the surface. From there we'll be able to reach the satellite communications center and call for help. Good work, I couldn't have gotten here without you. Let's go."
"ro_02_moving"	"It's moving! Thank goodness you've made it! I was beginning to give up on you. Raise the elevator up to the top floor."
"ro_02_opendoor"	"Hmm, I should be able to open this door."
"ro_02_thanks"	"Thank you! I thought I'd never get out of that elevator alive."
"ro_02_waithere"	"I'm going to wait here where it's safe. You need to find a way into the maintanance shaft of this elevator and raise it manually."
"ro_03_aligned"	"From here we'll be able to contact the military. From the look of these instruments it appears that the satellite dish is properly aligned. Good work. Now hit the switch and complete the uplink."
"ro_03_excellent"	"Excellent! We should now have a working uplink. I'll test it."
"ro_03_inside"	"Inside is the control room for the satellite dish, but this door is locked. If you can find a way into that warehouse, you should be able to make your way around to the other side of this door to let me in. I'll wait here. The way is too dangerous for me, but you'll be protected by the hazard suits."
"ro_03_keller"	"Dr. Keller? Dr. Keller? Do you read me? We've established the uplink and are transmitting the emergency signal."
"ro_03_madeit"	"Ah, you made it! The control room is just up the stairs. Quick, come with me."
"ro_03_makeway"	"You need to make your way through the warehouse. I'll wait, but please, hurry."
"ro_03_notalign"	"From here we'll be able to contact the military, but it appears the satellite dish is not aligned. One of you needs to go down and rotate the dish. The instruments in this room will tell us when the dish is positioned correctly."
"ro_03_notalign2"	"We can't do anything with this equipment until the dish is aligned."
"ro_03_perfect"	"That's it. Good. Perfect."
"ro_03_rotated"	"Good, the dish is being rotated. Once our indicators tell us it's aligned, hit the switch to complete the uplink."
"ro_03_senddown"	"I understand. I'll send them down. Out."
"ro_03_surface"	"Now that we've made it to the surface, we can get help. If we're quick enough, the people below may have a chance. Behind this fence is a satellite communications center we can use to communicate with military personnel outside of Black Mesa. The military has the best chance at being able to secure the facility and they'll be able to escort us to safety. Let's go."
"ro_03_toofar"	"Stop. Too far. Go back, that was it."
"ro_03_waithere"	"Listen, I can wait here for the military to arrive, but you're needed to help with the situation down below or others will be put in peril. You've done your job here, now get below and reach Dr. Keller. Be careful, both of you. Hopefully I'll see you on the outside."
"ro_calhoun"	"Calhoun?"
"ro_calhoun2"	"Calhoun? Wait a minute, you're not Calhoun."
"ro_cure0"	"You look terrible!"
"ro_cure1"	"You seem to be wounded."
"ro_cure2"	"You're going to need medical attention right away."
"ro_heal0"	"Let me take care of that wound for you."
"ro_heal1"	"This should make you feel better."
"ro_heal2"	"You need medical attention. Here."
"ro_heal3"	"Let me give you something for the pain."
"ro_heal4"	"Allow me to treat that injury."
"ro_mortal0"	"I'm not sure how much longer I can last."
"ro_mortal1"	"I don't think I can last much longer."
"ro_ok0"	"Let's get going."
"ro_ok1"	"I'll be right behind you."
"ro_ok2"	"Let's hurry! There's no time to waste."
"ro_ok3"	"Yes, let's go."
"ro_ok4"	"All right, let's stick together."
"ro_ok5"	"All right, you won't even know I'm here."
"ro_ok6"	"Yes, we'll have a better chance if we stick together."
"ro_ok7"	"Let's go."
"ro_plfear0"	"What are you doing?"
"ro_plfear1"	"I can't take this anymore!"
"ro_plfear2"	"This is madness!"
"ro_plfear3"	"No, please! I don't want to die!"
"ro_plfear4"	"Get out of here!"
"ro_rug"	"He suspects that the culprits might be the very people who, uh, 'soiled' your rug, and you're in a unique position to confirm or, uh, 'disconfirm' that suspicion."
"ro_scared0"	"My God! What are you doing? "
"ro_scared1"	"Stop attacking immediately!"
"ro_scared2"	"Are you insane? He's a friend!"
"ro_stop2"	"I need to rest a bit before I can go on."
"ro_wait0"	"We have no time to take a break. We must keep going."
"ro_wait1"	"This is no time to rest. We must keep going."
"ro_wait2"	"I'll wait here."
"ro_wait3"	"I'll stay here, but, hurry back."
"ro_wait4"	"Yes, maybe you should go on ahead for a bit. Just don't forget about me."
"ro_wound0"	"I'm seem to be wounded, but I can keep going."
"ro_wound1"	"I'm not doing too well, but I can make it."
"ro_xen_call1"	"Calhoun, you must hurry! We can't keep the portal open much longer."

//VOX
"HT01_0"	"Attention. Dr. Freeman, report to Anomalous Materials laboratory."
"HT01_1"	"Dr. Cross and Dr. Green, you are required in the Anomalous Materials Operations Center."
"HT01_2"	"All security personnel, check clearance with Inspector White."
"HT01_3"	"Attention. Science Team, decontamination required in Anomalous Materials laboratory."
"HT01_4"	"Attention. Topside leave has not been authorized with administration."
"HT01_5"	"Warning. Do not deactivate containment field systems."
"HT01_6"	"Announcement. Topside satellite communication dish has been disengaged."
"HT01_7"	"Laser containment system access is forbidden to inspection personnel."
"HT01_8"	"Announcement. Waste disposal control will proceed at 1:35."
"HT01_9"	"Anomalous Materials test not open to unauthorized personnel."
"HT05_0"	"Attention. All science personnel evacuate Level 3 immediately."
"HT05_1"	"Attention. This announcement system now under military command."
"HT05_2"	"Attention. Black Mesa Announcement System now under military command."
"HT05_3"	"Attention. Science Team, report to nearest security checkpoint immediately."
"HT05_4"	"Attention. All military personnel, intruder detected in Level 3."
"HT05_5"	"Attention. All science personnel, report to north transportation platform immediately."
"HT05_6"	"Warning. Unauthorized biological forms detected in ventilation system."
"HT05_7"	"Charlie Team reports Bravo-Foxtrot-Johnson facility is secured."
"HT05_8"	"Search and Destroy Squad Alpha, reports secondary objective terminated."
"CROSSDOOR"	"Dr. Cross, access granted."
"GREENDOOR"	"Dr. Green, access granted."
"GREENDOOR2"	"Dr. Green, access denied."

//Scientists
"crossgreen"	"Doctor Cross. Doctor Green."
"d01_sci01_waiting"	"Good morning. They're waiting for you in the control room."
"d01_sci02_door"	"Oh, I'll get the door for you. They should be able to get you back into the security database in the next room."
"d01_sci03_reregister"	"Greetings! It looks as though your data was lost in the system failure this morning. Not to worry, I can re-register you at this station. Step into the booth one at a time and I'll start the procedure."
"d01_sci04_oneatatime"	"One at a time, please."
"d01_sci05_bestillcross"	"Please be still during the procedure. Don't worry, Doctor Cross, it should only take a few moments."
"d01_sci06_dontmovegreen"	"Please don't move while I scan for re-registration into the security database. It will be over before you know it, Doctor Green."
"d01_sci07_spectrometer"	"We'd like you to bring the Anti-Mass Spectrometer online and take it up to eighty percent."
"d01_sci08_pushsample"	"If you would be so kind as to push the sample into the lift, we can start the experiment."
"d01_sci09_pushsample2"	"You'll need to push the sample cart into the lift in order for the experiment to proceed."
"d01_sci10_interesting"	"Interesting."
"d01_sci11_shouldnthappen"	"That shouldn't happen."
"d01_sci12_impossible"	"You know, theoretically, this is impossible."
"d01_sci13_jammed"	"Hmm, right. Something must be jammed. See if there's anything interfering with the lift machinery in the test chamber below. I'll continue trying to operate the lift from here."
"d01_sci14_right"	"Right."
"d01_sci15_onschedule"	"Ah, excellent. Everything appears to be on schedule, and the experiment will be starting shortly. I will leave the loudspeaker on so you can hear what's happening upstairs."
"d01_sci16_standby"	"Stand by."
"d01_sci17_secondary"	"Secondary magnetic chargers are active and functioning nominally."
"d01_sci18_wontshutdown"	"It won't shut down!"
"d08_sci01_idnumber"	"Uh, I only know the ID number to Gordon's HEV suit. No others. Couldn't you just let me go?"
"helloladies"	"Ah, hello, ladies. It's good to see you."
"icanhelp"	"I suppose I can help."
"idiotic"	"What? No! That's an idiotic thing to ask."
"safetyinnumbers"	"Haven't you heard of safety in numbers?"
"shesgonemad"	"Someone help! She's gone mad!"
"sunsets"	"While this may be your idea of fun, I prefer long walks on a sandy beach as the sun sets."
"thatsmell"	"That smell is, eh... interesting."
"ties"	"The least they could do is let us wear differing ties. I really don't understand this uniform policy."
"underbarrel"	"Shouldn't you be under the barrel now?"
"keller"	"Wasn't Dr. Keller looking for you?"
"assist"	"I believe you have an experiment to assist."
"c1a0_sci_dis1d"	"Very good. We'll take it from here."
"c1a0_sci_dis2a"	"Power to stage one emitters in three...two...one..."
"c1a0_sci_dis3a"	"I'm seeing predictable phase arrays."
"c1a0_sci_dis5a"	"Stage two emitters activating...now."
"c1a0_sci_dis10a"	"Gordon, we cannot predict how long the system can operate at this level, nor how long the reading will take. Please work as quickly as you can."
"c1a0_sci_dis9a"	"Overhead capacitors to one oh five percent."
"c1a0_sci_dis11a"	"Uh...it's probably not a problem...probably...but I'm showing a small discrepancy in...well, no, it's well within acceptable bounds again. Sustaining sequence."
"c1a0_sci_dis6a"	"I have just been informed that the sample is ready, Gordon. It should be coming up to you any moment now. Look to the delivery system for your specimen."
"c1a0_sci_dis16a"	"Gordon! Get away from the beams!"
"c1a0_sci_dis15a"	"Shutting down. Attempting shut down. It's not...it's-it's not...it's not shutting down...it's not..."
"b01_sci01_whereami"	"Where am I? I've got to get out of here!"
"b01_sci02_briefcase"	"You, with the briefcase. You've got to help me out of here!"
"b01_sci03_sirplease"	"Hello? Where are you going? Sir! Please!"
"overhere"	"Psst, over here."


//Barney
"ba_door0"	"I'll get that door open."
"ba_door1"	"Let me get that door for you."
"ba_attacking0"	"Get behind me, ma'am!"
"ba_attacking1"	"Open fire!"
"ba_attacking2"	"I'll protect you!"
"ba_becareful0"	"You ladies, be careful out there."
"ba_becareful1"	"Hey, try not to get eaten by a monster or anything, okay?"
"ba_cure0"	"That injury might need attention soon."
"ba_cure1"	"I hate to say it, but you're in bad shape."
"ba_hello0"	"Doctor."
"ba_hello1"	"Ma'am."
"ba_help0"	"Here, let me get that for you."
"ba_ht01_01"	"Good morning, doctor. Doctor. Looks like you two are right on time today."
"ba_ht01_02"	"I'm afraid there's been some trouble with the system, so you may have been deleted from the security database. If you follow me to the door, I can get you inside where you can straighten it all out."
"ba_ht01_03"	"So I guess today is the big day, huh? The big guy was pretty excited when he came in earlier. He was talking about the new guy, Dr. Freeman. I just hope everything goes well today."
"ba_ht01_04"	"All right, this should only take a second."
"ba_ht01_05"	"There you go. See you after the experiment."
"ba_ht01_06"	"You're gonna have to register yourself before I can let you through here. Just check in around the corner."
"ba_ht06_01"	"Soldiers, everywhere! They're killing everyone!"
"ba_ht06_02_alt"	"Help me!"
"ba_ht06_03"	"Man, am I glad to see you."
"ba_ht06_03_alt"	"Man, am I glad to see you."
"ba_ht06_04"	"Yeah, I've got the clearance codes to the security station, but I'm not leaving until those soldiers down there have been cleared out. If you can't take 'em out, maybe you can seal 'em off. Either way, it's not safe for me to leave here."
"ba_ht06_05"	"Yeah, I've got the clearance codes to the security station. Let's go."
"ba_ht06_06"	"I'm not going with you until you either take out those soldiers downstairs or cut 'em off. It's too dangerous."
"ba_ht06_07"	"I told you, I'm not leaving as long as those soldiers are running around down there."
"ba_ht06_08"	"Listen, you've got HEV suits to protect you. If I go down there, those soldiers will kill me! Take care of them, and I'll follow you."
"ba_ht06_09"	"I was worried you wouldn't make it. Anyway, let's get to the security station. You lead the way."
"ba_ht06_10"	"This door is locked. See if you can activate it from the console."
"ba_ht06_11"	"Sure do. You got a plan?"
"ba_ht08_01"	"I don't know anything! I'm not even with the science tea-"
"ba_ht08_01_alt"	"I don't know anything! I'm not even with the science team!"
"ba_ht08_01_alt2"	"I don't know anything! I'm not even with the science team!"
"ba_ht08_02"	"Hey, where did you come from? We should stick together, this place is crawling with soldiers!"
"ba_ht08_03"	"Hey, what are you two doing here? Take cover! There are soldiers everywhere!"
"ba_idle0"	"So, you think there's a future for us at the end all of this."
"ba_idle1"	"Don't worry, darlin', I'm right beside ya."
"ba_idle2"	"Not to worry, ma'am. I'm a trained professional."
"ba_idle3"	"That's a flattering HEV suit you got there, if you don't mind my saying so."
"ba_idle4"	"The orange in that suit really brings out your eyes."
"ba_idle5"	"You look good in orange."
"ba_idle6"	"I like you how you hold that gun."
"ba_kill0"	"It's all right, ma'am, I got him!"
"ba_kill1"	"That's good shooting."
"ba_kill2"	"Where'd you learn to shoot?"
"ba_lead0"	"I think it's over here."
"ba_lead1"	"It's this way."
"ba_lead2"	"You should follow me."
"ba_mad0"	"Hey, step off!"
"ba_mad1"	"I hate to have to do this."
"ba_mad2"	"You crazy woman!"
"ba_mad3"	"A man's gotta do what a man's gotta do!"
"ba_ok0"	"Sure thing, ma'am."
"ba_ok1"	"Ladies first."
"ba_ok2"	"After you."
"ba_ok3"	"You'll be safe with me."
"ba_ok4"	"I've always wanted you to ask me that."
"ba_ok5"	"I'll be right behind you."
"ba_plfear0"	"Watch it, lady, that's a friend!"
"ba_pok0"	"Sorry, ma'am, I can't leave my post right now."
"ba_pok1"	"I'd love to chat, but I'm on duty right now."
"ba_pok2"	"Can we do this later?"
"ba_pok3"	"Hey, y-you know what, m-maybe we could catch a movie later?"
"ba_shot0"	"Hey, watch it, lady!"
"ba_shot1"	"Damn! Just when I thought we were getting friendly!"
"ba_shot2"	"Woah, someone should teach you how to use that thing!"
"ba_stare0"	"Hmm?"
"ba_stare1"	"Hiya!"
"ba_stare2"	"Stick close to me, darlin'! Heh heh."
"ba_stare3"	"We'll get through this together."
"ba_stop0"	"I'm sorry, ma'am, I can't keep up."
"ba_stop1"	"I'm gonna have to stay behind."
"ba_wait0"	"You gonna be all right without me?"
"ba_wait1"	"I really don't think you should be alone right now."
"ba_wait2"	"I'll be right here if you need me."
"ba_wait3"	"You're not giving me the cold shoulder, are ya?"
"ba_wait4"	"Hey, I thought we were a good team."


//Keller
"dk_01_cascade"	"Never mind that, we've just witnessed a resonance cascade!"
"dk_01_collapsed"	"They failed! The entire containment system has collapsed! This is a resonance cascade, Doctor Rosenberg."
"dk_01_concern"	"I understand your concern, doctor, but the administrator was quite clear."
"dk_01_decision"	"This is not your decision. Now, if you wish to stay and monitor the experiment, so be it. Otherwise, you can go back to your little labs over by the train yard."
"dk_01_failed"	"The dampening fields failed!"
"dk_01_finished"	"I believe our discussion is finished, Doctor Rosenberg."
"dk_01_gonewrong"	"Something has gone wrong. Doctor Tolman cut the magnetic chargers."
"dk_01_gottodeal"	"No! We've got to deal with the problem. We can't expect anyone else to understand the importance of resetting those dampening fields. Without them in place, the dimensional gash could tear so wide it may never be repaired."
"dk_01_kleiner"	"Honestly, I do not understand what Kleiner sees in that boy."
"dk_01_late"	"Ah, hello Doctors. It's nice to see someone is on time today. Doctor Freeman is running late, again."
"dk_01_needspect"	"We'll need the spectrometer at one hundred five percent in order to continue. Doctors, please disengage the safety lock and proceed with the adjustment."
"dk_01_plan"	"Doctors, we have formulated a plan. You must escort Rosenberg to the surface, help him call for help. I couldn't possibly make it in my chair. I'll stay behind and assess the damage to our equipment and the extent of the cascade. Maybe I can find a clue as to what went wrong and how we can right things."
"dk_01_rosenberg"	"Ah, hello, Dr. Rosenberg. We're sort of in the middle of something right now, so if you could..."
"dk_01_shortcut"	"Let me activate the service lift. There's a shortcut through the training area that will get you to the surface. Good luck."
"dk_01_spectrom"	"Doctors, it's time to raise the Anti-Mass Spectrometer to one hundred five percent. Doctor Cross, you'll need to disengage the safety locks in order to allow the adjustment to occur."
"dk_01_started"	"Anyway, let's get started. When Dr. Freeman is running upstairs, they'll want to begin the experiment, so you'll need to retrieve the sample, Dr. Cross, and I'll let Dr. Green into the test chamber to make other preparations."
"dk_01_storage"	"Doctor Cross, the sample storage area is through the door here, and Doctor Green, we need you in the test chamber. We'll monitor the experiment from here."
"dk_01_survived"	"Perhaps you're right. Doctor Cross and Doctor Green may have survived. If so, they can help us. I'll try to find them with this terminal."
"dk_01_tolman"	"Doctor Tolman, would you power up the secondary magnetic chargers?"
"dk_01_yesgood"	"Yes, good!"
"dk_03_notime"	"Good work, but there's no time to wait for the military. I need the team down here immediately! The dampening fields are going critical and must be reset."
"dk_04_bewary"	"Be wary, my friends. Resetting the locks will probably put quite a strain on the pressure release valves, and they may cause increased displacement activity."
"dk_04_bringtram"	"I'm going to see if I can access the transit system and bring a working tram to us. I'm afraid whatever held the rift open did so with intent, my friends. These aliens may not all be here by accident."
"dk_04_bulkhead"	"That emergency bulkhead won't open until the secondary dampening locks are reset."
"dk_04_disenergy"	"The displacement energy is increasing in your area. You must reset the lock quickly!"
"dk_04_excellent"	"Excellent. I'll be able to communicate with you anywhere in the facility."
"dk_04_goonway"	"Go on your way."
"dk_04_ididit"	"I did it, the displacement fields have shut down. Damn it, this is the second time they've failed us!"
"dk_04_interfere"	"Something's wrong. I think something is interfering from the other side of the rift."
"dk_04_letssee"	"Let's see how the area is holding up."
"dk_04_monsters"	"Here, there be monsters."
"dk_04_onwaythen"	"On your way, then."
"dk_04_otherdamp"	"The secondary dampening locks are upstairs, at least a floor above us. Maybe two."
"dk_04_primlock"	"The primary dampening lock overlooks the transit lines."
"dk_04_primreset"	"The primary lock is reset, displacement energy in that area is astounding! Hold fast, this is gonna be rough."
"dk_04_resetdamp"	"In order to reset the dampening field, you'll have to reset the dampening locks manually. There are two secondary locks and one primary one. The dampening conduits are massive, so finding the locks shouldn't be hard."
"dk_04_resetnow"	"You must reset the lock now! The conduit will burst if you don't."
"dk_04_secfirst"	"Now, you'll have to reset the secondary locks first. Only the primary conduit is strong enough to support a full flow and I honestly can't guarantee it will hold."
"dk_04_testing"	"Test. Testing."
"dk_04_toomuch"	"It's too much pressure. I'm attempting an emergency shut down."
"dk_04_transmit"	"Ah, I can use this console to transmit directly to your suit's audio system. Let's try it out."
"dk_04_weakspot"	"I found indications of a weak spot on the conduit hall over the tram lines. Be watchful of that when you're resetting the lock."
"dk_05_gladalive"	"Glad to see you're still alive, but our mission isn't complete until you bring a security guard to me."
"dk_05_gotodorms"	"Unfortunately, the delivery rocket cannot launch without the all-clear codes. Now any security guard in this dorm complex should have the codes we need. Go through the dorms and find a security guard. I'll take the tram around to the north side where we can pick you up. Good luck."
"dk_05_havecode"	"I presume you've got the all-clear codes for the satellite delivery rocket?"
"dk_05_haveguard"	"Ah, you found a guard. Good job."
"dk_05_mustseal"	"The dimensional rift between here and the alien world must be sealed. We'll need to have the satellite in orbit in order to orchestrate a resonance reversal. The signal room for the satellite is nearby."
"dk_05_needcodes"	"The delivery rocket cannot be launched without the all-clear codes. Don't return until you've found a guard who has the codes."
"dk_05_needguard"	"You're going to have to locate a security guard before we leave this place. They're the only ones who know the codes we need."
"dk_05_nofoolish"	"We don't have time for any foolishness, get in there and find a guard."
"dk_05_onceorbit"	"Yes, once the satellite is in orbit, we can orchestrate a resonance reversal that may seal the rift between Earth and the alien world."
"dk_05_otherside"	"See you on the other side!"
"dk_07_basement"	"Gina? Colette? Do you read me? You're in the basement of the Black Mesa air control building. You need to find the control room. Set the air space monitor to send the all-clear codes so that Lambda Labs can launch the delivery rocket and deploy the satellite. I can unlock the security door in front of you from here, but I'm afraid the other power lock doors offer no remote access. You'll have to unlock them from inside."
"dk_07_lockout"	"The signal equipment will only function during a traffic control systems lockout. The system must be active to set the all-clear signal."
"dk_07_online"	"It looks like the signal is coming online. Stand by... I'm getting the all-clear signal, you've done it!"
"dk_10_beacon"	"We need to raise the beacon in order to use it. I can't seem to do it from here and the maintenance hatch to the basement controls is locked. You'll have to raise the beacon manually. Find it and I'll contact you again."
"dk_10_goingon"	"What's going on down there? We can't afford to lose this equipment, it's our only chance! You must find a way to raise the beacon, and for heaven's sake, try to keep it in one piece!"
"dk_10_jammed"	"You'll need to work quickly as we're running out of time. The beacon lift must be jammed because the surface seal won't open. Clear the obstruction and then use the controls to raise the beacon."
"dk_10_receiving"	"Gina? Colette? Are you receiving me? We've made it to Gamma Labs. The displacement beacon we need to perform a resonance reversal is near your position."
"dk_10_working"	"My equipment tells me that the displacement beacon is up and in working order. Good job! Come upstairs to Gamma Labs, we haven't much time."
"dk_11_activate"	"You need to go down to the lab and activate the device. I don't want to leave the doors unlocked any more than necessary."
"dk_11_bothin"	"You'll both need to be in the elevator for me to take it up."
"dk_11_elevator"	"I'll remotely operate the elevator once both of you are inside."
"dk_11_goodwork"	"Good work. With the beam matrix active, we can attempt a resonance reversal. We seem to have become quite an effective team, but everything comes down to this. The rift has become dangerously wide and it may already be too late. We must act, now!"
"dk_11_greatdone"	"Great, you've done it! Get back to the elevator, both of you."
"dk_11_matrixact"	"I can't let you back up until the beam matrix is activated!"
"dk_11_unlock"	"I'll briefly unlock the doors for you. I can remotely operate the elevator that will take you to the lab area. Then it's up to you to turn on the device."
"dk_11_upstairs"	"Up those stairs you can access the alien quarantine labs. I fear that the scientists working there may have been overcome by the very creatures they were studying. We need you to get inside those labs and activate a beam matrix which powers the displacement beacon. You won't find much help in activating the system, but I'm sure with your training it will be a simple matter."
"dk_12_allactive"	"All the crystals are activated! We're going to begin the reversal now, you must protect the beacon at all costs!"
"dk_12_attbeacon"	"It attacked the beacon! If the beacon is destroyed, the reversal will fail. You must destroy that thing!"
"dk_12_beacon1"	"I'm activating the displacement beacon now."
"dk_12_blastbunker"	"We've come this far and I'll be damned if we're going to fail now. Stand clear, I'm going to open that bunker right now!"
"dk_12_bunker"	"There's an ammunition storage bunker out there with you. I'm going to try and override the security locks and open it. I'm sure you could use the extra firepower."
"dk_12_bunkerfail"	"Damnation! The security system has cut power to the bunker doors! There's no way we're getting in there now."
"dk_12_bunkeropen"	"We've bypassed the security locks! I'm opening the ammunition bunker right now."
"dk_12_critical1"	"If you don't deploy the crystal, we're going to die here!"
"dk_12_critical2"	"Don't you understand what we're facing here? For God's sake, in hours! Deploy the crystal!"
"dk_12_deploy1"	"We're ready for you to deploy one of the crystals now."
"dk_12_donewell"	"You've done well, but we're not done yet. You must use the displacement beacon's focus emitter to charge the large crystals on the canyon walls. Once charged, I'll use them to start the resonance reversal. Those crystals will be far more effective than the dampening fields."
"dk_12_dontcare"	"...don't care if it's overloading, we need the power, do it now!"
"dk_12_failed"	"That thing has destroyed the beacon, the system is overloading! You've failed! You've killed us all!"
"dk_12_final20"	"Beam capacitor charged to twenty percent."
"dk_12_final75"	"Beam capacitor at seventy-five percent."
"dk_12_final100"	"One hundred percent, you can deploy the final crystal!"
"dk_12_first100"	"The beam matrix activated. Displacement beacon in working order. Beam capacitor charged to one hundred percent. Here we go!"
"dk_12_firstgo"	"Charging first crystal in three... two... one."
"dk_12_followme"	"Follow me."
"dk_12_iiii"	"I..."
"dk_12_mindopen"	"Would you mind opening this door for me?"
"dk_12_netting"	"This facility is normally used as a sort of cross-dimensional netting ground. It captured organic alien samples and creatures for study without the danger of actually going to Xen to retrieve them."
"dk_12_radio"	"...don't care if it's overloading, we need the power, do it now!"
"dk_12_second50"	"The beam capacitor is at fifty percent."
"dk_12_second80"	"Beam capacitor is now eighty percent."
"dk_12_second90"	"Ninety percent..."
"dk_12_second100"	"Beam capacitor at one hundred percent, deploy the second crystal."
"dk_12_success"	"Gina? Colette? You'll be all right. You were caught for a moment there in a harmonic reflux. It's one of the swirling eddies in the space between two displacement event currents. Although I can't imagine who is creating the other current. But it doesn't matter now. Rest my friends. We did it!"
"dk_12_surge"	"I'm detecting an energy surge. Something large is coming through the rift!"
"dk_12_thisisbad"	"This is bad! I don't think the beacon can survive another blast from that thing."
"dk_12_whenstart"	"When you start charging the crystals, the alien force will detect it and they'll try to stop you. It's possible you could be dealing with more enemies than you've ever seen. You must charge the crystals as quickly as possible."
"dk_hello0"	"Good day to you, doctor."
"dk_hello1"	"Hello, doctor."
"dk_hello2"	"Ah, hello there."
"dk_hello3"	"Doctor Cross."
"dk_hello4"	"Doctor Green."
"dk_help0"	"Damnation!"
"dk_help1"	"Assist me!"
"dk_help2"	"I need help! At once!"
"dk_idle0"	"This situation has become unreasonable."
"dk_idle1"	"Hmm."
"dk_idle2"	"I promise you, when this over, heads will roll."
"dk_idle3"	"Someone will pay for this mess."
"dk_idle4"	"This place has turned, my friends."
"dk_leads0"	"We should go this way."
"dk_leads1"	"Over here."
"dk_leads2"	"Follow me."
"dk_newstuff"	"Good job for doing previous stuff, let's get ready to do new stuff."
"dk_ok0"	"I will not be used."
"dk_ok1"	"My chair is powered, I do not need a push."
"dk_ok2"	"I believe you have something important to do?"
"dk_plfear0"	"Have you lost your senses?"
"dk_plfear1"	"Cease!"
"dk_plfear2"	"Be careful!"
"dk_plfear3"	"Stand down, woman!"
"dk_scared0"	"Mind yourself!"
"dk_scared1"	"Control your weapon!"
"dk_scared2"	"Stop that immediately!"
"dk_stare0"	"Yes?"
"dk_stare1"	"Do you need something?"
"dk_stare2"	"You have a task to attend to."
"dk_stop0"	"I can't go this way in my chair."
"dk_stop1"	"My chair my cannot navigate the way you'd like it to."
"dk_stop2"	"I'm afraid my mobility is limited here."
"dk_wait0"	"I will be here."
"dk_wait1"	"I'll wait."
"dk_wait2"	"I'm slowing you down, am I?"
"dk_wait3"	"I shall await your return."

//HECU Decay Specific
"ht05_halfway"	"Halfway through level three. Lots of civilian resistance. Target has not been acquired."

//Holo 
"tr_holo_jump"	"The first move we will practice in the hazard course is basic jumping. You will attempt to get over this set of pipes, using only your run and jump commands. It helps to get a running start. Watch me and then try it yourself."
"tr_holo_jduck"	"Now we will combine skills. You will need to jump, duck, and then jump again. This will prepare you for the next room, where you will have to do both moves at the same time."
"tr_holo_hitall"	"You'll have to hit every target in order to complete the course. But if you miss the first time, don't worry, it will come around again. Try to reload during pauses, rather than waiting to run out of ammunition at a critical time."
"tr_holo_commencing"	"Commencing sequence in five, four, tree, two, one."
"tr_holo_congrats"	"Congratulations! You have completed the Black Mesa target range. Please advance to the next area."
"tr_holo_leadguard"	"Lead the security guard in— Lead the security guard into the next—"

//H.E.V (minus battery percantages)
"HEV_AAx"	"Welcome to the HEV Mark 4 Protective System, for use in hazardous environment conditions. High-impact reactive armor activated. Atmospheric contaminant sensors activated. Vital signs monitoring activated. Automatic medical systems engaged. Defensive weapon selection system activated. Munition level monitoring activated. Communications interface online. Have a very safe day."
"HEV_A0"	"Welcome to the HEV Mark 4 Protective System, for use in hazardous environment conditions."
"HEV_A1"	"Power-assist movement activated."
"HEV_A2"	"High-impact reactive armor activated."
"HEV_A3"	"Atmospheric contaminant sensors activated."
"HEV_A4"	"Vital signs monitoring activated."
"HEV_A8"	"Automatic medical systems engaged."
"HEV_A7"	"Defensive weapon selection system activated."
"HEV_A5"	"Munition level monitoring activated."
"HEV_A6"	"Communications interface online."
"HEV_A10"	"Have a very safe day."
"HEV_HLTH1"	"Vital signs are dropping."
"HEV_HLTH2"	"Warning: Vital signs critical."
"HEV_HLTH3"	"Emergency. User death imminent."
"HEV_HLTH4"	"Vital signs are dropping. Evacuate area."
"HEV_HLTH5"	"Warning: Vital signs critical. Evacuate area."
"HEV_HLTH6"	"Warning: Vital signs critical. Evacuate area immediately."
"HEV_DMG7"	"Seek medical attention."
"HEV_SHOCK"	"Warning: Electrical damage detected."
"HEV_FIRE"	"Warning: Extreme heat damage detected."
"HEV_DMG3"	"Warning: Blood toxin levels detected."
"HEV_DMG0"	"Minor lacerations detected."
"HEV_DMG1"	"Major lacerations detected."
"HEV_DMG4"	"Minor fracture detected."
"HEV_DMG5"	"Major fracture detected."
"HEV_DMG6"	"Blood loss detected."
"HEV_DMG2"	"Internal bleeding detected."
"HEV_HEAL7"	"Morphine administered."
"HEV_DET2"	"Warning: Hazardous radiation levels detected."
"HEV_DET1"	"Warning: Hazardous chemical detected."
"HEV_DET0"	"Warning: Biohazard detected."
"HEV_AMO0"	"Ammunition depleted."

//Nihilanth
"nil_thieves"	"Thieves... you all are thieves... you all are..."

//Gina and Colette
"gina_attack0"	"I'll take 'em."
"gina_attack1"	"We've got trouble."
"gina_attack2"	"Hostiles!"
"gina_attack3"	"I'm going in."
"gina_attacked0"	"I'm hit!"
"gina_attacked1"	"I'm taking damage!"
"gina_attacked2"	"Incoming!"
"gina_attacked3"	"Cover me."
"gina_kill0"	"One down!"
"gina_kill1"	"Got 'em!"
"gina_kill2"	"Target down!"
"gina_kill3"	"Got one!"
"gina_kill4"	"Dropped one!"
"gina_mad0"	"Be careful!"
"gina_mad1"	"Hey, watch it!"
"gina_mad2"	"Friendly fire!"
"gina_stop0"	"I'm not moving another step."
"gina_stop1"	"I'm staying here."
"gina_stop2"	"I can't go on any further."
"gina_unuse0"	"I won't move from this point."
"gina_unuse1"	"I'll be right here."
"gina_unuse2"	"I'll wait here."
"gina_unuse3"	"I'll keep the area secure."
"gina_unuse4"	"Fine. I'll stay here."
"gina_use0"	"After you."
"gina_use1"	"I'm with you."
"gina_use2"	"Let's go."
"gina_use3"	"You lead the way."
"gina_use4"	"I'm right behind you."
"gina_use5"	"I'll keep you covered."
"colette_attack2"	"This is gonna be fun."
"colette_attacked0"	"This sucks."
"colette_attacked1"	"I'm taking damage."
"colette_attacked2"	"This isn't looking pretty."
"colette_attacked3"	"Cover me!"
"colette_kill0"	"Yeah!"
"colette_kill1"	"Gravy!"
"colette_kill2"	"Sweet!"
"colette_kill3"	"Ho yeah!"
"colette_kill4"	"Hah!"
"colette_mad0"	"Be careful!"
"colette_mad1"	"Excuse me!"
"colette_mad2"	"Watch where you aimin' that thing."
"colette_stop0"	"Sorry, can't go with you."
"colette_stop1"	"I can't go on any further."
"colette_stop2"	"Uh, I'm stuck."
"colette_unuse0"	"Fine. I'll stay here."
"colette_unuse1"	"I'm not going anywhere."
"colette_unuse2"	"Sure. I'll stay behind."
"colette_unuse3"	"Be here when you need me."
"colette_unuse4"	"All right. I'll stick around."
"colette_use0"	"What are we waiting for?"
"colette_use1"	"I'm trailing your tail."
"colette_use2"	"All right, let's move!"
"colette_use3"	"Let's go!"
"colette_use4"	"I'll keep you covered."
"colette_use5"	"Consider your ass covered."
}
}